<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="installing">
	<title>Installing Couchbase Server</title>
	<shortdesc>Couchbase Server 4.0 can be installed on Linux, Windows, or OS X systems.</shortdesc>

	<conbody>


		<section>
			<title>Downloading Couchbase Server</title>
			<p>If you haven't already downloaded Couchbase Server, get it now from the <b><xref
						href="http://www.couchbase.com/nosql-databases/downloads#PreRelease" format="html"
						scope="external">Couchbase Server downloads</xref></b> page.</p>

			<p>You can download Couchbase Server directly to a Linux system by using the
					<cmdname>wget</cmdname> command. The basic syntax of the <cmdname>wget</cmdname>
				command is:</p>
			<codeblock><synph><kwd>wget</kwd> [<var>option</var>]... [<var>url</var>]...</synph></codeblock>
			<p>For example, the following command downloads a version of Couchbase Server that runs on
				CentOS:</p>
			<codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ wget http://packages.couchbase.com/releases/4.0.0-dp/couchbase-server-enterprise-4.0.0-dp-centos7.x86_64.rpm</codeblock>
			<note type="tip">To find the URL to specify in the <cmdname>wget</cmdname> command, go to
				the download page and copy the download link for your specific operating system.</note>
			<p>If you do not download Couchbase Server directly to the server on which you want to
				install it, you need to transfer it to the server by some other means (for example, by
				using FTP).</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Installing on Red Hat or CentOS Linux systems</title>
			<p>To install on Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL) or CentOS Linux:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Log on to the server as root.</li>
				<li>
					<p>Back up the <filepath>/etc/rc.local</filepath> file:</p>
					<codeblock>$ sudo cp -p /etc/rc.local /etc/rc.local.`date +%Y%m%d-%H:%M`</codeblock>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>Disable transparent huge pages (THP) and THP defrag by adding the following lines
						to the <filepath>/etc/rc.local</filepath> file:</p>
					<codeblock outputclass="language-bash"># disable THP
if test -f /sys/kernel/mm/transparent_hugepage/enabled; then
  echo never > /sys/kernel/mm/transparent_hugepage/enabled
fi
 				
# disable THP defrag
if test -f /sys/kernel/mm/transparent_hugepage/defrag; then
   echo never > /sys/kernel/mm/transparent_hugepage/defrag
fi</codeblock>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>Enter the following command to install Couchbase Server, replacing
							<varname>couchbase-server-version.rpm</varname> with the name of the file you
						downloaded:</p>
					<codeblock>$ rpm --install <varname>couchbase-server-version.rpm</varname></codeblock>
					<p>Couchbase Server starts automatically after the installation completes.</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Installing on Debian or Ubuntu Linux systems</title>

			<p>To install on Debian or Ubuntu Linux:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Log on to the server as root.</li>
				<li>Enter the following command to install <xref
						href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/OpenSSL" format="html" scope="external"
						>OpenSSL</xref>, replacing <varname>version</varname> with a specific version
					number of
					OpenSSL:<codeblock>$ apt-get install libssl<varname>version</varname></codeblock></li>
				<li>
					<p>Enter the following command to install Couchbase Server, replacing
							<varname>couchbase-server-version.deb</varname> with the name of the file you
						downloaded:</p>
					<codeblock>$ dpkg -i <varname>couchbase-server-version.deb</varname></codeblock>
					<p>Couchbase Server starts automatically after the installation completes.</p>
				</li>

			</ol>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Installing on OS X systems</title>
			<p>To install on OS X:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Delete any previous installations of Couchbase Server either by using the command
					line or by dragging the Couchbase Server application to the Trash. </li>
				<li>Open a Terminal window and delete any application support files from previous
					installations:
					<codeblock>$ rm -rf ~/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase
$ rm -rf ~/Library/Application\ Support/Membase</codeblock></li>
				<li>Expand the downloaded zip file (if it didn't expand automatically) and open the
					folder. <p>The folder contains the Couchbase Server application and a
							<filepath>README.txt</filepath> file.</p></li>
				<li>Drag the <filepath>Couchbase Server</filepath> file to the
						<filepath>Applications</filepath> folder.</li>
				<li>
					<p>Start Couchbase Server by double-clicking the application icon.</p>
					<p>If you get a message that says you can't run Couchbase Server due to security
						restrictions, right-click the icon for Couchbase Server and choose
							<uicontrol>Open</uicontrol> from the pop-up menu.</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Installing on 64-bit Microsoft Windows systems</title>
			<p>To install on Microsoft Windows:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Double click on the downloaded executable file to start the installer.</li>
				<li>Follow the installer prompts.
				<ul>
					<li>If desired, you can change the installation location.</li>
					<li>If the default port is unavailable, the installer prompts you for a different
						port to use for server administration.</li>
					<li>When the installer asks if you want to increase the number of ephemeral ports,
						click <uicontrol>Yes</uicontrol>.</li>
				</ul></li>
				<li>After the installation is complete, restart Couchbase Server to apply the port changes.</li>
			</ol>
		</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
