<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
  
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="tryAQuery">
	
	<title>
		Try a Query
	</title>
	
	<shortdesc>
		Couchbase Server allows you to search for data interactively: the Couchbase Web Console
		provides a <i>Query Workbench</i>, at which you can compose and execute queries, and see
		the returned results.
	</shortdesc>
	
	<body> 
		
		<section>
			
			<title>
				Access the Query Workbench
			</title>
			
			<p>
				Left-click on the <uicontrol>Query</uicontrol> tab, located on the horizontal control-bar, near
				the top of the Couchbase Web Console:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryButton.png" id="query_button" align="left" width="100"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				This brings up the Query Workbench. 
			</p>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>
				Examine the Query Workbench
			</title>

			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryWorkbench.png" id="query_workbench" align="left" width="720"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				The workbench has three principal areas, which are:
			</p>
			
			<ul>
				<li>
					An upper panel, which features the prompt <codeph>Enter a query here</codeph>: and this is indeed
					where you will type your query. 
					
					<p>
						<!-- Vertical space -->
					</p>
					
				</li>
				
				<li>
					A <uicontrol>Bucket Analysis</uicontrol> panel, at the lower-left. This provides information on the
					buckets currently maintained by your system. Right now, it shows that just one exists; the
					bucket <codeph>travel-sample</codeph>. 
					
					<p>
						<!-- Vertical space -->
					</p>
					
				</li>
				
				<li>
					A <uicontrol>Results</uicontrol> panel, at the lower-right. This shows query-results; and provides
					a number of options for their display. To start with, you will use the default option, which is
					selectable by the <uicontrol>JSON</uicontrol> button, and duly displays results in JSON-format.
					
					<p>
						<!-- Vertical space -->
					</p>
					
				</li>
			</ul>
			
			<p>
				You will now use the Query Workbench to enter your first query.
			</p>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>
				Enter a Query
			</title>
			
			<p>
				In the upper panel, enter the following text:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/firstQuery.png" id="first_query" align="left" width="660"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				Note the mandatory use of <i>reverse quotes</i> around the bucket-name, <codeph>travel-sample</codeph>. Note
				also that you must terminate your query with a semi-colon.
			</p>
			
			<p>
				This query uses the Couchbase <b>N1QL</b> declarative query-language, which is specially defined for
				the querying of JSON documents. A basic N1QL query has three parts:
			</p>
			
			<ul>
				<li>
					<codeph>SELECT</codeph> &#8212; specifying the field or fields to be returned from each document
					
					<p>
						<!-- Vertical space -->
					</p>
					
				</li>
				
				<li>
					<codeph>FROM</codeph> &#8212; the data-bucket that is to be searched
					
					<p>
						<!-- Vertical space -->
					</p>
					
				</li>
				
				<li>
					<codeph>WHERE</codeph> &#8212; the conditions that the document must satisfy, for data to be returned
					
					<p>
						<!-- Vertical space -->
					</p>
					
				</li>
				
			</ul>
			
			<p>
				In your first query, then, you have specified that the <codeph>name</codeph> field of each document from
				the <codeph>travel-sample</codeph> bucket should be returned; provided that the value of the document's
				<codeph>call-sign</codeph> field is <codeph>MILE-AIR</codeph>.
			</p>
			
			<p>
				To execute your query, left-click on the <uicontrol>Execute</uicontrol> button, at the upper-left:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/executeButton.png" id="execute_button" align="left" width="100"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				Query-results now appear in the <uicontrol>Results</uicontrol> panel:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryResultsJSON.png" id="query_results_json" align="left" width="660"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				As you can see, a single document was found to match your specified criterion: which was the document
				whose <codeph>name</codeph> value is <codeph>40-Mile Air</codeph> (which is indeed the document you took an initial
				look at, during the previous stage of the <i>Getting Started</i> sequence).
			</p>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>
				Try Different Query-Options
			</title>
			
			<p>
				The Query Workbench allows you to display query-results in different ways. This can be better
				shown with a less restrictive query. Therefore, modify your previous query
				by removing the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause, as follows:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryNoWHERE.png" id="query_no_where" align="left" width="642"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				This modified query asks for the <codeph>name</codeph> value of every document in the <codeph>travel-sample</codeph>
				bucket, without exception. Again, left-click on the <uicontrol>Execute</uicontrol> button. The 
				<uicontrol>Results</uicontrol> panel now appears as follows:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryResultsJSONnoWHERE.png" id="query_results_json_no_where" align="left" width="660"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				The <uicontrol>Results Summary</uicontrol> horizontal bar, near the top of the UI, indicates that your query was
				indeed successful, and that 31,591 individual results were returned. Each returned result is a JSON document,
				within an array. Vertical scrolling is provided. Additionally, the UI provides different options for viewing 
				results, which are especially useful when
				result-sets are very large. These options can be selected by means of buttons, at the upper-left:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryDisplayButtons.png" id="query_display_buttons" align="left" width="180"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				Left-click on the <uicontrol>Table</uicontrol> button. The <uicontrol>Results</uicontrol> panel now appears
				as follows:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryResultsTable.png" id="query_results_table" align="left" width="660"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				And now, left-click on <uicontrol>Tree</uicontrol>:
			</p>
			
			<p>
				<image href="./images/queryResultsTree.png" id="query_results_tree" align="left" width="660"/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				You can continue to experiment with these options whenever you need a clearer view of the 
				result-set you have returned.
			</p>
			
			<p>
				Note that options for saving queries and results are also provided, by means of the <uicontrol>Save Query</uicontrol>
				and <uicontrol>Save JSON,</uicontrol> buttons. In each case, you are prompted for a filename, and the query or
				results-set is duly saved.
			</p>
				
		</section>
		
		<section>	
			
			<title>
				Next
			</title>
			
			<p>
				You can execute N1QL queries programmatically, as well as manually. This is demonstrated by means of
				an off-the-shelf code example in the next section,
				<xref href="./run-hello-world.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Run Hello World!</xref>.
			</p>
			
		</section>
		
		<section>
			
			<title>
				Other Destinations
			</title>
			
			<p>
				In this section, we've performed two very simple N1QL queries. In fact, the language provides
				the opportunity for queries that are far more complex, by means of extensive syntactic options. If you
				wish to investigate these right away, before running your first program, you can go to
				<xref href="../sdk/n1ql-query.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Querying with N1QL</xref>.
			</p>
			
			<p>
				As well as interactively specifying N1QL queries from the Query Workbench, you can also do so
				by means of <codeph>cbq</codeph>: this is an interactive shell-program, available in your
				Couchbase applications directory. For detailed information, see
				<xref href="../tools/cbq-shell.dita" scope="local" format="dita">cbq: The Command Line Shell for N1QL</xref>. 
			</p>

		</section>
		
	</body>
	
</topic>


	

