<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_g5j_djq_44">
	<title>Handling timeouts</title>
	<shortdesc>The SDK supports configuration options to control the various timeouts that you might want to override so you can fine-tune your applications.</shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>Internally the client uses a set of heuristics and accompanying logic to determine whether or
			not to retry operations if they fail with a timeout or to return a failure message to the
			calling application. In general, an application should not provide additional logic in the
			case that a timeout error is returned; however, it’s likely an indication that the
			application configuration may be in need of tuning or that perhaps a broader system or
			network level issue might be at play.</p>
	<section>
		<title>Client timeout configuration</title>
		<p>The following timeouts are configurable either through the <codeph>App.Config</codeph> or
					<codeph>Web.Config</codeph> or through the <apiname>ClientConfiguration</apiname> object
				itself: </p>
		<p>
					<table id="table_bx3_sf2_3p">
						<tgroup cols="3">
						<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1.29*"/>
						<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.88*"/>
						<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><codeph>OperationTimeout</codeph></entry>
								<entry>The amount of time to wait on a binary operation before timing out</entry>
								<entry>2,500 ms</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><codeph>ViewTimeout</codeph></entry>
								<entry>The amount of time to wait on a View query before timing
									out</entry>
								<entry>30,000 ms</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><codeph>QueryTimeout</codeph></entry>
								<entry>The amount of time to wait on a N1QL query before timing
									out</entry>
								<entry>30,000 ms</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><codeph>WaitTimeout</codeph></entry>
								<entry>The amount of time to wait for an available TCP connection
									before timing out</entry>
								<entry>2,500 ms</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><codeph>ObserveTimeout</codeph></entry>
								<entry>The amount of time to spend waiting for an Observe operation to meet its durability
									requirements before timing out</entry>
								<entry>500 ms</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><codeph>ShutdownTimeout</codeph></entry>
								<entry>The time between when the SDK closes a TCP connection and
									when it actually shuts down</entry>
								<entry>10,000 ms</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
					</table>
				</p>
		<p>Certain timeouts such as <codeph>ViewTimeout</codeph> and <codeph>QueryTimeout</codeph> can
				also be overridden on a per query basis. <note>In general, the default settings are
					sufficient for most applications—only after encountering issues should they be
					adjusted.</note></p>
	</section>
	</conbody>
</concept>
