<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_fd5_vcf_3w">
  <title>Deploying a Single Node Cluster</title>
  <shortdesc>To run a single node cluster, you need to deploy a single Couchbase Server container representing the single node.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>For deployments with Couchbase Server containers, use the Couchbase Docker images available on <xref href="https://hub.docker.com/_/couchbase/" scope="external" format="html">Docker Hub</xref>.</p> 
    <note>Before you begin, review the container requirements section for prerequisites and resource requirements for the containers.</note>
    <ol>
      <li>Start the Couchbase Server container, db, using the following command:
          <codeblock>docker run -d --name db -p 8091-8094:8091-8094 -p 11210:11210 couchbase</codeblock><p>This
          command downloads and runs the container tagged "latest" from the Couchbase repo on Docker
          Hub. </p><p>Check the Docker logs to verify that the container has started:
          <codeblock>docker logs db</codeblock> If the container is started, it should return the
          following output:
          <codeblock>Starting Couchbase Server -- Web UI available at http://&lt;ip&gt;:8091</codeblock></p><note>If
          Couchbase Server is running locally on the machine without containers, the port mappings
          specified using the <codeph>-p</codeph> option may fail. Ensure that you stop your local
          instance of Couchbase Server before running the above command.</note></li>
      <li>From the browser, access the Web Console using <filepath>http://localhost:8091</filepath>.
        If the container is up and running, you should see the Couchbase Server Setup Screen. <image
          placement="break" href="picts/setup-screen.png" width="570" id="image_rq4_sgg_3w"/></li>
      <li>Set up Couchbase Server. Walk through the Setup wizard and accept default values.<p>You
          may need to lower the RAM allocated to various services to fit within the bounds of the
          resource for the containers. Enable the `travel-sample` and `beer-sample` buckets to load
          some sample data. </p></li></ol>
    <p>This is all that is needed for a single node deployment of Couchbase Server. If you want to add nodes to your cluster, see <xref href="docker-deploy-multi-node-cluster.dita"></xref>.</p>
    <section><title>Running a N1QL Query</title>
      <p>Open the Web Console at <filepath>http://localhost:8091</filepath> and switch to the Query tab. Run the following N1QL query: <codeblock>SELECT name FROM `beer-sample` WHERE  brewery_id ="mishawaka_brewing";</codeblock></p>
      <p>To run a query from command line query tool: <ol>
        <li>Run the interactive shell on the container: <codeblock>bash -c "clear &amp;&amp; docker exec -it db sh"</codeblock></li>
        <li>Navigate to the <filepath>bin</filepath> directory: 
          <codeblock># cd /opt/couchbase/bin</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the <cmdname>cbq</cmdname> command line tool: <codeblock># ./cbq</codeblock></li>
        <li>Execute a N1QL query on the `beer-sample` bucket: <codeblock>cbq> SELECT name FROM `beer-sample` WHERE  brewery_id ="mishawaka_brewing";</codeblock>
        </li>
      </ol></p>
      <p>For more query samples, see <xref href="../getting-started/first-n1ql-query.dita"></xref>. </p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Connect via SDK</title>
      <p>Simply run your application through the Couchbase Server SDKs on the host and point it to <filepath>http://localhost:8091/pools</filepath> to connect to the container.</p>
      <p>For information on deploying a sample application to a container, see <xref href="../travel-app/index.dita"></xref>. </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
