<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ggq_hfy_p4">
  <title>Using Hostnames</title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    Each individual Couchbase Server-node can be referenced by a hostname, as
    well as by an IP address. You can specify a node's hostname by using either the
    Couchbase Web Console or the REST API, during the process of node-configuration
    and cluster-definition.
  </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Specifying a Hostname
      </title>

    <p>
      Initial configuration of Couchbase Server allows the node to be referenced by means of a default
      IP address: <codeph>127.0.0.1</codeph>. This option is provided 
      in the <uicontrol>Configure Server Hostname</uicontrol> panel, itself located
      on the <uicontrol>Configure Server</uicontrol>
      screen:
    </p>
    
    <p>
      <image href="./picts/configure-server-hostname.png" id="configure-server-hostname" align="left" width="560"/>
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Alternatively, you may choose to specify a different IP address, or a <i>hostname</i>.
      The hostname must be valid, and must ultimately resolve to a valid IP
      Address. 
    </p>
      
    <p>
      If you restart a node, Couchbase Server continues to use the specified hostname. 
      Note, however, that if you fail over, or remove the node from a cluster, Couchbase Server 
      will no longer use the specified hostname: therefore, in such circumstances, you 
      must reconfigure the node, in order to <i>re-specify</i> the hostname.
    </p>
      
    <p>
      You can specify a hostname when performing initial configuration of Couchbase Server; when adding a node 
      to an existing cluster; or <i>before</i> adding a node to a cluster, by means of a REST API call.
      Each of these options is described below.
    </p>
      
    </section>
   
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Provide a Hostname on Initial Configuration
      </title>
      
      <p>
        In the <uicontrol>Configure Server Hostname</uicontrol> panel, near the bottom of the
        <uicontrol>Configure Server</uicontrol> screen, you can enter either a
        hostname or a specific IP address into the interactive text-field. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="../admin/picts/cluster-setup-host.png" id="image_cwm_4rd_dt" align="left" width="560"/>
      </p>
    
    </section> 
   
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Provide a Hostname while Adding a Node
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Nodes can be added to a cluster by means of the <uicontrol>Server Nodes</uicontrol> tab, visible on
        the horizontal top control-bar provided by Couchbase Web Console. This displays the <uicontrol>Servers</uicontrol>
        screen, on which the <uicontrol>Add Server</uicontrol> button is located. Left-click on this button to
        display the following dialog:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="picts/upgrade-online-02.png" id="image_yxs_y3f_zs" align="left" width="500"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Enter a hostname (instead of an IP address) into the interactive <uicontrol>Server IP Address</uicontrol> 
        text-field.
      </p>
      
    </section>
  
    <section>
      <title>
        Provide a Hostname using the REST API
      </title>
      
      <p>
        The REST API provides the endpoint <codeph>/node/controller/rename</codeph>, which can
        be used to specify a hostname <i>before</i> the node has been added to a cluster. For example:
      </p>
      
      <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">curl -v -X POST -u Administrator:adm1npwd \
http://127.0.0.1:8091/node/controller/rename -d hostname=shz.localdomain</codeblock>
        
      <p>
        Note that if the node is already part of a cluster, Couchbase Server rejects the request; returning
        the following error:
      </p>
        
      <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">error 400 reason: unknown ["Renaming is disallowed for nodes that are 
already part of a cluster"]</codeblock>
    
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>
        Hostname Errors
      </title>

      <p>
        If the hostname you specify is invalid, or has been specified at an inappropriate point in the configuration
        or node-addition sequence, an error is returned. The following are examples of errors that you might
        encounter:
      </p>
      
      <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">Could not resolve the host name. The host name you provide as a parameter
does not resolve to a IP address.

Could not listen. The host name resolves to an IP address, but no network
connection exists for the address.
        
Could not rename the node because name was fixed at server start-up.

Could not save address after rename.

Requested name host name is not allowed. Invalid host name provided.

Renaming is disallowed for nodes that are already part of a cluster.</codeblock>

      </section>
         
  </body>
  
</topic>
