<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ggq_hfy_p4">
  <title>Using hostnames</title><shortdesc>Each Couchbase Server's instance can have its hostname.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>When you first install Couchbase Server, you can access it using a default IP address.
      However, in some cases you might want to provide a hostname for each instance of a server.
      Each hostname you provide must be a valid one and will ultimately resolve to a valid IP
      Address. If you restart a node, it will use the hostname once again. If you failover or remove
      a node from a cluster, the node needs to be configured with the hostname once again.</p>
      
      <p>There are several ways you can provide hostnames: <ul>
        <li>When installing a Couchbase Server on a machine.</li>
        <li>When adding a node to an existing cluster for an online upgrade.</li>
        <li>Using a REST API call.</li>
      </ul> Couchbase Server stores the hostnames in a configuration file on the disk.</p>
   
    <section><title>Provide hostname on initial setup</title>In the first screen, provide either a
      hostname or IP address under <wintitle>Configure Server Hostname</wintitle>. <p>The provided
        hostname survives node restart.</p><p><image href="../admin/picts/cluster-setup-host.png"
          id="image_cwm_4rd_dt" align="left" width="720"/></p></section> 
   
    <section><title>Provide hostname while adding a node</title>If a new node is being added to an
      existing 2.0.1 or earlier Couchbase Server cluster, first set up the hostname for the new node
      in the setup wizard. <p>Add a new node to a cluster by providing either a hostname or IP
        address under <menucascade>
          <uicontrol>Add Server</uicontrol>
          <uicontrol>Server IP Address</uicontrol>
        </menucascade>.</p>
      <p><image href="picts/upgrade-online-02.png" id="image_yxs_y3f_zs" align="left"/></p>
    </section>
  
    <section><title>Provide hostname via REST API</title>Provide a hostname for a node a hostname
      with the REST request at the <filepath>/node/controller/rename endpoint</filepath>. <p>Provide
        the hostname before adding a node to a cluster. If the node is already part of a cluster,
        Couchbase Server rejects the request and returns an
        error:<codeblock>error 400 reason: unknown ["Renaming is disallowed for nodes that are already part of a cluster"]</codeblock><codeblock>curl -v -X POST -u Administrator:asdasd \
http://127.0.0.1:8091/node/controller/rename -d hostname=shz.localdomain</codeblock></p></section>
      
      <section><title>Hostname errors</title>
      <p>Provide the hostname and port for the node and administrative credentials for the
        cluster. The value you provide for <codeph>hostname</codeph> must be a valid hostname for
        the node. Possible errors that can occur:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><systemoutput>Could not resolve the host name. The host name you provide as a parameter does not
          resolve to a IP address.</systemoutput></li>
        <li><systemoutput>Could not listen. The host name resolves to an IP address, but no network connection
          exists for the address.</systemoutput></li>
        <li><systemoutput>Could not rename the node because name was fixed at server start-up.</systemoutput></li>
        <li><systemoutput>Could not save address after rename.</systemoutput></li>
        <li><systemoutput>Requested name host name is not allowed. Invalid host name provided.</systemoutput></li>
        <li><systemoutput>Renaming is disallowed for nodes that are already part of a cluster.</systemoutput></li>
      </ul>
      </section>
         
      
  </body>
  
</topic>
