<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_ttw_pbp_ts">
 <title>Security considerations</title>
 <shortdesc>You should keep in mind security best practices before and after you install Couchbase Server.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  <p>Security is important for every line of business. By following a few best practices, you can avoid many security vulnerabilities. 
   This topic discusses some security best practices that you should consider before and after you install Couchbase Server. </p>
 <p>While you are setting up your server environment, be sure to do the following:</p>
   
  <dl>
   <dlentry>
    <dt>Enhance physical security</dt>
    <dd>To enhance physical security of your Couchbase clusters, following are couple of things that
     you might consider: <ul>
      <li>Ensure that only authorized personnel have physical access to the Couchbase servers.</li>
      <li>Do not directly connect your Couchbase servers to the Internet. Instead put your database
       behind a firewall. </li>
      <li>Backup all data regularly and secure the backups in an off-site location. </li>
     </ul></dd>
   </dlentry>
  </dl> 

  
  <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Use a firewall</dt>
     <dd>Firewall offers a layer of defense against external threats and should be put in place to safeguard the perimeters of your deployment.</dd>
     <dd>
      Guidelines for using firewalls with Couchbase Server are:
     <ul>
      <li>Put the firewall between the Internet and your Couchbase cluster, and enable it.
      <!-- <note type="note">The highest level of security will be achieved if you put the application servers and
        Couchbase servers on separate networks and have a two-tiered system. In this case you will
        have a firewall between the internet and your application servers and  another firewall
        between your application servers and the Couchbase servers.</note>--></li>
      
      <li>When designing web applications with a multi-tier architecture in mind, use firewalls 
       to segment the network layers appropriately, 
       and place your database server at the inner data storage layer. 
       First, block all traffic through the firewall, 
       and then selectively admit only what is required.</li>
     </ul></dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
   
   <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Isolate and secure services</dt>
     <dd>You can isolate your data, index and query services, so that if one server is compromised, 
      others are not. Make sure that you apply the latest OS patches to secure your operating system you are running on.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
   
   <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Secure the file system</dt>
     <dd>You might also want to consider encrypting your file system to ensure that only authorized
          processes and users can get access. There are a number of third-party libraries available
          that can be used to transparently encrypt data in Couchbase without any application
          changes. See <xref href="../security/security-intro.dita#concept_kx3_kkf_xp"/>for more
          information.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
   
  
 </conbody>  
   
</concept>
