<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
  
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="ipv6-setup">
  
<title>Using IPv6 With Couchbase</title>
  
  <shortdesc> Couchbase Server supports IP version 6 (IPv6). Set-up is required for each platform. </shortdesc>
  
<body>
    <note type="attention">IPv6 support is only available in Couchbase Server Enterprise
      Edition.</note> 
  
  <section id="ipv6-overview">
      <title>IPv6 Overview </title>
      <p>By default, when Couchbase Server starts up it uses IPv4. To enable IPv6, set-up is
        required for each platform, as described in the sections below. Note that the steps for
        Linux and macOS are to be performed <i>after</i> the basic Couchbase Server installation is
        complete, and the steps for Windows are integrated into the basic installation procedure
          itself.<note>In a clustered setup, IPv6 is enabled only when IPv6 is enabled on all of the
          nodes.</note></p>
      <p> See <xref href="install-intro.dita#topic_edn_wtd_54"/> for more information about
        installation procedures. </p>
    </section>
  
  <section id="linux-ipv6-setup">
    
    <title>IPv6 Set-Up for Linux </title>
    
    <p>After the Couchbase Server package has been installed, the <codeph>couchbase</codeph> service
        is started by default. To enable IPv6, proceed as follows:</p>
    
    <ol>
    
    <li>Stop the <codeph>couchbase-server</codeph> service.</li>
      
    <li>In <codeph>/opt/couchbase/etc/couchbase/static_config</codeph>, set <codeph>ipv6</codeph> to
            <codeph>true</codeph>.</li>
      
    <li>Delete <codeph>/opt/couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/config/config.dat</codeph>.</li>
      
    <li>Restart the <codeph>couchbase-server</codeph> service (this starts Couchbase Server in IPv6
          mode). To check, point a supported web browser to  <codeph>http://[::1]:8091</codeph>,
          which is the IPv6 address and port number on which Couchbase Server should be
          running.</li>     
    </ol>
  </section>
  
  <section id="windows-ipv6-setup">
    
    <title>IPv6 Set-Up for Windows </title>
    
    <p>IPv6 set-up requirements are incorporated into the InstallShield wizard itself. During
        installation of the Couchbase package, a check box is available to enable IPv6 mode. (Note
        that after installation, any subsequent mode-change requires re-installation.) </p>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="macos-ipv6-setup">
    
    <title>IPv6 Set-Up for macOS </title>
    
    <p>After you install the Couchbase Server application, proceed as follows: </p>
    
    <ol>
    <li>Ensure that the <codeph>couchbase-server</codeph> service is stopped. (Quit the Couchbase
          Server application if it is running.)</li>
    
    <li>In <codeph>/Applications/Couchbase\
            Server.app/Contents/Resources/couchbase-core/etc/couchbase/static_config.in</codeph>,
          set <codeph>ipv6</codeph> to <codeph>true</codeph>.</li>
    
    <li>Delete <codeph>~/Library/Application\
            Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/config/config.dat</codeph>.</li>
      
    <li>Restart the <codeph>couchbase-server</codeph> service (this starts Couchbase Server in IPv6
          mode). To check, point a supported web browser to  <codeph>http://[::1]:8091</codeph>,
          which is the IPv6 address and port number on which Couchbase Server should be
          running.</li>
      
    </ol>
    
  </section>
  
</body>

</topic>
