<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_axp_glg_xs">
  <title>General considerations</title> <shortdesc>Evaluate the overall 
    performance and capacity requirements and determine the hardware and other resources.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>You have to consider many variables when sizing a cluster, but the basic task is 
      to evaluate the overall performance and capacity requirements for 
      your workload and dataset and then allocate the sufficient hardware and 
      other resources. The sizing of your Couchbase cluster is critical to its stability and performance.  
      Your application wants as many reads as possible coming out of cache as well as the I/O capacity to handle its writes.  
      There needs to be enough capacity 
      in all the various areas to support everything else the system is doing while 
      maintaining the required level of performance.
    </p>
    <p>These guidelines refer to these five determining factors one should be aware of when sizing a
      Couchbase cluster: RAM, disk I/O, disk space, CPU, and network bandwidth.</p>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>RAM</dt>
        <dd>RAM is what enables Couchbase to be so fast and is frequently one of the most crucial areas to size correctly.  
          Cached documents allow reads to be served at very low latency and high throughput, and available RAM does the same for writes.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Disk size</dt>
        <dd>Disk size refers to the amount disk storage space that is needed to hold your entire
          data set. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Disk I/O</dt>
        <dd>Disk I/O is a combination of your sustained write rate, the need for compacting the database files and anything else that requires disk access.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>CPU</dt>
        <dd>CPU refers to the number of cores required to run your workload. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Network</dt>
        <dd>In most situations, the network is not the determining factor for sizing a Couchbase
          cluster. However, it is always important to understand what is going on at the network
          level. You must ensure that there is enough bandwidth between your application and the
          Couchbase nodes as well as between nodes themselves to serve the traffic. With XDCR, it’s
          also important to ensure there is enough bandwidth between clusters, which are often
          spread geographically over a WAN. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
  </body>
</topic>
