<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_axp_glg_xs">
  <title>General considerations</title> <shortdesc>Evaluate the overall 
    performance and capacity requirements and determine the hardware and other resources.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The sizing of your Couchbase cluster is absolutely critical to its overall stability and performance. 
      While there are obviously many variables that go into this, 
      the idea is to evaluate the overall performance and capacity requirements for your workload and dataset. 
      Then divide that into the hardware and resources you have available. 
      Your application wants the majority of reads coming out of cache, and the I/O capacity to handle its writes.  
      There needs to be enough capacity in all areas to support everything the 
      system is doing while maintaining the required level of performance.
    </p>
    <p>This guideline will refer to five determining factors one should be aware of when sizing a Couchbase cluster: 
      RAM, Disk (I/O and space), CPU and network bandwidth.</p>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>RAM</dt>
        <dd>Frequently one of the most crucial areas to size correctly. 
          Cached documents allow reads to be served at very low latency and consistently high throughput.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Disk</dt>
        <dd>The requirements of your disk subsystem are broken down into two components: size and I/O.
           </dd>
        <dd>Disk size refers to the amount disk storage space that needed to hold your entire data set.</dd>
        <dd>Disk I/O is a combination of your sustained read/write rate, the need for compacting the database files and anything else that requires disk access.</dd>
      
      </dlentry>  
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>CPU</dt>
        <dd>CPU refers to the number of cores required to run your workload. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Network</dt>
        <dd>Enough network bandwidth is vital to the performance of Couchbase Server. 
          A reliable high speed network for intra-cluster and inter-cluster communications has a huge effect on overall 
          performance and scalability of Couchbase. Most people can do this with a 1GB interface, some need 10GB.
        </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <p>In the following sections, sizing guidelines for different services are discussed. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
