<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_y23_jjv_xs">
  <title>Upgrade Options</title><shortdesc>Upgrade a Couchbase Server cluster in a manner that is best suited to your operations.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    
    <p>Couchbase Server can be upgraded in multiple ways each with their own pros and cons. 
      Which way is best for your cluster will depend on a few factors in your architecture and company organization (e.g. SLAs). 
      On this and subsequent pages of this section we will discuss not just the mechanics of an upgrade, but why each may or may work best for you.</p>   
    
    <section><title>Option #1 - Rolling Online Upgrade</title>
      <p>A rolling online upgrade is the recommended upgrade process for a Couchbase Server cluster and should be chosen unless you 
        have special circumstances that would rule it out. As an online upgrade, this method avoids downtime for the database and 
        applications because all data operations continue normally throughout the process. Rolling upgrades involve using the 
        rebalance feature of Couchbase to redistribute the data amongst the nodes in the cluster running the Data Service, 
        thus keeping the data accessible for the duration of the upgrade. As long as you keep some nodes from the Index and Query Services</p>  
      <p>As Couchbase Server is specifically designed to provide fully online upgrades 
        If you find this is not the case, please report a bug.</p>
      <p>There are three options for rolling online upgrades:</p> 
      
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Swap Rebalance</dt>
          <dd>This method entails introducing new nodes into a Couchbase Server cluster as you remove an equal number of nodes to be upgraded. 
            It uses a feature called Swap Rebalance to move vBuckets efficiently 
            from an existing node running the Data Service to a new node that will run the Data Service, without involving other nodes in the cluster. 
          </dd>
          <dd>As long as you swap an equal number of nodes (e.g. one for one, two for two, etc.), a Swap Rebalance will be used. 
            This also keeps the cluster capacity consistent so as to not interfere with the load running on the cluster.
            
            While this method is the safest and provides the most availability, one downside to this option is the overall duration of a 
            cluster upgrade may be longer as compared to other options. 
            If the speed of an upgrade is a primary concern for your cluster, as it might be if you have a tight maintenance window, see <xref
              href="../clustersetup/setup-failover-graceful.dita#topic_ysk_ycm_zs">Graceful
              Failover</xref> or <xref href="upgrade-offline.dita#topic_q11_1my_p4"/>.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Regular Rebalance</dt>
          <dd>This method is suitable when you must complete the upgrade using only the nodes currently in the cluster. 
            It involves removing at least one running node from the cluster, 
            upgrading the node, and then adding it back in. This upgrade method reduces the capacity of the cluster during the upgrade process.</dd>
          <dd>Like a swap rebalance upgrade, this style will require multiple rebalances to
            complete.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>  
      <dl>
        <dlentry id="graceful">
          <dt>Graceful Failover</dt>
          <dd>This option involves performing a rolling online upgrade using a <xref
              href="../clustersetup/setup-failover-graceful.dita#topic_ysk_ycm_zs">Graceful
            Failover</xref> instead of the full addition and removal of nodes in option #1. 
            It is typically faster and less resource intensive because vBuckets do not need to be moved between nodes. 
            With this process, there is a cluster rebalance but it is only to synchronize the vBuckets on the upgraded 
            node when each node returns to the cluster. 
            Another advantage compared to the other online upgrades is that this method preserves the global secondary 
            indexes and doesn’t need to rebuild them. </dd>
          <dd>The primary downside to this option is increased risk as replicas are used for faster failover and not recreated 
            until a rebalance occurs. This option is not available when choosing to upgrade with net-new systems 
            (as in the case of many cloud deployments) since those new nodes would not have the previous nodes’ 
            data in place. Use Option #1 when upgrading with net-new systems.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      
    </section>
    <section><title>Option #2 - Upgrade Using Intercluster Replication</title>
      <p>For this option, another Couchbase Server cluster is created or already exists and then
        intercluster replication is enabled via the Cross Datacenter Replication (<xref
          href="../xdcr/xdcr-intro.dita#topic1500">XDCR</xref>) built-in feature of Couchbase
        Server. The administrator then transitions the application to use the new cluster as part of the upgrade process. 
        While this upgrade process is relatively straightforward  to set up, it  requires more investment in servers/instances and networking, 
        as well as a change to the application so that it uses the newly upgraded cluster. It is best used when an administrator needs an 
        immediate rollback position or does not want to tinker with the original cluster for some reason. 
        This method is recommended when an existing XDCR connection is already in place.
      </p>  
      <p>Some people modify their application, to make this can be a zero downtime upgrade by having
        their application aware of both clusters and can failover between them automatically. If you
        do this, keep in mind that unlike regular operations against the Data Service, XDCR is
        eventually consistent. Most people treat this as an offline upgrade and will roll the
        application over with the new cluster configurations. Which solution is best will depend on
        your SLA requirements. </p> 
      
    </section>
    <section id="offline"><title>Option #3 - Offline Upgrade</title>
      <p>Choose an offline upgrade when the situation calls for an easy and fast upgrade method as well as when the database can incur a controlled outage. 
        The offline upgrade is more likely to succeed in situations where an online upgrade option might fail, but also the rare time a cluster is unstable 
        and has been determined that a Couchbase Server upgrade will fix a specific issue.</p>
      <p>The offline upgrade is the best choice in situations where an online upgrade option might fail, such as the rare times a cluster 
        is unstable and it has been determined that an upgrade will fix the issue.</p>
      
      
    </section>
    <section><title>Choosing the Upgrade Strategy</title>
      
      <p>Both the online and offline upgrade processes have trade-offs. The following table
      illustrates some important aspects of the two upgrade strategies.</p>
    <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_shv_yr2_zs">
      <title>Differences between online and offline upgrades</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feature</entry>
            <entry>Online upgrade</entry>
            <entry>Offline upgrade</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Applications remain available</entry>
            <entry>Yes</entry>
            <entry>No</entry>
           
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cluster stays in operation</entry>
            <entry>Yes</entry>
            <entry>No</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cluster must be shut down</entry>
            <entry>No</entry>
            <entry>Yes</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Typically required steps</entry>
            <entry>Rebalance, upgrade, rebalance per node</entry>
            <entry>All cluster nodes are upgraded at once.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
   <note type="important">Mac OSX does not support a direct upgrade. When upgrading on this
      platform, first back up your data and perform a clean uninstall of the old version. Once you
      install the new version, restore the data back to the new cluster.</note> </section>
  </body>
</topic>
