<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_sv3_pyp_fp">
  <title>Backup and restore</title>
  <shortdesc>Back up your entire cluster periodically to minimize data inconsistency when a restore
    is required.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Backing up your data should be a regular process on your cluster to ensure that
    you do not lose information in the event of a serious hardware or installation
    failure.</p>
    
    <p>There are a number of methods for performing a backup:</p>
<<<<<<< HEAD
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Using <cmdname>cbbackup</cmdname></dt>
        <dd>The <cmdname>cbbackup</cmdname> command enables you to back up a single node, single
          buckets, or the entire cluster into a flexible backup structure, which can restore the
          data into the same, or different, clusters and buckets. All backups can be performed on a
          live cluster or node. The command <cmdname>cbbackup</cmdname> is the most flexible and
          recommended backup tool.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Using file copies</dt>
        <dd>A running or offline cluster can be backed up by copying the files on each node. With
          this method, you can only restore to a cluster with the identical configuration.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
=======
    <ul>
      <li>Using <xref href="../cli/cbbackup-tool.dita#cbbackup-tool"/>, <xref
          href="../cli/cbrestore-tool.dita#cdbrestore-tool"/>, and <xref
          href="../cli/cbbackup-wrapper.dita#topic_r3f_422_dt"/>.</li>
      <li>Using  <xref href="../cli/backup-restore/br-howtodo.dita#topic_zqt_fnf_z5"/>.</li>
      <li>Using file copies. A running or offline cluster can be backed up by copying the files on each node. With
        this method, you can only restore to a cluster with the identical configuration.</li>
    </ul>
  
 
>>>>>>> f02991819b4e4029cd336f1117de1bbc95146f44
    <note type="note">Due to the active nature of Couchbase Server, it is impossible to create a
      complete in-time backup and snapshot of the entire cluster. Because the data is always being
      updated and modified, it is impossible to take an accurate snapshot.</note>
    
    <note type="note">You must back up and restore your entire cluster to minimize any data
      inconsistencies. Couchbase is always per-item consistent but does not guarantee total cluster
      consistency or in-order persistence.</note>
    
  </body>
</topic>
