<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_plr_jwp_yn">
	<title>Incremental backup and restore</title>
	<shortdesc>Incremental backup and restore enables administrators to back up quickly only the
		modified data in the database, making backup and restore more efficient for larger data
		sets.</shortdesc>


	<conbody>
		<note type="attention">This feature is available only for the Enterprise edition of Couchbase
			Server.</note>
		<p>The purpose of an incremental backup is to back up only the data that has changed since the
			previous backup. Incremental backups provide the following benefits:</p>
		
		<ul>
			<li>More options for backup strategies.</li>
			<li>Greater flexibility in the restoration process.</li>
			<li>Reduce the amount of time needed for daily backups.</li>
			<li>Reduce the amount of disk storage needed for backups.</li>
			<li>Reduce bandwidth usage when backing up over a network.</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>When you need to recover data, the restoration process uses the last full backup and one or
			more incremental backups. You can restore data either beginning with a specified date or ending with a specified date. 
		For more information, see the Couchbase CLI <xref href="../CLI/cli-increment-backup.dita">cbbackup</xref> and 
			<xref href="../CLI/cli-incremental-restore.dita">cbrestore commands</xref>.
		</p>		
		
			<p>In addition to full backups, Couchbase Server offers the following types of incremental backups:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Differential incremental backup</li>
				<li>Cumulative incremental backup</li>
			</ul>

		<section>
			<title>Differential incremental backup</title><p>Differential incremental backups
				contain only the database changes that occurred since the last backup. Differential
				backups are created quickly because less data is backed up, but restorations from
				differential backups take longer than restorations from cumulative incremental
				backups. </p><p>The following figure shows an example of a differential incremental
				backup strategy. Every Sunday, a full backup is made. On the other days of the week,
				a differential incremental backup is made.</p>
			<p><image href="../admin/picts/backup-differential-incremental.jpg"
					id="image_jm5_td2_dt" align="left" width="720"/></p>In this example, the Monday
			backup contains the changes made since the full backup on Sunday, the Tuesday backup
			contains the changes made since the Monday backup, the Wednesday backup contains the
			changes made since the Tuesday backup, and so on. For example, a restore operation
			performed on Wednesday uses the full backup from Sunday and the differential incremental
			backups from Monday and Tuesday.</section>

		<section>
			<title>Cumulative incremental backup</title><p>Cumulative incremental backups contain
				all changes that occurred since the last full backup. Restorations from cumulative
				backups are faster than restorations from differential backups, but cumulative
				backups require a longer backup window and use more disk space than differential
				backups.</p><p>The following figure shows an example of a cumulative incremental
				backup strategy. Every Sunday, a full backup is made. On the other days of the week,
				a cumulative incremental backup is made. </p>
			<p><image href="../admin/picts/backup-cumulative-incremental.jpg" id="image_y2y_yd2_dt"
					align="left" width="720"/></p>
			<p>In this example, the Monday backup contains all the changes made since the full backup on
				Sunday, the Tuesday backup contains all the changes made since the full backup on
				Sunday, the Wednesday backup contains all the changes made since the full backup on
				Sunday, and so on. For example, a restore operation performed on Wednesday uses the
				full backup from Sunday and the cumulative incremental backup from Tuesday. </p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Combining incremental backup
				types </title><p>For greater flexibility in the restoration process, your backup
				strategy can include a combination of differential and cumulative incremental
				backups.</p><p>The following figure shows an example of a backup strategy that
				incorporates both differential and cumulative backups. Every Sunday, a full backup
				is made. For the remainder of the week, depending on the day, either a differential
				or cumulative incremental backup is made.</p>
			
			<p><image href="../admin/picts/backup-combined-incremental.jpg" id="image_qpn_b22_dt"
					align="left" width="720"/></p><p>In this example, the backup schedule includes differential and cumulative incremental backups on
				different days. On Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday a differential
				incremental backup is made. On Thursday, a cumulative incremental backup is made.
				For example, a restore operation performed on Saturday uses the full backup from
				Sunday, the cumulative incremental backup from Thursday, and the differential
				incremental backup from Friday.</p>
		</section>

	</conbody>
</concept>
