<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_az5_djy_wr">
 <title>Server node information</title>
 <shortdesc>Server node-specific information includes the IP address, OS, Couchbase version and
  Memory and Disk allocation.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  <image href="../images/web-console-server-node.png" width="720" align="left"/>
  <section>
   <title>Node information</title>
   <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Server Name</dt>
     <dd>The server IP address and port number used to communicate with this server.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
   <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Uptime</dt>
     <dd>The uptime of the Couchbase Server process. This displays how long Couchbase Server has
      been running as a node, not the uptime for the server.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
   <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>OS</dt>
     <dd>The operating system identifier, showing the platform, environment, operating system and
      operating system derivative.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
   <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Version</dt>
     <dd>The version number of Couchbase Server installed and running on this node.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
  </section>
  <section><title>Memory cache</title> The Memory Cache section shows you the information about
   memory usage, both for Couchbase Server and for the server as a whole. You can use this to
   compare RAM usage within Couchbase Server to the overall available RAM. The specific details
   tracked are: <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Couchbase Quota</dt>
     <dd>Shows the amount of RAM in the server allocated specifically to Couchbase Server. </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>In Use</dt>
     <dd>Shows the amount of RAM currently in use by stored data by Couchbase Server.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Other Data</dt>
     <dd>Shows the RAM used by other processes on the server. </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Free</dt>
     <dd>Shows the amount of free RAM out of the total RAM available on the server. </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Total</dt>
     <dd>Shows the total amount of free RAM on the server available for all processes. </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl></section>
  <section><title>Disk Storage</title>This section shows the amount of disk storage available and
   configured for Couchbase. Information will be displayed for each configured disk. <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>In Use</dt>
     <dd>Shows the amount of disk space currently used to stored data for Couchbase Server. </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Other Data</dt>
     <dd>Shows the disk space used by other files on the configured device, not controlled by
      Couchbase Server. </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Free</dt>
     <dd>Shows the amount of free disk storage on the server out of the total disk space available.
     </dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl><dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Total</dt>
     <dd>Shows the total disk size for the configured storage device.</dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl>
  </section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
