<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_wqc_4rc_34">
  <title>Alerts</title><shortdesc>Enable to raise email alerts when a significant error occurs on your Couchbase
    Server cluster.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The email alert system works by sending an email directly to a configured SMTP server. Each
      alert email is sent to the list of configured email recipients to highlight specific issues
      and problems that you should be aware of and may need to check to ensure the health of your
      Couchbase cluster. Alerts are provided as a popup within the Couchbase Web Console.</p>
    <p>Select the  <uicontrol>Enable email alerts</uicontrol> checkbox to enable the configuration
      of email alerts, which are raised for the errors selected in the Available Alerts section.</p>
 
    <image href="../images/web-console-server-settings-alerts.png" align="left" width="720"/>
    <section>
      <title>Email Server Settings</title>
    </section>
    <p>The available settings are:</p>
    <table frame="all" id="table_server">
      <title>Email Server Settings</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Options</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Host</entry>
            <entry>The hostname of the SMTP server that will be used to send the email.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Port</entry>
            <entry>The TCP/IP port to be used to communicate with the SMTP server. The default is
              the standard SMTP port 25.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Username</entry>
            <entry>For email servers that require a username and password to send email, the
              username is used for authentication.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Password</entry>
            <entry>For email servers that require a username and password to send email, the
              password is used for authentication.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Require TSL</entry>
            <entry>Enable Transport Layer Security (TLS) when sending the email through the
              designated server.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <section>
      <title>Email Settings</title>
      <table frame="all" id="table_email_settings">
        <title>Email settings</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Sender email</entry>
              <entry>The email address identified as a source from which the email is sent. This
                email address should be one that is valid as a sender address for the SMTP server
                that you specify.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Recipients</entry>
              <entry>A list of the recipients of each alert message. To specify more than one
                recipient, separate each address by a space, comma, or semicolon.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Test Mail</entry>
              <entry>Click <uicontrol>Test Mail</uicontrol> to send a test email to confirm the
                settings and configuration of the email server and recipients.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Available Alerts</title>
      <p>You can enable individual alert messages that can be sent by using the series of check
        boxes. The supported alerts are:</p>
      <table frame="all" id="table_alerts">
        <title>Available alerts</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Alert</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>The node was auto-failed-over</entry>
              <entry>The sending node has been failed over automatically.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>The maximum number of auto-failed-over nodes was reached</entry>
              <entry>The auto-failover system stops auto-failover when the maximum number of spare
                nodes available has been reached.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>The node wasn't auto-failed-over as other nodes are down at the same
                time</entry>
              <entry>Auto-failover does not take place if there are no spare nodes within the
                current cluster.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>The node wasn't auto-failed-over as the cluster was too small (less than three
                nodes)</entry>
              <entry>You cannot support auto-failover with less than three nodes.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Node's IP address has changed unexpectedly</entry>
              <entry>The IP address of the node has changed, which may indicate a network interface,
                operating system, or other network or system failure.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Disk space used for persistent storage has reach at least 90% of
                capacity</entry>
              <entry>The disk device configured for storage of persistent data is nearing full
                capacity.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Metadata overhead is more than 50%</entry>
              <entry>The amount of data required to store the metadata information for your dataset
                is now greater than 50% of the available RAM.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Bucket memory on a node is entirely used for metadata</entry>
              <entry>All the available RAM on a node is being used to store the metadata for the
                objects stored. This means that there is no memory available for caching values.
                With no memory left for storing metadata, further requests to store data will also
                fail.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Writing data to disk for a specific bucket has failed</entry>
              <entry>The disk or device used for persisting data has failed to store persistent data
                for a bucket.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
