<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="dotnet-fle">
  <title>Field Level Encryption from the .NET SDK</title>
  <shortdesc>Field Level Encryption is available in Couchbase Data Platform 5.5, from .NET SDK version 2.6.0.</shortdesc>
  <conbody>
        <section id="package">
          <title>Packaging</title>
            <p>The Couchbase .NET SDK uses .NET Attributes to declaratively define which fields will be encrypted on a POCO (Plain Old CSharp Object) that matches the structure of your JSON document.</p>
            <p>Field Level Encryption (FLE) for .NET is available as a <xref href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption/" format="html" scope="external">NuGet package</xref> for download. The name of the package is <codeph>Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption</codeph>. Using the NuGet Package Manager, it can be installed using the following command:<codeblock>Install-Package Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption -Version 1.0.0-dp1</codeblock></p>

            <p>If you are using the .NET CLI, then it can be installed using this command:<codeblock>dotnet add package Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption --version 1.0.0-dp1</codeblock></p>

            <p>If you are using Visual Studio, just type <codeph>Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption</codeph> into the NuGet Package Manager search box; locate the package, and install it.
              <fig id="field_level_encryption--nuget.png">
                <title>Installing Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption via NuGET</title>
                <image placement="break" href="../shared/images/field_level_encryption--nuget.png" />
              </fig>
              This will also include the dependency on the Couchbase .NET SDK, which is required by the Field Level Encryption extension.</p>
        </section>


        <section id="configuration">
          <title>Configuring Field Level Encryption</title>
            <p>Once you have included the FLE package in your Visual Studio or CodeVS project, you’ll need to configure the SDK to use it. FLE 
              currently doesn’t allow for config file configuration; this has to be done programmatically using the <codeph>ClientConfiguration</codeph> 
              found in the <codeph>Couchbase.Configuration.Client</codeph> namespace. Note that all of code snippets below can be found in full in 
              our <xref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/devguide-examples/tree/master/dotnet" format="html" scope="external">devguide-examples repo</xref> 
              in GitHub.</p>

            <p>First, add the following namespaces to your code file:<codeblock>using System.Collections.Generic;
using Couchbase.Configuration.Client;
using Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption;
using Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption.Providers;
using Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption.Stores;</codeblock></p>

            <p>Then, add the configuration required to enable FLE to use the SDK:<codeblock>const string publicKey = "!mysecretkey#9^5usdk39d&amp;dlf)03sL";
const string publicKeyName = "publickey";
 
const string signingKey = "myauthpassword";
const string signingKeyName = "mysecret";
 
var keystore = new InsecureKeyStore(
      new KeyValuePair&lt;string, string>(publicKeyName, publicKey),
      new KeyValuePair&lt;string, string>(signingKeyName, signingKey));
 
var cryptoProvider = new AesCryptoProvider(keystore)
{
      PublicKeyName = publicKeyName,
      SigningKeyName = signingKeyName
};
 
var config = new ClientConfiguration();
config.EnableFieldEncryption(cryptoProvider); 
var cluster = new Cluster(config);</codeblock></p>

            <p>First the keystore is created with a public key and a signing key; the signing key is required for ensuring that the encrypted data or any part 
              of the message is not tampered with. Then an <codeph>AesCryptoProvider</codeph> instance is created which takes the keystore as a constructor parameter. Finally 
              the configuration is created and the extension method <codeph>EnableFieldEncryption</codeph> is called passing in the <codeph>ICryptoProvider</codeph> instance. Once this is done, 
              configuration is complete!
            </p>

            <p>Note, that this example uses the <codeph>InsecureKeyStore</codeph> class which is an in-memory keystore that stores the keys unprotected; this is fine for testing and examples, but for real world applications the <codeph>FileSystemKeyStore</codeph>, which uses the DAPI, is a better choice.</p>

            <p>Once we have setup our configuration, we’ll open a cluster and bucket object. Note that for a real-world application, you’ll want to tie the scope of both the cluster and the bucket to the lifespan of the application - see the <xref href="https://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/current/sdk/dotnet/managing-connections.html" format="html" scope="external">Managing Connections documentation</xref> for more information.</p>
        </section>


        <section id="fields">
          <title>Specifying what to Encrypt</title>
            <p>In order to specify which field to encrypt, a special .NET attribute is used to annotate a property on a POCO (Plain Old Csharp Object) For cross-sdk support, although any property on a POCO can be encrypted, this must be a root-level property.<codeblock>public class Person
{
      [EncryptedField(Provider = "AES-256-HMAC-SHA256")]
      public string Password { get; set; }
      public string FirstName { get; set; }
      public string LastName { get; set; }
      public string UserName { get; set; }
      public int Age { get; set; }
}</codeblock></p>

            <p>In the POCO above, we have a field which we wish to encrypt called <codeph>Password</codeph> which represents a person’s password. This 
               property is annotated with <codeph>EncryptedFieldAttribute</codeph> and the <codeph>ICryptoProvider.Provider</codeph> name we are using. 
               Note, this must match the type of <codeph>ICryptoProvider</codeph> we supplied in our configuration (“AES-256-HMAC-SHA256").
            </p>
        </section>


        <section id="storing-and-retrieving">
          <title>Storing and Retrieving Documents with Encrypted Fields</title>
            <p>Once this is done, it's simply a matter of using the basic CRUD operations that Couchbase supports to insert or fetch the document from the database. 
              For example, assuming a Person class annotated with the <codeph>EncryptedField</codeph> attribute on a Password property:<codeblock>var teddy = new Person
{
     Age = 33,
     FirstName = "Ted",
     LastName = "DeBloss",
     Password = "ssloBeD12345"
};

var bucket = cluster.OpenBucket();
var insert = bucket.Upsert("person::1", teddy);</codeblock></p>

<p>Retrieving a document with an encrypted field is no different than any other get assuming you use an annotated POCO:<codeblock>var get = bucket.Get&lt;Person>("person::2");
if (get.Success)
{
       Console.WriteLine("Fetched person...");
}</codeblock></p>

            <p>It's important to note that the data is encrypted for transport and storage only. When you retrieve the document the value for Password 
              will be in its unencrypted format.</p>
        </section>



  </conbody>
</concept>
