<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_alz_z1n_bw">
  <title>Handling Exceptions and Other Errors with the .NET SDK in Couchbase</title>
  <titlealts><navtitle>Handling Errors</navtitle></titlealts>
  <shortdesc>This section gives an overview of the kind of error handling a .NET program will want
    to consider, properties of results, and the kinds of exceptions you should plan to
    handle.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>How the SDK Handles Errors</title>
      <p>The .NET SDK generally handles errors in two ways: either by catching an internally thrown
        exception and returning it back the application tier as a property of the
          <apiname>IDocumentResult</apiname> or by throwing the exception with the expectation that
        the application will handle it. The general rule is if the error is scoped to an operation
        or query, then it's handled gracefully and returned as part of the response. If the error is
        scoped to the client internals and non-recoverable, then the exception is thrown to the
        application. An example of an error that is caught and returned as a property of the
        response would be an <codeph>OperationTimeoutException</codeph>. A non-recoverable error such as a
        <codeph>BootstrapException</codeph> would be thrown since the client cannot function without successfully
        bootstrapping to the server.</p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Useful Properties of IResult and its Derivatives</title><p>The
          <apiname>Document</apiname>, <apiname>Query</apiname> (N1QL) and <apiname>View</apiname>
        API methods all return results that inherit from a common interface: IResult. The IResult
        interface contains signatures for the following properties:<ul id="ul_dyj_xbn_gw">
          <li><b><apiname>Success</apiname></b>: returns a boolean value indicating whether the
            overall operation or request was successful or not.</li>
          <li><b><apiname>Message</apiname></b>: returns an optional message if
              <codeph>Success</codeph> was false - this may indicate the reason for the
            failure.</li>
          <li><b><apiname>Exception</apiname></b>: if <codeph>Success</codeph> was false an optional
            exception if one was generated.</li>
        </ul></p><p>The purpose of these properties is to provide information regarding the
        operation and if it was a failure, enough information to diagnose or handle the error within
        the application. For example, in the event of a failure, the application may decide to
        rethrow the exception up the stack or perhaps log the error and keep on going.<codeblock><![CDATA[var result = bucket.GetDocument("thekey");
if(!result.Success && result.Exception != null){
  throw result.Exception;
}]]></codeblock></p><p>There is also an interface that inherits <apiname>IResult</apiname> called
          <apiname>IResult&lt;T&gt;</apiname> which has a Value property of Type "T"; its purpose is
        for operations that retrieve a document from Couchbase. A good example would be
          <apiname>IBucket.GetDocument&lt;T&gt;(string id)</apiname> which retrieves a document from
        Couchbase and casts it to whatever you specify as T (assuming the document is compatible
        with whatever T is).</p><p>As mentioned previously, each SDK has its own
          <apiname>IResult</apiname> specification which extends the definition for its own
        domain-specific purpose. Query has an <apiname>IQueryResult&lt;T&gt;</apiname> and Views has an
          <apiname>IViewResult</apiname>. Since both of have IResult in the inheritance chain, they
        share implementations of the common properties above, plus much more.</p><image
        href="images/iresult-interface-inheritence.JPG" id="image_pyd_mwg_hw" align="center"
      /></section>
    <section><p>For more detail on each specific implementation, look within the section for each of the
        respective APIs: <xref href="document-operations.dita#document-operations-dotnet"
          >Document</xref>, <xref href="n1ql-queries-with-sdk.dita#java-n1ql">Query</xref>, <xref
          href="full-text-searching-with-sdk.dita#dotnet-fts">Full Text Search</xref> and <xref
          href="view-queries-with-sdk.dita#java-views">Views</xref>.</p></section>
    <section>
      <title>The Exception Types and Their Meanings</title>
      <p>As mentioned previously, the .NET SDK differentiates between throwing non-recoverable
        exceptions and returning recoverable exceptions as part of the IResult.Exception property.
        The following table defines each exception type in the SDK and the behavior of the client
        when it is encountered.<table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_i4n_rxg_hw">
          <title>Overview of .NET SDK Exceptions</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="newCol2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.42*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Name</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>BootstrapException</entry>
                <entry>The client failed to bootstrap for one more reasons. See Note below.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>AuthenticationException</entry>
                <entry>The client failed to authenticate - thrown along with BootstrapException. See
                  Note below.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ConfigException</entry>
                <entry>The client could not bootstrap for a given provider type. Client will
                  generally recover if a Memcached bucket.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>CouchbaseBootstrapException and BootstrapException</entry>
                <entry>An error occurred while bootstrapping the client on a Couchbase
                  bucket.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>BucketAlreadyOpenException</entry>
                <entry>An attempt to open a bucket that has already been opened.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>BucketNotFoundException</entry>
                <entry>A bucket was referenced that does not exist.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>DocumentMutationLostException</entry>
                <entry>If enhanced durability is enabled, indicates a non-recoverable state when
                  using an overload.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>InitializationException</entry>
                <entry>A failure occurred during initialization.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>NodeUnavailableException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown if a node in the cluster is not online to service a pending
                  request.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ReplicaNotConfiguredException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown if requested ReplicateTo value exceeds the number of configured
                  replicas on the Server.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ServiceNotSupportedException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown if a service (Data, Query, etc) is requested that is not supported or
                  configured on the cluster.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>BufferUnavailableException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when an available buffer cannot be obtained from the
                  BufferAllocator.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ConnectionUnavailableException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when an available IConnection cannot be obtained from the
                  IConnectionPool after a number of tries.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RemoteHostClosedException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when the remote host closes a connection.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RemoteHostTimeoutException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when an in-process operation times out.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>IndexAlreadyExistsException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when attempting to create an index that already exists.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>IndexDoesNotExistException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when an attempt is made to use an index that does not exist.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>PrepareStatementException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when the IQueryClient cannot prepare a non-adhoc statement on the
                  server.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>NullConfigException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when a node locator can not be found.  This generally indicates a
                  problem in the client internals.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ServerUnavailableException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown when the client representation of a remote host cannot be located to
                  fulfill a request.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UnsupportedAddressFamilyException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown if an IP cannot be resolved from a domain name.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>System.TimeoutException</entry>
                <entry>Thrown if a request cannot be fulfilled by the configured timeout.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table><note>both BootstrapException and AuthenticationException will nearly always be
          wrapped in a System.AggregateException.</note><note>not all exceptions are returned back
          to application or thrown - in many appropriate cases they are handled internally and
          logged. This should be considered when using a debugger to break on exceptions.</note></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
