<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="contact-couchbase">
  
  <title>
    Contact Couchbase
  </title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    Provide feedback, and get help with any problem you may encounter.
  </shortdesc>

  <body>
    <section id="options_for_making_contact">
      
      <title>
        Options for Making Contact
      </title>
      
      <p>
        You can get in touch with Couchbase in any of the following ways:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>Contact Couchbase Support</i>: If you are a customer of Couchbase Server <i>Enterprise Edition</i>,
            and have a support contract, you can log into the Couchbase Customer Support Portal, and so make
            contact with Couchbase staff-members, who will provide guidance and assist with any problems you
            are encountering. Email and phone support are also available.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>Participate in a Forum</i>: Multiple online forums are available, whereby you can post a 
            question, and get answers; both from Couchbase employees and from members of the Couchbase
            community of developers and administrators. 
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>Submit a ticket</i>: Couchbase lets you use <i>JIRA</i> software, to report issues as individual 
            <i>tickets</i>.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <p>
            <i>Submit documentation changes</i>: If you find errors in Couchbase documentation, you can
            make your own edits to the source; and directly submit your changes to the Couchbase documentation
            team.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
          
        </li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>
        Further details are provided below.
      </p>

    </section>
    
    <section id="contact_couchbase_support">
      
      <title>
        Contact Couchbase Support
      </title>
      
      <p>
        The
        <xref href="https://support.couchbase.com" scope="external" format="html">Couchbase Support Portal</xref> provides online
        support for all customers of Couchbase Server <i>Enterprise Edition</i> who have a support contract:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./images/supportal.png" id="supportal" align="left" width="420"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        You can also contact Couchbase Support by phoning +1-650-417-7500, or by sending email
        to <codeph>support@couchbase.com</codeph>.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="participate_in_a_forum">
      
      <title>
        Participate in a Forum
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Couchbase <i>Community Forums</i> let you share knowledge with
        developers, administrators, and Couchbase in-house experts. All forums can be accessed at
        <xref href="https://forums.couchbase.com" scope="external" format="html">forums.couchbase.com</xref>:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./images/forums.png" id="forums" align="left" width="620"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        To participate fully, you need to register: left-click on the <b>Sign Up</b> button, at the upper right.
        Then, to access individual forums, select from the <b>all categories</b> pull-down menu.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="submit_a_ticket">
      
      <title>
        Submit a Ticket
      </title>
      
        <p>
          If you have a JIRA account, you can submit tickets to Couchbase. When submitting, include all
          information that might be appropriate. For example:
        </p>
      
        <ul>
         
          <li>
            <p>
              A description of your environment (package installation, build number, operating system, etc).
            </p>
            
            <p>
            </p>

          </li>
            

          <li>
            <p>
              All steps required to reproduce the issue. This should include all relevant
              expression-names, parameters, flags, and values; with sample output in
              verbose mode from repeated executions, using different values.
            </p>
            
            <p>
              
            </p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <p>
              Logs from all cluster-nodes.
            </p>
          
             <p>
            
             </p>
          </li>
            
            
          <li>
            <p>
              Query-results from the command-line, when failures have occurred through use of the UI; and <i>vice versa</i>.
            </p>
            
            <p>
              
            </p>
          </li>
         
        </ul>
      </section> 
    
      <section id="submit_documentation_changes">
        
        <title>
          Submit Documentation Changes
        </title>
        
        <p>
          If you find a documentation-error, to fix it, you can left-click on the link at the upper right of each page:
        </p>
        
        <p>
          <image href="./images/editOnGitHub.png" id="edit_on_git_hub" align="left" width="120"/>
        </p>
        
        <p>
          This takes you to an interactive edit-pane, in which the page-source can be directly edited:
        </p>
        
        <p>
          <image href="./images/gitHubEditPane.png" id="git_hub_edit_pane" align="left" width="640"/>
        </p>
        
        <p>
          When you have made your edits, left-click on the <uicontrol>Commit changes</uicontrol> button,
          at the lower left:
        </p>
        
        <p>
          <image href="./images/commitChangesButton.png" id="commit_changes_button" align="left" width="200"/>
        </p>
        
        <p>
          This allows you to open a <i>pull request</i>, which will be reviewed by Couchbase staff-members, prior
          to integration of your submitted changes into the documentation-set.
        </p>
        
        
      </section>
    
  </body>
</topic>
