<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
	
<topic id="couchbase-editions">
	<title>Couchbase Server Editions</title>
	<shortdesc>Couchbase Server is available in several editions: enterprise, community, and open
		source. </shortdesc>

	<body><p>Each edition offers different features and levels of support. For more information on each feature, see the <xref href="#couchbase-editions/ee-vs-ce" format="dita">Enterprise and community edition feature matrix</xref>.</p>
<dl>
			<dlentry>
				<dt>Enterprise Edition</dt>
				<dd>The Enterprise edition (EE) represents the latest, most stable, production-ready release of
					Couchbase Server. We recommend the enterprise edition binaries for commercial
					production systems running Couchbase Server. The enterprise edition
					contains some unique features that make it the best fit for production
					deployments running in data centers or a public cloud infrastructure. These
					features, which are not available in the community edition, are listed in the
						<xref href="#couchbase-editions/ee-vs-ce" format="dita"/>. 
						Use of EE in development and test environments is free. EE requires a paid subscription for production use. Our <xref
						href="http://www.couchbase.com/subscriptions-and-support" format="html"
						scope="external">paid annual subscriptions</xref> for EE include a
					commercial license, better availability capabilities, enhanced security
					features, advanced tooling and higher performance and scale. It also includes
					technical support with service level commitments via our 24x7 support
					organization and hot fixes for releases.   
					One important principle for CE and EE is to ensure full portability of applications between two editions. The capabilities ensure that an application running on EE should simply transition to CE without code changes and visa versa.
					</dd>
			</dlentry>
			<dlentry>
				<dt>Community Edition</dt>
				<dd>The Community Edition (CE) is best for noncommercial developers where basic availability,
					performance, scale, tooling, security capabilities and community support is
					sufficient. CE comes free and there are no constraints on using these
					binaries in production systems. However, CE is not subjected to the iterative
					"test, fix, and verify" quality assurance cycle that is a part of the enterprise
					edition release process. The release version of CE is several months behind EE. CE
					also do not include the latest bug fixes. Documentation, mailing lists, and
					forums provide support for the Couchbase user community to help troubleshoot
					issues and answer questions. </dd>
			</dlentry>
			<dlentry>
				<dt>Open source project</dt>
				<dd>The Couchbase Server open source project is a platform for innovation. Couchbase is
					committed to open source development and the open source project continues to
					serve as the foundation for both the community edition and the enterprise
					edition. There are many ways to contribute to the open source project: You can contribute code to our core engine, to our SDKs, connectors and other integration components that help us connect to other products through <xref href="https://github.com/couchbase" format="html" scope="external">github.com/couchbase</xref>, you can report issues on our tracking system: <xref href="https://issues.couchbase.com/projects/MB?selectedItem=com.atlassian.jira.jira-projects-plugin:release-page"  format="html" scope="external">JIRA</xref> and contribute to documentation either through <xref href="http://github.com/couchbase/docs-cb4" format="html" scope="external">github.com/couchbase/docs-cb4</xref> or by simply clicking the "Feedback" link in our online documentation. The full details on contributing to open source can be found on the open source page <xref href="http://developer.couchbase.com/open-source-projects" format="html" scope="external">developer.couchbase.com/open-source-projects</xref>.</dd>
			</dlentry>
		</dl>

		<p>For a feature comparison between the editions, take a look at <xref
				href="https://www.couchbase.com/products/editions" format="html" scope="external"
				>https://www.couchbase.com/products/editions</xref>. </p>
	</body>

</topic>
