<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="couchbase-introduction">

	<title>Introduction to Couchbase Server</title>
	<shortdesc>Couchbase Server is an open source, distributed NoSQL document-oriented database. It
		exposes a fast key-value store with managed cache for submillisecond data operations,
		purpose-built indexers for fast queries and a query engine for executing SQL queries.  For
		mobile and internet of things environments, Couchbase Lite runs native on-device and manages
		sync to Couchbase Server. </shortdesc>

	<conbody>
		<p>Couchbase Server is specialized to provide low-latency data management for large-scale
			interactive web, mobile, and IoT applications. Common requirements that Couchbase Server
			was designed to satisfy include:</p>
		<ul><li>Flexible data model</li><li>Powerful query language</li>
			<li>Scalability</li>
			<li>Performance</li>
			<li>Simple administration</li>
			<li>High Availability</li></ul>

		<section><title>Flexible data model, dynamic schemas</title><p>Couchbase Server's flexible data
				model and dynamic schemas enable frequent improvements to applications without
				downtime or schema migrations. </p>Couchbase documents are JSON, a self-describing
			format capable of representing rich structures and relationships. Unlike a traditional
			RDBMS, the schema in Couchbase Server is a logical construct entirely defined in the
			application code and captured in the structure of the stored documents. Since there is
			no explicit schema to maintain, developers can add new objects and properties at any
			time just by pushing new application code that stores new JSON, without having to also
			having to make the same changes to the schemas. Because of this, applications can evolve
			quickly and seamlessly.</section>
		<section>
			<title>Powerful query language</title>
			<p>Couchbase Server can be queried by using N1QL, an expressive, powerful, and complete SQL
				dialect for querying, transforming, and manipulating JSON data. As SQL, it’s
				immediately familiar to developers, who can quickly get started developing rich
				applications. Unlike other NoSQL databases, Couchbase supports JOIN operations,
				which enables a wide range of data models. To help users develop rich applications
				with agility, N1QL is supported by a rich index infrastructure and also has
				extensions that allow it to handle heterogeneous documents with nested structures.
				N1QL is accessible to a full range of tools for analytics and data integration via
				JDBC and ODBC, such as Microsoft Excel, Tableau.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Submillisecond latencies at scale</title>
			<p>Couchbase Server is designed to process online operational data-heavy read and write traffic
				for large modern web, mobile, and IoT applications. For Couchbase Server, low
				latency at scale typically refers to consistent sub-millisecond reads and writes.
				While maximum raw speeds are important, many practitioners care more about being
				able to deliver those high speeds and low latencies with minimal variance during
				heavy workloads. Couchbase continues to deliver consistently high performance even
				under heavy load. Predictable, consistent performance guarantees responsiveness and
				improves the user experience in real-world deployments. </p>
			<p>Couchbase Server is a memory-centric system that intelligently keeps frequently
				accessed documents, metadata, and indexes in RAM, yielding high read/write
				throughput at very low latency. These capabilities arise from Couchbase’s integral
				object managed cache, which is a distributed hash table with full memcached API
				compatibility. The document database makes heavy use of the object managed cache. </p>
			<p>Couchbase Server is a true operational store that serves end customer requests
				directly. This contrasts with Hadoop and Spark, which are primarily analytic and
				machine learning environments that are accessed by analysts and data scientists and
				which tolerate orders of magnitude more latency.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Easy, elastic scaling</title>
			<p>Couchbase server is designed to scale easily on commodity hardware and to be more hardware
				efficient than other similar solutions. Replication and sharding are fundamental
				features of Couchbase Server. It automatically distributes data across nodes in the
				cluster. Thus, the database can grow horizontally to share load by adding more RAM,
				disk, and CPU capacity, without increasing the burden on developers and
				administrators. Couchbase Server achieves high hardware efficiency by employing
				asynchronous, non-blocking I/O at all levels for effective utilization of server
				resources. This maximizes both the storage I/O and the number of simultaneously
				connected clients per node. Couchbase’s architecture ensures that workloads are
				evenly distributed across cluster nodes, reducing bottlenecks and allowing users to
				take full advantage of the available hardware. </p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Simple administration</title>
			<p>Couchbase Server is extremely straightforward to deploy and manage. Features such as
				replication are built in and happen automatically. Topology changes happen
				transparently, without needing changes to the application or other Couchbase nodes.
				Each Couchbase Server node consists of completely identical software, making
				automation a breeze. The entire cluster is managed through a single administrator
				console that offers single-click cluster expansion and rebalance. Even highly
				sophisticated technology, such as cross data center replication, can be configured
				with a single click in the admin console.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>High availability</title>
			<p>Built with a strong emphasis on reliability, high availability, and simple
				management, an important feature of Couchbase Server is that all operations can be
				done while the system remains online, without requiring modifications or
				interrupting running applications. The system never needs to be taken offline for
				routine maintenance such as software upgrades, index building, compaction, hardware
				refreshes, or any other operation. Even provisioning or removing nodes can be done
				entirely online without any interruption to running applications, and without
				requiring developers to modify their applications. </p>
			<p>Equally important, Couchbase Server’s built-in fault tolerance mechanisms protect
				against downtime caused by arbitrary unplanned incidents, including server failures.
				Replication and failover are important mechanisms that increase system availability.
				Couchbase Server replicates data across multiple nodes to support failover. Ensuring
				that additional copies of the data are available in case of the inevitable failures
				that large distributed systems are designed to recover from. All of this is done
				automatically without need for manual intervention or downtime.</p>
			<p>Entire Couchbase Server clusters can be replicated to one or more alternate
				geographical locations using cross data center replication (XDCR), a technology that
				delivers increased high availability, disaster recovery and geographic load
				balancing. XDCR addresses the unique challenges inherent in linking clusters that
				span across a wide-area network (WAN) rather than simply extending local-cluster
				replication across a WAN.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Summary</title>
			<p>Many databases are able to satisfy one or more of these requirements, but require tradeoffs
				when running in production. For example, one solution might be very flexible in the
				data model but lack the ability to add or remove nodes without serious impact on
				performance, another solution might demonstrate good write scalability without being
				able to add indexes and change the data model on the fly.  Couchbase Server is
				designed to deliver an excellent developer experience  and easy administration while
				also providing oustanding performance at scale.</p>
		</section>

	</conbody>

</concept>
