<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="whats-new">
  <title>What's New?</title>
  <body>
    <p>Couchbase Server 5.5 is a substantial extension of the Couchbase Data Platform. This release
      introduces several new enterprise grade features relating to agility, performance, and
      manageability. It also includes enhancements to existing services as well as new server and
      SDK components that have been in the works for a long time. Take a look at the <xref
        href="../release-notes/relnotes.dita#topic_gbk_tyh_t5">release notes</xref> for a list of
      known and fixed issues in this release.</p>
    
    <section> <title>Unmatched agility and flexibility</title>
      <p><b>Couchbase Eventing Service</b></p>
      <p>This release introduces our Couchbase Eventing Service – a multidimensional-scaling (MDS)
        enabled service that lets you process changes to data as they happen in near real-time. </p>
      <p>Couchbase Functions is the first offering under the Couchbase Eventing Service that enables
        you to write server-side functions that are automatically triggered using the familiar
        Event-Condition-Action model. It provides an easy-to-use online JavaScript code editor that
        lets you develop and debug the code on generated mutations to the data residing in Couchbase
        cluster. </p>
      <p>The Couchbase Eventing Service handles all the complexity of scaling to a large number of
        document mutations. This new offering enables you to develop deeply engaging and
        personalized user experiences based on real-time events. To learn more about this new
        service, see <xref href="../eventing/eventing-Introduction.dita#eventing_operations"/>.</p>
      <p><b>Couchbase Analytics (Developer Preview)</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase Analytics (currently in Developer Preview) enables you to analyze your JSON data
        in real time without the need to extract, transform, load (ETL) your data into a separate
        system. It allows you to develop insight-driven applications quickly and easily using the
        same SDKs. It removes the need for ETL and the complexity of managing a separate analytics
        system. With this release, Analytics is fully integrated with Couchbase Server and no longer
        requires a separate installation. Couchbase’s unique architecture for Multi-Dimensional
        Scaling (MDS) allows operational and analytical queries to run concurrently without
        impacting one another, providing the workload isolation required for production deployments.
        To learn more about this service, see <xref href="../analytics/introduction.html"
          format="html">Couchbase Analytics</xref>.</p>
      <p><b>ANSI joins in N1QL</b></p>
      <p>The Couchbase Data Platform is the only platform that extends SQL to support JSON data
        natively via N1QL queries. N1QL now has support for ANSI joins making it easier to migrate
        applications from RDBMS to Couchbase. Developers can leverage their SQL knowledge to develop
        applications on Couchbase, thereby increasing productivity. </p>
      <p>ANSI joins support improved data modeling capability and flexibility with Couchbase. Since
        you can join based on arbitrarily complex expressions, business requirements can be coded
        and translated effectively and efficiently. We've extended ANSI syntax to join on both
        scalars and arrays. See the <xref
          href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/from.dita#topic_rnt_zfk_np/section_ek1_jnx_1db"/>
        for details.</p>
    </section>
    <section> <title>Unparalleled performance at scale</title>
      <p><b>N1QL pushdowns - aggregate optimization</b></p>
      <p>One of the key advantages of a declarative query language like N1QL is that the system can
        optimize and improve the query plans and execution without changing the applications. Since
        the introduction of N1QL, Couchbase has improved the query performance by orders of
        magnitude. </p>
      <p>With aggregate optimization, the query engine leverages the indexes to perform aggregate
        calculations to improve the performance of queries by another order of magnitude. Your
        existing aggregate queries with matching indexes will simply run faster. See <xref
          href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/groupby-aggregate-performance.dita#groupby-aggregate-performance"
        /> for details.</p>
      <p><b>Index partitioning</b></p>
      <p>With support for index partitioning, you can now index a large number of documents and
        horizontally scale an index as needed. The system will partition the index across a number
        of index nodes using hash partitioning. </p>
      <p>Index partitioning is transparent to queries – one does not have to update the queries when
        changing the index partitioning strategy. See <xref
          href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/index-partitioning.dita#untitled1"/> for
        details.</p>
      <p><b>End-to-end data compression</b></p>
      <p>With the introduction of compression across layers from client to storage, Couchbase
        significantly reduces the cost of network, memory, and storage required for your existing
        workloads. </p>
      <p>Documents are transparently compressed when transferred between the clients and the
        servers, in the server cache, and on disk. Documents are also compressed when transferred
        between clusters across data centers. See <xref
          href="../understanding-couchbase/buckets-memory-and-storage/compression.dita"/> for more
        information.</p>
      <p><b>New Full-Text Search index engine (Developer Preview)</b></p>
      <p>The latest update to the full-text search service provides a preview of our new indexing
        engine, codename: scorch. If you want to test the new performance, you can choose to use the
        current engine (version 5.0) or try the new engine (version 6.0) when creating an index
        through the GUI or REST API.</p>
      <p>The indexing speed is substantially faster, up to 2x faster, and the index size on disk has
        been dramatically reduced, up to 80% reduction. Note that these are interim performance
        numbers as development continues. </p>
      <p>This release of Full-text Search also includes 11 new language analyzers including: Danish,
        Dutch, Finnish, German, Hungarian, Norwegian, Romanian, Russian, Spanish (Castilian),
        Swedish, and Turkish.</p>
    </section>
    <section> <title>Ease of platform management</title>
      <p><b>Security compliance</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase continues to extend its support for security to enable enterprises to meet
        increasing security compliance requirements such as the EU's General Data Protection
        Regulation (GDPR) effective May 2018. We extend <xref
          href="../security/security-certs-auth.dita#topic_pcr_mvh_p1b">X.509 certificate
          authentication</xref> beyond key-value data access to query and search services for <xref
          href="../sdk/dotnet/sdk-authentication-overview.dita#sdk_authentication">all SDK</xref>. </p>
      <p>We also support <xref href="../sdk/encryption.dita#encryption">field-level
          encryption</xref> in our SDKs to protect sensitive user data. Users can <xref
          href="../clustersetup/logging.dita#logging/understanding_redaction">enable log redaction</xref>
        to prevent leaking sensitive user data when using the logs for troubleshooting production
        issues. </p>
      <p>Furthermore, we employ system auditing to track all admin and non-admin access, including
          <xref href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/n1ql-auditing.dita#n1ql-auditing">auditing of
          query statements</xref>.</p>
     <!-- <p><b>Deploying and managing Couchbase at scale with Kubernetes</b></p>
      <p>An open source system for deploying, scaling, and managing containerized applications,
        Kubernetes handles the work of scheduling containers onto a cluster and manages the
        workloads to ensure they run as the user intended. By leveraging the latest features from
        Kubernetes to support stateful applications, we allow users to leverage their investment in
        Kubernetes and containers to easily deploy and manage Couchbase clusters at scale. In
        addition, a close partnership with Red Hat is bringing all of this capability to OpenShift.
        See the <xref
          href="http://docs.couchbase.com/prerelease/couchbase-operator/beta/overview.html"
          format="html" scope="external">Couchbase Operator User's Guide</xref> for more
        information.</p>-->
      <p><b>Auto failover</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase further improves high availability for mission-critical deployments and reduce
        operator intervention. Couchbase enhances the detection of common disk failures and
        automatically fails over the node with bad disks saving without operator intervention. It
        also handles multiple server failures based on the replica count to avoid data loss, and can
        fail over an entire server group if a rack or zone is not available.</p>
      <p><b>Response Time Observability</b></p>
      <p>With response time observability, you now have telemetry for monitoring how well your
        Couchbase cluster is meeting your application SLAs. In your application you can set
        thresholds to allow you to log operations based on performance of your requests. You can
        correlate timing information from client through to server and back to quickly triage
        performance issues and help identify the root cause of performance issues. </p>
      <p>The performance of operations are all exposed via methods you are already familiar with in
        the Couchbase SDK. See <xref href="../sdk/dotnet/threshold-logging.dita#threshold-logging"/>
        for details.</p>
      <p><b>IPv6 support</b></p>
      <p>With the explosion of mobile and IoT devices, enterprises are seeing an increasing
        percentage of their user traffic coming from IPv6. Many large enterprises are starting to
        deploy IPv6 infrastructure to support these IPv6 devices. We have added IPv6 support to
        enable our customers to deliver exceptional user experiences with the Couchbase Data
        Platform. See <xref href="../install/ipv6-setup.dita#ipv6-setup"/> for more information.</p>
      <p><b>SDK enhancements</b></p>
      <p>Many improvements are exposed through the Couchbase SDK, therefore update to the latest
        versions to ensure maximum compatibility. See the <xref
          href="../sdk/java/start-using-sdk.dita#topic_vpj_dh5_xv">SDK documentation</xref> for
        details. <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_kt1_yrr_42b">
          <title>SDK versions that support release 5.5 features</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.04*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.01*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>SDK</entry>
                <entry>Version Supporting 5.5 Features</entry>
                <entry>Field Encryption (Unbundled libs)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Go</entry>
                <entry>1.4.0</entry>
                <entry><xref href="http://github.com/couchbaselabs/gocbfieldcrypt" format="html"
                    scope="external">gocbfieldcrypt</xref></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Node</entry>
                <entry>2.5.0</entry>
                <entry><xref href="https://github.com/couchbase/node-couchbase-encryption"
                    format="html" scope="external">couchbase-encryption</xref></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Java</entry>
                <entry>2.6.0</entry>
                <entry>
                  <p dir="ltr"><xref href="https://github.com/couchbase/java-couchbase-encryption"
                      format="html" scope="external">encryption-extension</xref></p>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>.NET</entry>
                <entry>2.6.0</entry>
                <entry><xref href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption"
                    format="html" scope="external">Couchbase.Extensions.Encryption</xref></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Python</entry>
                <entry>2.4.0<p>(Improvements pending for threshold logging)</p></entry>
                <entry><xref href="https://pypi.org/project/cbencryption/" format="html"
                    scope="external">cbencryption</xref></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>PHP</entry>
                <entry>2.5.0</entry>
                <entry><xref href="https://packagist.org/packages/couchbase/couchbase-encryption"
                    format="html" scope="external">couchbase-encryption</xref></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>LCB</entry>
                <entry>2.9.2</entry>
                <entry>Not applicable</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></p>
    </section>
    <section> <title>Additional improvements</title>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Query: ALTER INDEX</dt>
          <dd>This new declarative command provides administrators the ability to move indexes from one
            node to the other. See <xref
              href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/alterindex.dita#untitled1"/> for details.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Index: Index usage parameters on the Web Console</dt>
          <dd>Revamped Administrator Console and REST endpoints that expose various index usage parameters.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Search: Geospatial searches</dt>
          <dd>Geospatial point/distance and bounding box queries on point data are now GA. See <xref
            href="../fts/fts-geospatial-queries.dita#geospatial_queries"/> for details.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Tools: Enhancements to cbbackupmgr utility</dt>
          <dd>For more information, see <xref href="../backup-restore/cbbackupmgr.dita#cbbackupmgr.1"
          />.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Docs editor</dt>
          <dd>Edit document data from the user interface without the syntactic constraints of JSON.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
