<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="whats-new">
  <title>What's New?</title>
  <body>
    <p>Couchbase Server 5.5 is a substantial extension of the Couchbase Data Platform. This release
      introduces several new enterprise grade features relating to agility, performance, and
      manageability. It also includes enhancements to existing services as well as new server and
      SDK components that have been in the works for a long time. Take a look at the <xref
        href="../release-notes/relnotes.dita#topic_gbk_tyh_t5">release notes</xref> for a list of
      known and fixed issues in this release.</p>
    
    <section> <title>Unmatched agility and flexibility</title>
      <p><b>Couchbase Eventing Service</b></p>
      <p>This release introduces our Couchbase Eventing Service – a multidimensional-scaling (MDS)
        enabled service that lets you process changes to data as they happen in near real-time. </p>
      <p>Couchbase Functions is the first offering under the Couchbase Eventing Service that enables
        you to write server-side functions that are automatically triggered using the familiar
        Event-Condition-Action model. It provides an easy-to-use online JavaScript code editor that
        lets you develop and debug the code on generated mutations to the data residing in Couchbase
        cluster. </p>
      <p>The Couchbase Eventing Service handles all the complexity of scaling to a large number of
        document mutations. This new offering enables you to develop deeply engaging and
        personalized user experiences based on real-time events. To learn more about this new
        service, see <xref href="../eventing/eventing-Introduction.dita#eventing_operations"/>.</p>
      <p><b>Couchbase Analytics (Developer Preview)</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase Analytics (currently in Developer Preview) enables you to analyze your JSON data
        in real time without the need to extract, transform, load (ETL) your data into a separate
        system. It allows you to develop insight-driven applications quickly and easily using the
        same SDKs. It removes the need for ETL and the complexity of managing a separate analytics
        system. With this release, Analytics is fully integrated with Couchbase Server and no longer
        requires a separate installation. Couchbase’s unique architecture for Multi-Dimensional
        Scaling (MDS) allows operational and analytical queries to run concurrently without
        impacting one another, providing the workload isolation required for production deployments.
        To learn more about this service, see <xref href="../analytics/introduction.html"
          format="html">Couchbase Analytics</xref>.</p>
      <p><b>ANSI joins in N1QL</b></p>
      <p>The Couchbase Data Platform is the only platform that extends SQL to support JSON data
        natively via N1QL queries. N1QL now has support for ANSI joins making it easier to migrate
        applications from RDBMS to Couchbase. Developers can leverage their SQL knowledge to develop
        applications on Couchbase, thereby increasing productivity. </p>
      <p>ANSI joins support improved data modeling capability and flexibility with Couchbase. Since
        you can join based on arbitrarily complex expressions, business requirements can be coded
        and translated effectively and efficiently. We've extended ANSI syntax to join on both
        scalars and arrays. See the <xref
          href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/from.dita#topic_rnt_zfk_np/section_ek1_jnx_1db"/>
        for details.</p>
    </section>
    <section> <title>Unparalleled performance at scale</title>
      <p><b>N1QL pushdowns - aggregate optimization</b></p>
      <p>One of the key advantages of a declarative query language like N1QL is that the system can
        optimize and improve the query plans and execution without changing the applications. Since
        the introduction of N1QL, Couchbase has improved the query performance by orders of
        magnitude. </p>
      <p>With aggregate optimization, the query engine leverages the indexes to perform aggregate
        calculations to improve the performance of queries by another order of magnitude. Your
        existing aggregate queries with matching indexes will simply run faster. See <xref
          href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/groupby-aggregate-performance.dita#groupby-aggregate-performance"
        /> for details.</p>
      <p><b>Index partitioning</b></p>
      <p>With support for index partitioning, you can now index a large number of documents and
        horizontally scale an index as needed. The system will partition the index across a number
        of index nodes using hash partitioning. </p>
      <p>Index partitioning is transparent to queries – one does not have to update the queries when
        changing the index partitioning strategy. See <xref
          href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/index-partitioning.dita#untitled1"/> for
        details.</p>
      <p><b>End-to-end data compression</b></p>
      <p>With the introduction of compression across layers from client to storage, Couchbase
        significantly reduces the cost of network, memory, and storage required for your existing
        workloads. </p>
      <p>Documents are transparently compressed when transferred between the clients and the
        servers, in the server cache, and on disk. Documents are also compressed when transferred
        between clusters across data centers. See <xref
          href="../understanding-couchbase/buckets-memory-and-storage/compression.dita"/> for more
        information.</p>
      <p><b>New Full-Text Search index engine (Developer Preview)</b></p>
      <p>The latest update to the full-text search service provides a preview of our new indexing
        engine, codename: scorch. If you want to test the new performance, you can choose to use the
        current engine (version 5.0) or try the new engine (version 6.0) when creating an index
        through the GUI or REST API.</p>
      <p>The indexing speed is substantially faster, up to 2x faster, and the index size on disk has
        been dramatically reduced, up to 80% reduction. Note that these are interim performance
        numbers as development continues. </p>
      <p>This release of Full-text Search also includes 11 new language analyzers including: Danish,
        Dutch, Finnish, German, Hungarian, Norwegian, Romanian, Russian, Spanish (Castilian),
        Swedish, and Turkish.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="platforms">
      <title>Supported Platforms</title>
      <p>This release adds support for the following platforms: <ul id="ul_sfs_kd3_n2b">
          <li>Debian 9</li>
          <li>macOS 10.13 (High Sierra)</li>
        </ul>See <xref href="../install/install-platforms.dita#topic1634"/> for the complete list of
        supported platforms.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
