<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="whats-new">
  <title>What's New?</title>
  <body>
    <p>Couchbase Server 6.0 Beta brings significant updates to the Analytics, Eventing and Full-text Search services.</p> 
    <note type="important"><p>This Beta version is intended for development and testing purposes only. We consider Beta
      releases to have some rough edges and bugs, and may change significantly before the final GA
      release. This release is <b>not supported</b> in production. </p><p>The Beta release does <b>not
        support</b> upgrading from an earlier version of Couchbase Server.</p></note>
    <p>Take a look at the <xref
      href="../release-notes/relnotes.dita#topic_gbk_tyh_t5">release notes</xref> for a list of
      known issues in this release.</p>
    
    <section id="new-features"><title>New features</title>
      <p><b>Couchbase Analytics [Beta]</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase Analytics is now in Beta! Our Analytics service enables you to analyze your JSON data in real time without the need to extract, transform, load (ETL) your data into a separate system. It allows you to develop
        insight-driven applications quickly and easily using the same SDKs. It removes the need for
        ETL and the complexity of managing a separate analytics system. With this release, Analytics
        is fully integrated with Couchbase Server and no longer requires a separate installation.
        Couchbase’s unique architecture for Multi-Dimensional Scaling (MDS) allows operational and
        analytical queries to run concurrently without impacting one another, providing the workload
        isolation required for production deployments. To learn more about this service, see <xref
          href="../analytics/introduction.html" format="html">Couchbase Analytics</xref>.</p>
      
      <p><b>Support for Timers in Couchbase Functions</b></p>
      <p>This release adds support for timers in Couchbase Functions. Timers enable asynchronous
        compute in reference to wall-clock events. They are constructs which developers can use to
        specify a routine (business logic) to be triggered at a future time. For more information,
        see <xref
          href="../eventing/eventing-language-constructs.dita#eventing_language_constructs/timers"
        />.</p> 
      
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
