<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ncd_gdg_q4">
  <title>Adding a Node</title><shortdesc>Add a node to the cluster during initial installation or after the installation. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Full Administrators and Cluster Administrators can use the UI, CLI, or REST API interface to
      add a node.</p>
    <p>There are several methods for adding a node to a cluster. In each case, one or more nodes are
      marked to be added to the cluster, but it doesn't become an active member of the cluster until
      you rebalance the cluster. </p>
    <p>In a CLI call, the rebalance can optionally be done while adding the new node and using the
      UI, rebalancing requires an extra step. </p>
    
    <section><title>During Initial Installation</title>
      
      
      
    </section>
      
      <p>When setting up a new Couchbase Server installation, you have the option to join the new
      node to an existing cluster. For detailed instructions, see <xref
        href="../install/init-setup.dita#topic12527"/>.</p>
   
      
      <p>The node will be created as a new cluster, but the pending status of the node within the
      new cluster will be indicated, as shown in the example below:</p>
      
      <fig>
      <image href="../images/admin-tasks-rebalance-node-added.png"  align="left"/>
    </fig>
      
    <section>
      <title>Using the UI</title>
      
      <p>Using the same method, you can add a server that was previously part of this or another
        cluster. During this process, Couchbase Server must be running.</p>
      <fig>
        <image href="../admin/picts/add-server-new2.png" id="image_myt_vqk_zs" align="left"
          />
      </fig><p>To add a new node to an existing cluster using the Web Console: </p>
      <ol id="ol_dyg_qjq_cz">
        <li>From the <uicontrol>Couchbase Web Console > Servers ></uicontrol> click <uicontrol>Add
            Server</uicontrol>.</li>
        <li>Enter the following information and click <uicontrol>Add Server</uicontrol>.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>
        <table id="table_wdz_skq_cz">
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="col2" colwidth="4*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Option</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Server IP Address</entry>
                <entry>The IP address or FQDN (Fully Qualified Domain Name) of the server that you
                  want to add. It is preferred that you use FQDNs, especially in a cloud hosting
                  environment.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Assign Server Group</entry>
                <entry>Select the server group name from the list. For more information about server
                  groups, see <xref href="manage-groups.dita#mangage-server-groups"/>.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Username</entry>
                <entry>The username of the administrator account of the node to be added.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Password</entry>
                <entry>The password of the administrator account of the node to be added.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Services</entry>
                <entry>Select the appropriate check box to define the kind of <xref
                  href="../understanding-couchbase/services-and-indexes/services/services.dita"
                    >services</xref> will be provided on the server node that's been added. You can
                  add one or more services. The options are: Data, Query, Index, Search, Analytics,
                  and Eventing.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </p>
      <p>A warning will appear indicating that the operation is destructive on the destination
        server. Any data currently stored on the server will be deleted, and if the server is
        currently part of another cluster, it will be removed and marked as failed over in that
        cluster.</p>
      <p>Once the information has been entered successfully, the node will be marked as ready to be
        added to the cluster, and the cluster's pending rebalance count will be updated.</p>
      <note type="important">Once a node is added with a specific service, you cannot change the
        type of services on that node. You must remove the node, rebalance, and then add it back to
        the cluster with the services of your choice.</note>
    </section>
    <section><title>Using the CLI</title> 
      
      <p>
        The Couchbase CLI can be used to add one or more nodes to an existing cluster. See the
        <xref href="../cli/cbcli/couchbase-cli-server-add.html" format="html" scope="local">server-add</xref>
        command. See also the
        <xref href="../cli/cbcli/couchbase-cli-rebalance.html" format="html" scope="local">rebalance</xref>
        command, which must be used after the nodes have been added.
      </p>
    </section>  
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Using the REST API
      </title>
      
      <p>
        With the REST API, you can add nodes to the cluster, by
        providing the IP address, administrator username, and password as part of the data
        payload. See 
        <xref href="../rest-api/rest-cluster-addnodes.dita" format="dita" scope="local">Adding Nodes to Clusters</xref>,
        for information. Also, see
        <xref href="../rest-api/rest-cluster-rebalance.dita" format="dita" scope="local">Rebalancing Nodes</xref>, for
        information on how to rebalance the cluster with the REST API, following node-addition.
      </p>
      
    </section>
  
  </body>
 
</topic>
