<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_fcf_chm_zs">
  <title>Automatic failover</title> <shortdesc>Automatic failover marks a node as failed-over if the node was identified as unresponsive or unavailable.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    
   <note type="note"> To avoid cascading failures and split-brain scenarios, only one auto-failover is allowed for Couchbase Server.</note>
    <p>There are some deliberate limitations to the auto-failover feature. Here are some automatic failover considerations you should become familiar
      with: </p> 
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Disabled by default</dt>
        <dd>Automatic failover is disabled by default to prevent Couchbase Server from using
          automatic failover without the user explicitly enabling it. Enabling auto-failover will
          enable it for all services except for the Index service. An option is provided in the
            <codeph>InternalSettings</codeph> API to enable also the auto-failover for Index Only
          nodes. This option has effect only when auto-failover is enabled. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Minimum node</dt>
        <dd>Automatic failover is available only on clusters that consist of at least three (3)
          nodes. If two or more nodes go down at the same time within a specified delay period, the
          automatic failover system will not failover any nodes.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Required intervention</dt>
        <dd>Automatic failover will only fail over one node before requiring human intervention to
          prevent a chain reaction failure of all nodes in the cluster. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Failover delay</dt>
        <dd>There is a minimum 120-second delay before a node will be failed over. The time can be
          adjusted, but the software will still perform multiple pings of a node that could be down.
          Software intervention prevents failover of a functioning but slow node or to prevent
          network connection issues from triggering failover.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    
    <p>There are automatic failover policies per service type. The current policies are as follows: </p>
   <dl>
     <dlentry>
       <dt>Data</dt>
       <dd>Auto-failover Data service node if more than 2 data nodes are in the cluster.</dd>
     </dlentry>
   </dl>
   <dl>
     <dlentry>
       <dt>Index only</dt>
       <dd>Auto-failover Index only node if more than 1 Index node is in the cluster.</dd>
     </dlentry>
   </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Query only</dt>
        <dd>Auto-failover Query only node if more than 1 Query node is in the cluster.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <p>For multiple services co-located on one node, the policies are different:</p>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Data + Index and / or Query node</dt>
        <dd>Auto-failover policy is same as for the Data service. </dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Index + Query node</dt>
        <dd>Both services are treated equally — the auto-failover policy of each service is also
          taken into consideration.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
  </body>
</topic>
