<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_mfl_rmn_vs">
  
  <title>
    Change Bucket Settings
  </title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    Full, Cluster, and Bucket Administrators can edit a subset of the settings already established on an existing bucket. This section
    explains how to do so; and notes the possible consequences of such configuration-changes.
  </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Edit an Existing Bucket-Configuration
      </title>
      
      <p>
        To edit an existing bucket-configuration, access the Couchbase Web Console, and left-click on the <uicontrol>Buckets</uicontrol>
        tab, in the vertical navigation-bar at the left-hand side.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/accessBucketTab.png" id="access_bucket_tab" align="left" width="80"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The <uicontrol>Buckets</uicontrol> screen now appears, showing the buckets that have already been
        defined for your system:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/bucketsViewInitial.png" id="buckets_view_initial" align="left" width="880"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        To edit the settings for a particular bucket, left-click on the bucket's row in the UI; then, when
        the <uicontrol>Edit</uicontrol> button appears, left-click on it:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/editBucketButton.png" id="edit_bucket_button" align="left" width="260"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        This displays the <uicontrol>Edit Bucket Settings</uicontrol> dialog, which permits changes to be
        made to a subset of existing settings. All the settings contained here are described in detail for
        the <uicontrol>+ Add Data Bucket</uicontrol> dialog, in the section
        <xref href="../clustersetup/create-bucket.dita">Create a New Bucket</xref>
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Making Changes
      </title>
    
    <p>
      Only a subset of settings are available for modification, after the creation of a bucket.
      These settings are listed below:
    </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>Per Node RAM Quota</b>: The amount of RAM allocated per-node to this bucket. If
          you decide to lower this setting, note that the value you specify cannot be lower than the amount of memory
          currently used by the bucket on any of the nodes in your cluster. Once changed, this setting takes
          effect immediately.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Cache Ejection Policy</b>: The ejection policy used by a bucket. The two available 
          policies are discussed in 
          <xref href="../architecture/core-data-access-buckets.dita#ejection-and-eviction-definitions" scope="local" format="dita">Ejection
          and Eviction</xref>. 
          Note that changing the ejection-policy forces
          a bucket-restart; resulting in the temporary inaccessibility of data, while the bucket warms up.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Access Control</b>: The authentication policy used by the bucket. See
          <xref href="../clustersetup/create-bucket.dita#bucket-access-control" scope="local" format="dita">Access Control</xref>.
          Note that if you decide to change this
          setting, you should ensure that all client applications are made aware of the need for new
          credentials.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Number of Replicas</b>: The number of bucket-replicas to be maintained by the cluster. This number can be changed at any
          time: however, a rebalance is required after a setting-change, in order to redistribute
          the correct number of replica-items across the cluster.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Bucket Priority</b>: The priority to be assigned to the current bucket's background
          tasks. See
          <xref href="../install/init-setup.dita#bucket-io-priority-definition-01" scope="local" format="dita">Bucket Priority</xref>
          for information.
          Note that a priority-changes invokes a bucket restart,
          resulting in the temporary inaccessibility of data, while the bucket warms up.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Auto-Compaction Parameters</b>: When established, these settings, which determine the conditions under which data-compaction
          for the bucket is performed, override the
          cluster-wide defaults; as discussed in <xref href="../settings/configure-compact-settings.dita">Configuring Auto-Compaction</xref>.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Flush</b>: This setting enables or disables the <xref href="../clustersetup/bucket-flush.dita">Flush</xref> command for the
          current bucket. It can be changed at any time. Note that when flushing is enabled, left-clicking on the bucket's display-row on
          the <uicontrol>Buckets</uicontrol> screen displays the <uicontrol>Flush</uicontrol> button:
          
          <p>
            <image href="./picts/flushBucketButton.png" id="flush_bucket_button" align="left" width="360"/>
          </p>
          
          <p>
            If flushing is <i>disabled</i>, the <uicontrol>Flush</uicontrol> button does not appear.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
      </ul> 
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Changing Bucket-Settings with the CLI and REST API
      </title>
      
      <p>
        You can change bucket-settings using the CLI command 
        <xref href="../cli/cbcli/bucket-edit.dita#reference_hhk_gmn_ls">bucket-edit</xref>; or the 
        <xref href="../rest-api/rest-bucket-parameters.dita#rest-bucket-change">Bucket REST API</xref>.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Unchangeable Bucket-Settings
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Some settings cannot be changed, after bucket-creation. These are:
      </p>
    
      <ul>
        <li>
          <b>Bucket Name</b>: Once created, the bucket name cannot be changed.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>Bucket Type</b>: Once a <codeph>Memcached</codeph>, <codeph>Couchbase</codeph>, or <codeph>Ephemeral</codeph>
          bucket has been created, its type cannot be changed.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <b>View index replicas</b>: <xref href="../indexes/mapreduce-view-replication.dita">View index replicas</xref> 
          cannot be enabled or disabled, once a bucket has been created.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
      </ul>
 
    </section>
    
  </body>
  
  <related-links>
    <link href="../security/concepts-rba.dita#concept_ntl_jph_hr"/>
  </related-links>
</topic>
