<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_nzk_yln_vs">
  <title>Failing over a Node</title><shortdesc>Failover is the process 
    in which a node of a Couchbase cluster is removed quickly (as opposed to a regular remove and rebalance) from the cluster. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>There are three types of failovers: <term>graceful</term>, <term>hard</term>, and
        <term>automatic</term>.</p>

    <note type="note">To fully understand how failover works, see  <xref
        href="../concepts/distributed-data-management.dita#concept_cz5_szf_vs"/> and <xref
        href="../concepts/multidimensional-scaling.dita#concept_ckt_svy_zs"/>to learn how Couchbase
      partitions data and database services are distributed across a Couchbase cluster.</note>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt><xref href="setup-failover-graceful.dita#topic_ysk_ycm_zs">Graceful failover</xref></dt>
        <dd>Graceful failover is the proactive ability to remove a Data service node from the
          cluster in an orderly and controlled fashion. It is an online operation with zero
          downtime, which is achieved by promoting replica vBuckets on the remaining cluster nodes
          to active and the active vBuckets on the node to failover to dead. This type of failover
          is primarily used for planned maintenance of the cluster.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>

<dl>
  <dlentry>
    <dt><xref href="hard-failover.dita#topic_a4s_d24_vs">Hard failover</xref></dt>
    <dd>Hard failover is the ability to drop a node quickly from the cluster when it has become
          unavailable or unstable. This is achieved by promoting replica vBuckets on the remaining
          cluster nodes to active. Hard failover is primarily used when there is an unplanned outage
          to a node in the cluster.</dd>
  </dlentry>
</dl>
<dl>
  <dlentry>
    <dt><xref href="automatic-failover.dita#topic_fcf_chm_zs">Automatic failover</xref></dt>
    <dd>Automatic failover is the built-in ability to have the Cluster Manager detect and determine
          when a node is unavailable and then initiate a hard failover.</dd>
  </dlentry>
</dl>
  </body>
</topic>
