<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="logging">
  
  <title>Logging</title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    The <i>Logging</i> facility allows a record to be maintained of important events
    that occur on Couchbase Server. 
  </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section id="logging_overview">
      
      <title>
        Logging Overview
      </title>
      
      <p>
        The Couchbase Logging facility records important events, and saves the details to log files, on disk. Additionally,
        subsets of information are provided on the <b>Logs</b> screen, in Couchbase Web Console. This may
        appear as follows:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/loggingScreenBasic.png" id="welcome" align="left" width="720"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        By default, on Linux systems, log files are saved to <codeph>/opt/couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/logs</codeph>; on MacOS,
        to <codeph>/Users/</codeph><i>username</i><codeph>/Library/Application Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/logs</codeph>;
        and on Windows, to <codeph>C:\Program Files\Couchbase\Server\var\lib\couchbase\logs</codeph>. 
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="collecting_information">
      
      <title>
        Collecting Information
      </title>
      
      <p>
        On each node within a Couchbase Server-cluster, logging is performed continuously. <i>A subset</i> of
        the results can be reviewed
        in the Couchbase Web Console <b>Logs</b> screen; while <i>all</i> details are saved to
        the <codeph>logs</codeph> directory,
        as described above.
        (Note that the  <codeph>logs</codeph> directory may include
        <codeph>audit.log</codeph>. This is a special log file, used to manage cluster-security, and
        is handled separately from the other log files. The information provided throughout the
        remainder of this page &#8212; on collecting, uploading,
        and redacting &#8212; <i>does not</i> apply to <codeph>audit.log</codeph>. For information on <codeph>audit.log</codeph>,
        see
        <xref href="../security/security-auditing.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Auditing</xref>.)
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Additionally, <i>explicit logging</i> can be performed by the user. This allows
        comprehensive and fully updated
        information to be generated as required. The output includes everything currently
        on disk, together with additional data that is gathered in real time. Explicit logging can either be performed
        for all nodes in the cluster, or for one or more individual nodes. The results are saved as zip
        files: each zip file contains the log-data generated for an individual node. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Explicit logging can be performed by means
        of the Couchbase CLI utility <codeph>cbcollect_info</codeph>.
        The documentation for this utility, provided
        <xref href="../cli/cbcollect-info-tool.dita" scope="local" format="dita">here</xref>, includes
        a complete list of the log files that can be created, and a description of the contents of each. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Explicit logging can also be performed by means of Couchbase Web Console: on the <b>Logs</b> page, 
        left-click on the
        <uicontrol>Collect Information</uicontrol> tab, located near the top.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/collectInfo.png" id="collect_info" align="left" width="248"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        This brings up the <b>Collect Information</b> screen:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/collectInformationScreen.png" id="collect_info_screen" align="left" width="720"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        This allows logs and diagnostic information to be collected either from all or from selected nodes
        within the cluster. It also allows a <b>Log Redaction Level</b> to be specified (this is
        described in
        <xref href="./logging.dita#logging/applying_redaction" scope="local" format="dita">Applying Redaction</xref>,
        below). The <b>Specify custom temp directory</b> checkbox can be checked to specify the absolute pathname
        of a directory into which data is temporarily saved, during the collection process.
        The <b>Specify custom destination directory</b> can be checked to specify the absolute pathname
        of a directory
        into which the competed zip files are saved. 

      </p>
      
      <p>
        The <b>Upload to Couchbase</b> checkbox is described in
        <xref href="./logging.dita#logging/uploading_log_files" scope="local" format="dita">Uploading Log Files</xref>,
        below.
      </p>
        
      <p>  
        To start the collection-process, left-click on the <uicontrol>Start Collection</uicontrol>
        button. A notification is displayed, indicating that the collection-process is running. When
        the process has completed, the following information is displayed:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/collectInformationComplete.png" id="collect_info_complete" align="left" width="720"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        As this indicates, a set of log files has been created for 
        each node in the cluster. Each file is
        saved as a zip file in the stated temporary location. 
      </p>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="uploading_log_files">
      
      <title>
        Uploading Log Files
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Log files can be uploaded to Couchbase, for inspection by Couchbase Support. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        For information on performing upload at the command-prompt, see
        <xref href="../cli/cbcollect-info-tool.dita" scope="local" format="dita">cbcollect_info</xref>. To upload
        by means of Couchbase Web Console, before starting the collection-process, check the
        <uicontrol>Upload to Couchbase</uicontrol> checkbox:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/uploadToCouchbaseCheckbox.png" id="upload_to_couchbase_checkbox" align="left" width="218"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The display changes to the following: 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/uploadToCouchbaseDialogBasic.png" id="upload_to_couchbase_dialog_basic" align="left" width="302"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The dialog now features an <b>Upload to Host</b> field, which contains the server-location to which the customer-data
        is uploaded. Fields are also provided for <b>Customer Name</b> (required) and <b>Ticket Number</b> (optional).
        The <b>Upload Proxy</b> field optionally takes the hostname of a remote system, which contains
        the directory specified by the pathname.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Left-click on the <b>Start Collection</b> button. When collection is complete, a notification 
        provides the URL of the uploaded zip file.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="understanding_redaction">
      
      <title>
        Understanding Redaction
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Optionally, log files can be <i>redacted</i>. This means that user-data,
        considered to be private, is removed. Such data includes:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          Key/value pairs in JSON documents
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Usernames
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Query-fields that reference key/value pairs and/or usernames
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Names and email addresses retrieved during product registration
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Extended attributes
        </li>
        
      </ul>
      
      <p>
        This redaction of user-data is referred to as <i>partial</i> redaction. (<i>Full</i> redaction, which
        will be available in a forthcoming
        version of Couchbase Server, additionally redacts <i>meta-data</i>.)
      </p>
      
      <p>
        In each modified log file,
        encrypted text (achieved with SHA1) 
        is substituted for redacted text. For example, the following log-file fragment displays
        private data &#8212; a Couchbase username:
      </p>
      
      <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">0ms [I0] {2506} [INFO] (instance - L:421) Effective connection string: 
couchbase://127.0.0.1?username=Administrator&amp;console_log_level=5&amp;;. 
Bucket=default</codeblock>
      
      <p>
        The redacted version of the log file might appear as follows:
      </p>
      
      <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">0ms [I0] {2506} [INFO] (instance - L:421) Effective connection string: 
&lt;UD&gt;e07a9ca6d84189c1d91dfefacb832a6491431e95&lt;/UD&gt;. 
Bucket=&lt;UD&gt;e16d86f91f9fd0b110be28ad00e348664b435e9e&lt;/UD&gt;</codeblock>
        
      <p>
        Note that redaction may eliminate some parameters containing non-private data, as well as all 
        parameters containing private.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Note also that redaction of log files may have one or both of the following consequences:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>Logged issues will be found harder to diagnose, by both the user and Couchbase Support.
        
          <p>
          
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Log-collection is significantly more time-consumptive, since redaction is performed at collection-time.
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="applying_redaction">
      
      <title>
        Applying Redaction
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Redaction of log files saved on the cluster can be applied as required, when performing <i>explicit logging</i>, by 
        means of either <codeph>cbcollect_info</codeph> or the <b>Logs</b> facility of Couchbase Web Console.
            
      </p>
      
      <p>
        For information on performing explicit logging with redaction at the 
        command-prompt, see
        <xref href="../cli/cbcollect-info-tool.dita" scope="local" format="dita">cbcollect_info</xref>. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        To perform explicit logging with redaction
        by means of Couchbase Web Console, before starting the collection-process, 
        access the <b>Log Redaction Level</b> panel, on the <b>Collect Information</b> screen.
        This features two radio-buttons, labelled <b>None</b> and <b>Partial Redaction</b>. Make sure the
        <uicontrol>Partial Redaction</uicontrol> radio-button is selected. Guidance on redaction is displayed below it:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="./picts/partialRedactionSelection.png" id="partial_redaction_selection" align="left" width="682"/>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Left-click on the <uicontrol>Start Collection</uicontrol> button. A notification explains that the
        collection-process is now running. When
        the process has completed, a further notification appears, specifying the location (local or remote) of each
        created zip file. Note that, when redaction has been specified, two zip files are provided for each node: one
        file containing redacted data, the other unredacted data.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="redacting-log-files-outside-the-cluster">
      
      <title>
        Redacting Log Files Outside the Cluster
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Certain Couchbase technologies &#8212; such as <codeph>cbbackupmgr</codeph>, the SDK, connectors, and 
        Mobile &#8212; create log files saved outside the Couchbase Cluster. These can be redacted by
        means of the command-line tool <codeph>cblogredaction</codeph>. Multiple log files can be
        specified simultaneously. Each file must be specified as plain text. Optionally, the salt to be used
        in encryption can be automatically generated.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        For example:
      </p>
      
      <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ cblogredaction /Users/username/testlog.log -g -o /Users/username -vv
2018/07/17T11:27:06 WARNING: Automatically generating salt. This will make it difficult to cross reference logs
2018/07/17T11:27:07 DEBUG: /Users/username/testlog.log - Starting redaction file size is 19034284 bytes
2018/07/17T11:27:07 DEBUG: /Users/usernae/testlog.log - Log redacted using salt: &lt;ud&gt;COeAtexHB69hGEf3&lt;/ud&gt;
2018/07/17T11:27:07 INFO: /Users/username/testlog.log - Finished redacting, 50373 lines processed, 740 tags redacted, 0 lines with unmatched tags</codeblock>
    
      <p>
        For more information, see the corresponding man page, or run the command with the <codeph>--h</codeph> (help)
        option.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
  </body>
 
</topic>
