<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ysk_ycm_zs">
  <title>Using Graceful Failover</title> <shortdesc>Graceful failover is used to eject a node containing the Data service from the cluster
    after all in-flight operations, and data synchronizations are complete.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Graceful failover is a method of safely ejecting a node containing the Data service from a
      Couchbase cluster where the Cluster Manager initiates data synchronization between nodes of
      the cluster before removal. It is most commonly used for planned maintenance on the cluster to
      speed up the node removal, but it doesn't come without some risks. There are pros and cons to
      graceful failover compared to <xref href="hard-failover.dita#topic_a4s_d24_vs">hard
        failover</xref> and regular node removal and rebalance. <note type="note">Graceful failover
        only applies to the Data service</note></p>
    <note type="note">To understand how graceful failover works, you must understand the data
      distribution and what Couchbase Server does to partition data across a cluster. </note>
    
    <section><title>How does Graceful Failover Work?</title>
      <p>Graceful Failover drains the node to be failed over of active vBuckets, one at a time until
        that node hosts no buckets and no active vBuckets. All in-flight operations to the active
        vBucket are completed, the corresponding replica vBucket is synchronized by the Cluster
        Manager to match and then the replicas are promoted to active on the other node. This occurs
        one bucket and one vBucket at a time, until complete. The final failover actions are taken
        after the last vBucket promotion occurs. Each promotion happens in a coordinated
        split-second timeframe. At no time will data be unavailable and the application should not
        notice that data is missing.</p>
      <p>Since synchronization of the active and replica vBuckets is required each time a vBucket is
        moved,  graceful failover by and of itself takes slightly longer to complete than a hard
        failover. It is fast, but not as much as the hard failover. The performance difference is
        only noticeable if the cluster is under very high write load or when data replication is
        slow.</p>
      <p>Use Graceful failover only when the following conditions are met; otherwise, use hard
        failover. </p>
     <ul>
       <li>All nodes in the cluster are healthy (for example, none has failed or is
          malfunctioning).</li>
       <li>Each bucket in the cluster has all active vBuckets and at least one full set of replica
          vBuckets. If not, first fix the problems and rebalance the cluster. For each bucket, look
          at the <codeph>vBucket Resources</codeph> section of the metrics, then look at the active
          and replica vBucket graphs to confirm that each graph has 1024 for that bucket.<p><image
              href="../admin/picts/graceful-failover.png" id="image_zqj_cbm_5v" align="left"
              width="550"/></p></li>
     </ul> 
      <p>For example:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>In a seven-node cluster, if a bucket is configured for one replica, one node can be
          gracefully failed over.</li>
        <li>In a seven-node cluster, if a bucket is configured for two replicas, two nodes can be
          gracefully failed over.</li>
        <li>In a seven-node cluster, if a bucket is configured for three replicas, three nodes can
          be gracefully failed over.</li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>A graceful failover can also be halted mid-process. You can restart a graceful failover
        that has been paused, in which case the cluster picks up from where it left off previously.
        If you stop the graceful failover and do not intend to restart it, you must rebalance the
        cluster. This will generate any replica vBuckets that were promoted as part of the graceful
        failover process and set the cluster back to where it was, essentially undoing the effects
        of the graceful failover that you paused.</p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Understanding when to use Graceful Failover</title>
      
    <p>Graceful failover offers these advantages:</p> 
      <ul>
        <li>Maintenance can be completed faster than with a remove and rebalance. If you have a
          tight maintenance window, you can gracefully failover a node, do your upgrades, changes,
          patches and so on on that node, and then quickly add it back using Delta Node Recovery to
          catch up on data where it left off. A use case will be when the security patching on a
          node is needed or if your cloud provider informs you that you need to restart an instance.
          Using graceful failover to remove the node and then Delta Node Recovery to add it back
          when the maintenance is complete is very quick, easy, and fairly non-intrusive.</li>
        <li>Graceful failover is less resource-intensive than hard failover. In a graceful failover
          scenario, vBuckets simply have their status changed from replica to active. They are not
          redistributed (copied) to other nodes as they would during a rebalance. There is little
          increase in network and disk utilization among the nodes of the Data service.</li>
      </ul>
      
      
    </section>
    <section><title>When to use Hard Failover Instead</title>
      <p><xref href="hard-failover.dita#topic_a4s_d24_vs">Hard failover</xref> is the corrective
        action for an unplanned outage of a node that is unhealthy or unstable, whereas graceful
        failover is meant for planned maintenance. A hard failover ejects the node from the cluster
        immediately, with no regard for draining of vBuckets from the unhealthy node or vBucket
        synchronization. </p>
      
    </section>
    <section><title>Understand the Risks of Using Graceful Failover</title>
  <p>Graceful failover might cause the following:</p> 
      <ul>
        <li>Temporary loss of resiliency. By promoting the replica vBuckets to active on the
          remaining nodes, the cluster does not have the full accompaniment of replica vBuckets
          necessary for further node failures. So if another node fails after you have gracefully
          failed over a node, but before you have rebalanced the cluster, you would not have
          replicas to promote to active as you sacrificed them during the graceful failover. </li>
        <li>Possible temporary loss of performance. Depending on how your cluster is sized and the
          workload on the cluster, the replica data may or may not be in the Couchbase’s managed
          cache: when under memory pressure, Couchbase Server will eject replica data before active
            data.<p>If the replica data is not already in the managed cache, your replica data
            resident ratio could be as low as 0% before failover occurs. Once failover occurs, the
            data in those failed-over vBuckets will take longer to access as they are loaded from
            disk into the managed cache. In other words, a cache miss occurs. Like any cache miss,
            it takes more time and resources: more disk access, putting a strain on disk resources,
            and temporarily reducing performance when accessing this section of the data. The impact
            is not severe enough so that you have to account for it in cluster sizing, but it is
            something you need to know about and monitor. You will probably see a higher cache miss
            ratio in the bucket metrics on the remaining nodes of the cluster for some time after a
            graceful failover.</p></li>
      </ul>
      
    </section>
    
    <section><title>A Hypothetical Scenario</title>
      <p>Imagine that you have a Couchbase bucket distributed across four nodes of the Data service
        in a cluster, and you need to remove one node. The system administrator never sent prior
        notice, and she is telling you the node needs a critical security patch that requires a
        reboot. Of course, it must be done as soon as possible. You do not have enough time to do a
        full removal and rebalancing of the node, and then add it back and rebalance again. Graceful
        failover saves the day! </p>
      <p>Under the hood, here’s what happens when you initiate a graceful failover. With a four-node
        cluster and one replica for each bucket, there are 256 active and 256 replica vBuckets on
        each of the four nodes, totaling 1024 active and 1024 replica vBuckets. In this particular
        example, we will only talk about one vBucket, #762, although the same process is repeated
        for every vBucket on the node to be gracefully failed over: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Graceful failover is initiated to remove the node where the active vBucket #762 resides,
          which is node 4. Active vBucket #762 receives writes as normal during this process.</li>
        <li>The Cluster Manager confirms that active vBucket #762 is in sync with replica vBucket
          #762 that resides on node 2 of the cluster.</li>
        <li>When they are synchronized, the Cluster Manager coordinates a takeover by node 2 of
          vBucket 762. As part of that, the Cluster Manager promotes replica vBucket 762 to active
          status on node 2 and dead status on the old vBucket on the failed over node 4.  Note that
          this leaves the cluster with no replica for vBucket 762 until the next rebalance or Delta
          Node Recovery unless you have more than one replica configured for this bucket.</li>
        <li>As this is a cluster topology change, the cluster map is updated so that the subsequent
          reads and writes by the Couchbase client SDKs go to the correct location for data in
          vBucket 762, now node 2.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This process all happens in fractions of a second. The same steps are repeated for the
        remaining 255 vBuckets of the bucket on this node, one at a time. Likewise, if there is more
        than one bucket, the same step is repeated on each of them until their vBuckets have all
        been activated on other nodes, at which time the graceful failover is complete.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
