<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_ul5_45f_ps">
 <title>Data Access</title>
  <shortdesc>Couchbase provides multiple ways of accessing data: using a key-value access pattern,
    querying data using MapReduce (views) or N1QL. You can also use Full Text Search (FTS) feature
    to query data. </shortdesc>
 <conbody>
   <p>At a high level, key-value access provides a high performance access path directly to data
      using the key to the item stored. For applications looking for sub millisecond latencies,
      key-value method provides the fastest access your data. However, not all data access can have
      a key in hand and that is where queries come in. Queries can be done using MapReduce views and
      N1QL. N1QL provides a flexible and declarative query language that is similar to SQL access
      provided by relational databases. N1QL is great for fast access to your data for operations
      such as secondary lookup on attributes in your JSON document. For example, lookup users using
      the user email address and not the userID that is used for the document key. </p>
   <p>Views also
        provide a powerful way to index data with user defined map and reduce functions. Views can be
        a powerful option for complex reshaping and pre-aggregation of data. Views are the ideal
        solution for interactive reporting over your data.</p>
   <section> <title> Key-Value Operations</title>
     <p> At the heart of Couchbase is the distributed key-value (KV) store. A KV store is an extremely
       simple, schema-less approach to data management that, as the name implies, stores a unique
       ID (key) together with a piece of arbitrary information (value); it may be thought of as a
       hash map or dictionary. The KV store itself can accept any data, whether it be a binary blob
       or a JSON document, and Couchbase features such as N1QL and MapReduce make use of the KV
       store’s ability to process JSON documents. </p>
     <p>Due to their simplicity, KV operations execute with extremely low latency, often sub-millisecond. While the Query service is accessed by a defined query language (N1QL), the KV store is accessed using simple CRUD (Create, Read, Update, Delete) APIs, and thus provides a simpler interface when accessing documents using their IDs (primary keys).</p>
     <p>The KV store contains the authoritative, most up-to-date state for each item. In order to
       perform better, query and MapReduce services provide eventually consistent indexes that, by
       default, use a version of the data that is potentially slightly out-of-date. However, they
       can instead elect to wait briefly to make sure they have had a chance to update before
       responding to a query. By contrast, querying the KV store directly will always access the
       latest version of data.</p>
     
     <p>While N1QL provides a richer query interface, applications will use the KV store when speed,
       consistency, and simplified access patterns are preferred over flexible query options.</p>
     
     <p>All KV operations are atomic, which means that Read and Update are individual operations. In
       order to avoid conflicts that might arise with multiple concurrent updates to the same
       document, applications may make use of Compare-And-Swap (CAS), which is a per-document
       checksum that Couchbase modifies each time a document is changed. </p>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title> MapReduce Views</title>
     <p> Developers can write custom JavaScript MapReduce programs to specify complex indexing and
       aggregation of items stored in Couchbase.  MapReduce is a programming model for distributed
       data processing on highly parallelizable data: the <cmdname>map</cmdname> function reads all
       documents across the cluster, filters them to select the relevant information, and then
       emits the results; the <cmdname>reduce</cmdname> function sorts and aggregates the results.
       MapReduce is most useful for highly customized data processing on large input sets. </p>
     <p>MapReduce data processing is incremental, so the output continues to update as the
       underlying data undergoes mutations. </p>
     <p>Programmers can also write Spatial MapReduce programs that operate on geometric data in the
       form of GeoJSON, n-dimensional numeric data (hyper-cubes), or a combination of the two. This
       can be used to handle queries about geometries, for example, to return a list of all items
       within a particular bounding box.</p>
     <p>MapReduce programs output either MapReduce Views or Spatial Views, which are described
       further in <xref href="../concepts/indexing.dita#concept_kl3_y5f_ps"/>.  </p>
   </section>
  <section> <title> Querying with N1QL</title>
   <p>Couchbase Server can be programmed using SQL. Given that nearly all programmers already know
    SQL, most developers will be able to get started quickly on Couchbase. And since most
    organizations already have significant amounts of SQL code, Couchbase Server fits into the
    technology landscape easily. Support for SQL by JDBC and ODBC drivers opens the ecosystem of
    tools for analytics and data integration such as Microsoft Excel and Tableau.</p>
      <p>N1QL (pronounced "nickel") is the first query language that leverages the complete
        flexibility of JSON with the full power of SQL. Developed by Couchbase for use with the
        Couchbase Server, N1QL provides a common query language and JSON-based data model for
        distributed document-oriented databases.</p>
   <p>Couchbase created its own SQL dialect called N1QL in order to give developers and enterprises an expressive, powerful, and complete language for querying, transforming, and manipulating JSON data. The N1QL query engine is optimized for modern, highly parallel multi-core execution. N1QL has special extensions that allow it to deal with documents with variable and/or nested structures.  Just as SQL operates on rows, columns and tables of an RDBMS and returns rows and columns to the application, N1QL operates on JSON and returns JSON to the application.
   </p>
    <p> N1QL provides a rich set of features that let you retrieve, manipulate, transform, and create
      JSON document data. The key features include: </p>
    
    <ul>
      <li><b>SELECT Statement</b>: The SELECT statement in N1QL extends the functionality of the SQL
        SELECT statement to work with JSON documents. You can use your knowledge of SQL to work with
        the powerful NoSQL features of Couchbase, which in turn enable you to work with big data, big
        data users, and cloud computing. </li>
      <li><b>Data Manipulation Language (DML)</b>: N1QL provides the DELETE, INSERT, UPDATE, and
        UPSERT statements to create, delete, and modify the data stored in JSON documents. You can
        perform these operations by specifying and executing simple commands.</li>
      <li><b>Indexes</b>: N1QL provides the CREATE and DROP INDEX statements to easily create and
        delete indexes.</li>
      <li><b>Primary Key Access</b>: Data in the Couchbase Server can be stored in key-value pairs,
        providing primary key access to any data. </li>
      <li><b>Aggregation</b>: N1QL provides the standard SQL aggregation operators such as MIN, MAX,
        COUNT, as well as the grouping operators, the GROUP BY clause, and the group filter,
        HAVING.</li>
      <li><b>Joins</b>: N1QL lets you retrieve data from multiple documents by specifying joins in the
        FROM clause. </li>
      <li><b>Nesting</b>: Nests enable you to retrieve sub-records for a record. That is, for each
        left hand input, the matching right hand inputs are collected into an array, which is then
        embedded in the result. For example, you can nest each item in a customer’s order. Nests can be
        performed on multiple documents.</li>
      <li><b>Unnesting</b>: Unnesting is the opposite of nesting. The UNNEST function extracts nested
        sub-records from a record, making each extraction a separate record. Note that unnesting can be
        performed on a single document.</li>
      <li><b>Subqueries</b>: N1QL supports multi-part queries through subqueries. You can use a
        subquery with the SELECT statement or nest it within another subquery, thereby refining the
        results of the preceding queries. </li>
      <li><b>UNION, INTERSECT, and EXCEPT</b>: N1QL provides the UNION, INTERSECT, and EXCEPT
        operations to compare two or more queries. UNION combines the results of two or more queries
        into a single result set that includes all the rows that belong to all queries in the union.
        EXCEPT returns any distinct values from the left query that are not found on the right query.
        INTERSECT returns any distinct values that are returned by the queries on both sides of the
        INTERSECT operand.</li>
    </ul> 
   <p>For more information on how to query using N1QL, see <xref
          href="../sdk/n1ql-query.dita"/>.  For the complete language and REST API
        reference, see <xref href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/index.dita">N1QL Language Reference</xref> and the <xref href="../n1ql/n1ql-rest-api/index.dita">N1QL REST API</xref>.</p>
  </section>
  <section> <title> Full text search</title>
   <p> Couchbase Server performs search queries using <xref href="../fts/full-text-intro.dita"/>
        (Developer Preview), an integrated full text search engine. With Couchbase Full Text Search,
        you, as a developer, can easily add full-text search capabilities to your application
        without deploying additional components, which reduces operational complexity.
        Alternatively, if you are using external search engines such as Elasticsearch or Lucidworks,
        you can leverage the available connectors to
        continuously replicate data from the Couchbase Server cluster to the search engines. </p></section>
 </conbody>
  <related-links>
    <link href="../developer-guide/sub-doc-api.dita"></link>
  </related-links>
</concept>
