<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_axj_xtr_zz2">
  
  <title>
    Index Availability and Performance
  </title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    The <i>Index Service</i> ensures availability and performance through <i>replication</i> and
    <i>partitioning</i>. The <i>consistency</i> of query-results can be controlled per query.
  </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section id="section_tnn_hbz_zz2">
      
      <title>
        Index Replication
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Secondary indexes can be replicated across cluster-nodes. This ensures:
      </p>
      
      <p>
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
            <i>Availability</i>: If one Index-Service node is lost, the other continues to provide
            access to replicated indexes.
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <i>High Performance</i>: If original and replica copies
          are available, incoming queries are load-balanced across them.
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>
        Index-replicas can be
        created with the N1QL <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> statement. Note that whenever
        a given number of index-replicas is specified for creation, the number must be less than the number of cluster-nodes
        currently running the 
        <xref href="../../services-and-indexes/services/index-service.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Index Service</xref>.
        If it is not, the index-creation fails. Note also that if, following creation of the maximum number of copies, 
        the number of nodes running the Index Service 
        decreases, Couchbase Server progressively assigns replacement 
        index-replicas to any and all Index-Service nodes
        subsequently be added to the cluster, until
        the required number of index-replicas again exists for each replicated index.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Index-replicas can be created as follows:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          Specifying, by means of the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause, the destination nodes. In the following example,
          an index with two replicas is created. The active index is on <codeph>node1</codeph>, and the replicas
          are on <codeph>node2</codeph> and <codeph>node3</codeph>:
          
          <codeblock id="nodes-example2">CREATE INDEX productName_index1 ON bucket_name(productName, ProductID) 
    WHERE type="product" USING GSI 
    WITH {"nodes":["node1:8091", "node2:8091", "node3:8091"]};</codeblock>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Specifying <i>no</i> destination nodes; but specifying instead, by means of the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause
          and the <codeph>num_replica</codeph> attribute,
          only the <i>number</i> of replicas required. The replicas are automatically distributed across those nodes of the
          cluster that are running the Index Service: the distribution-pattern is based on a projection of
          optimal index-availability, given the number and disposition of Index-Service nodes across
          defined server-groups.
          
          <p>
            In the following example, an index is created with two replicas, with no destination-nodes
            specified:
          </p>
          
          <codeblock>CREATE INDEX productName_index1 ON bucket_name(productName, ProductID) 
    WHERE type="product" USING GSI 
    WITH {"num_replica": 2};</codeblock>
          
          <p>
            Note that if
            <codeph>nodes</codeph> and <codeph>num_replica</codeph> are both specified in the <codeph>WITH</codeph>
            clause, the specified number of nodes must be <i>one greater</i> than <codeph>num_replica</codeph>.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          Specifying a number of index-replicas to be created by the Index Service whenever <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> is
          invoked. The default is <codeph>0</codeph>. If the default is changed to, say, 
          <codeph>2</codeph>, creation of a single index is henceforth
          accompanied by the creation of two replicas, which are automatically distributed across the nodes of the cluster
          running the Index Service. No explicit specification within the <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> statement is
          required. 
          
          <p>
            With credentials that provide appropriate authorization, this default can be changed; by means of 
            the <codeph>curl</codeph> command, as follows:
          </p>
          
          <codeblock>curl -u &lt;username>:&lt;password> &lt;host>:9102/settings -d "{\"indexer.settings.num_replica\": &lt;num_replicas>}"</codeblock>
          
          <p>
            Note, however, 
            that whenever explicit specification of replica-numbers is made 
            within the <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> statement, this 
            explicit specification takes
            precedence over any established default.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>     
        
      </ul>
      
      <p>
        For further information on using N1QL, see
        <xref href="../../../sdk/n1ql-query.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Querying with N1QL</xref>.
      </p>
        
    </section>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Index Partitioning
      </title>
      
      <p>
        As index-sizes and item-counts increase, individual indexes
        may not fit on their assigned node. To remedy this, indexes can be <i>partitioned</i> (divided into two
        or more segments) by means of the 
        <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause to <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph>: the resulting partitions
        can be distributed across multiple, individually specified Index-Service nodes, under 
        different index-names.
        </p>
      
        <p>
         In the following example, <i>ranges</i> are specified, to partition index-content
         across two indexes:
        </p>
      
              <codeblock>CREATE INDEX productName_index1 ON bucket_name(productName, ProductID) 
    WHERE type="product" AND productName BETWEEN "A" AND "K" USING GSI 
    WITH {"nodes":["node1:8091"]};
    
    CREATE INDEX productName_index2 ON bucket_name(productName, ProductID) 
    WHERE type="product" AND productName BETWEEN "K" AND "Z" USING GSI 
    WITH {"nodes":["node2:8091"]};</codeblock>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Index Consistency
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Whereas Couchbase Server handles data-mutations with <i>full consistency</i> &#8212;
        all mutations to a given key are applied to the same vBucket, and become immediately
        available &#8212; it maintains indexes with degrees of
        <i>eventual consistency</i>, determined by means of the following query consistency-options,
        specified per query:
      </p>
      
        <ul id="ul_vzd_j1z_zz2">
          
          <li>
            <codeph>not_bounded</codeph>: Executes the query
            immediately, without requiring any consistency for the query. If index-maintenance is
            running behind, out-of-date results may be returned. 
            
            <p>
            </p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <codeph>at_plus</codeph>: Executes the query, requiring
            indexes first to be updated to the timestamp of the last update. If
            index-maintenance is running behind, the query waits for it to catch up. 
            
            <p>
              
            </p>
            
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <codeph>request_plus</codeph>: Executes the query, requiring the indexes first to be updated 
            to the timestamp of the current
            query-request. If
            index-maintenance is running behind, the query waits for it to catch up.
            
            <p>
            </p>
          
          </li>
          
        </ul>
      
      <p>
        For N1QL, the default consistency is <codeph>not_bounded</codeph>.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    

  </body>
</topic>
