<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="buckets_memory_and_storage">
  
  <title>
    Memory and Storage
  </title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    Couchbase Server provides a caching layer to facilitate high-speed data-access; and tunable disk I/O
    priorities, supported by multi-threaded readers and writers. 
  </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Caching and Persistence
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Couchbase Server provides a fully integrated <i>caching layer</i>, which provides high-speed data-access. Couchbase
        Server automatically manages the caching layer, ensuring that sufficient memory is available in relation
        to occupied disk-space, in order to maintain optimal performance. Data associated with <i>Couchbase</i> buckets
        is also maintained <i>persistenly</i>, on disk.
        Such items, when they come into the caching layer, are 
        placed onto the disk queue, to be written to disk; and at the same time, if appropriate, are placed on a
        replication queue, so that one or more replica buckets can be created or updated accordingly.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        Memory quotas, established by the Full Administrator when the server is configured, are automatically managed
        by Couchbase Server with reference to <i>watermarks</i>, which specify how much free memory should be
        consistently maintained within the caching layer. Consequently, infrequently used items are written to disk; are 
        then removed from memory in order to free up space; and are subsequently re-acquired from disk 
        as necessary. This process, referred to
        as <i>ejection</i>, is managed asynchronously, while the server continues to service active requests. 
        
        A <i>working-set</i> of most frequently used data is tracked and maintained, and the items kept in memory to ensure high performance.
      </p>
      
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Saving New Items
      </title>
      
      <p>
        When a new item, such as a document, is saved by an application, it is
        saved in memory only, if the item is contained by an <i>Ephemeral</i> bucket,
        and is saved both in memory and on disk, if the item is contained by a
        <i>Couchbase</i> bucket. If the bucket (either Ephemeral or Couchbase) has
        been <i>replicated</i> one or more times, a copy of the new item is saved
        in each replica.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The following sequence illustrates how a new document is created by an application
        and saved in a Couchbase bucket.
      </p>
      
      <ol>
        <li>
          The application creates a new document.
          
          <p>
            <image href="./images/createDocSequence1.png" id="create-doc-sequence-1" align="left" width="580" />
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          
          <p>
            
          </p>
        </li>
        
      </ol>
      


      
      
    </section>
    
    
    
  </body>
  
</topic>
