<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="memory">
 
 <title>
  Memory
 </title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  Couchbase Server memory-management ensures high performance and scalability.
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
  
  <section id="service-memory-quotas">
   
   <title>Service Memory Quotas</title>
   
   <p>
    Memory-quota allocation on Couchbase Server occurs <i>per service</i> (except in the case
    of the
    <xref href="./../services-and-indexes/services/query-service.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Query Service</xref>, 
    which does not require a specific allocation). This allows
    the availability of memory-resources to be tuned according to the assignment of services,
    node by node. Note that the 
    <xref href="./../services-and-indexes/services/data-service.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Data Service</xref> 
    must run on at least one node; and that on each of those nodes, quotas for buckets,
    specified at the time of bucket-creation, are subtracted 
    from the quota allocated to the Data Service.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The memory-quota allocation specified for a given service applies to every instance of that
    service across the cluster. For example, if 2048 MB is specified for the 
    <xref href="./../services-and-indexes/services/analytics-service.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Analytics Service</xref>,
    and the Analytics Service is run on three of a cluster's five nodes, each of the three
    instances of the service is duly allocated 2048 MB. Note that it is not possible to have
    different memory allocations across multiple instances of the same service within a single cluster.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    By default, Couchbase Server allows 80% of a node's total available memory to be allocated to 
    the server and its services.
    Consequently, if a node's total available memory is 100 GB, any attempt to allocate memory beyond 80 GB produces
    an error. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Instructions on how to allocate memory quotas to services when initializing a new cluster can be
    found in the section
    <xref href="../../install/init-setup.dita#topic12527/configure-couchbase-server" scope="local" format="dita">Configure Couchbase Server</xref>,
    on the page
    <xref href="../../install/init-setup.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Initializing the Cluster</xref>.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    When a node is added to a cluster, the <i>Default Configuration</i>, as established by the set-up of
    the first node in the cluster, is available: this covers all configurable elements, including memory
    quotas. However, if insufficient memory for the default configuration is available on the new node,  
    the default configuration is prohibited: in such cases, settings
    for the new node can be custom-configured, allowing an appropriate subset of services to be specified. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    If, when the initial node of a cluster is set up, only a subset of services is assigned, additional
    nodes can subsequently be added, in order to host additional services: in which case, each new service can be given
    its initial memory allocation as its node is added.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Instructions on how to add a new node to a cluster, determine which services be can be retained, and
    add new services, can
    be found in the section 
    <xref href="../../install/init-setup.dita#topic12527/join-an-existing-cluster" scope="local" format="dita">Join an Existing Cluster</xref>,
    on the page
    <xref href="../../install/init-setup.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Initializing the Cluster</xref>.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The <b>Service Memory Quotas</b> panel on the <b>Settings</b> screen of Couchbase Web Console lists all 
    services running on the cluster, and specifies
    the memory allocation for each.
    The panel is interactive, and allows the memory allocations to be changed and saved. If a modification
    attemptedly exceeds a permitted maximum or minimum,
    a notification 
    of the error is displayed, and the modification is disallowed. See 
    <xref href="../../settings/cluster-settings.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Configure Cluster Settings</xref> 
    for further information.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Minimum-required memory-quotas are:
   </p>
   
   <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="memory_quota_mimumums">

    <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
     <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="0.6*"/>
     <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Service</entry>
       <entry>Minimum Memory Quota (in MB)</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      
      <row>
       <entry>Data</entry>
       <entry>256</entry>
      </row>
      
      <row>
       <entry>Index</entry>
       <entry>256</entry>
      </row>
      
      <row>
       <entry>Search</entry>
       <entry>256</entry>
      </row>
      
      <row>
       <entry>Analytics</entry>
       <entry>1024</entry>
      </row>
      
      <row>
       <entry>Eventing</entry>
       <entry>256</entry>
      </row>
      
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   
   
  </section>

  
  <section id="initialization-and-warmup">
   
   <title>
    Initialization and Warmup
   </title>
   
   <p>
    When Couchbase Server is restarted on a node, the node goes through a <i>warmup process</i> 
    before it restarts the handling of data requests. During this warmup process, data 
    on disk is sequentially reloaded into memory. The time required for the reload
    depends on the size and configuration of the system, the amount of data persisted on
    the node, and the ejection policy configured for the buckets. 
   </p>
    
   <p>
    Frequently used items are
    identified via a scanner process, which examines an <i>access log</i>, and obtains the 
    appropriate keys. Corresponding items are then loaded with the highest priority. The scanner
    process is configurable, via the CLI utility <codeph>cbepctl</codeph>, with the <codeph>flush_param</codeph>
    parameter.
    This utility also provides the parameters <codeph>warmup_min_memory_threshold</codeph> and 
    <codeph>warmup_min_item_threshold</codeph>, which can be used to schedule the resumption of traffic
    before all items have been reloaded into memory. See
    <xref href="../../cli/cbepctl/set-flush_param.dita" scope="local" format="dita">set flush_param</xref>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section id="ejection">
   
   <title>
    Ejection
   </title>
   
   <p>
    If a bucket's memory quota is exceeded, items may be <i>ejected</i> from the bucket by the
    Data Service. Different
    <i>ejection methods</i> are available, and are configured per bucket. Note that in
    some cases, ejection is configured <i>not</i> to occur.
    For detailed information, see
    <xref href="./buckets.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Buckets</xref>.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    For each bucket, available memory is managed according to two <i>watermarks</i>, which are
    <codeph>mem_low_wat</codeph> and <codeph>mem_high_wat</codeph>.
    If data is continuously loaded into the bucket, its quantity eventually 
    increases to the value indicated by the
    <codeph>mem_low_wat</codeph> watermark. At this point, <i>paging</i> is triggered, so
    that
    memory-availability is continuously optimized. Then, as still more data is
    loaded, the data's quantity 
    increases to the value indicated by the <codeph>mem_high_wat</codeph> watermark. 
    If, based on the bucket's configuration, items can be ejected from the bucket, 
    the Data Service 
    ejects items from the bucket until
    the quantity of data has decreased to the <codeph>mem_low_wat</codeph> watermark. 
    If the rate at which data continues to be loaded is greater than that at which it is being ejected, or
    if ejection cannot be performed, the system displays an <i>insufficient memory</i>
    notification until
    sufficient memory is available.
   </p> 
   
   <p>
    Items are selected for ejection based on metadata that each contains, indicating
    whether the item can be classified as <i>Not Recently Used</i> (NRU). If an item has not been recently used, 
    it is a candidate for ejection. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The relationship of <codeph>mem_low_wat</codeph> and <codeph>mem_high_wat</codeph> to the 
    bucket's overall memory quota is illustrated as follows:
   </p>
    
    <p>
     <image href="./images/tunableMemory.png" width="416" id="tunable_memory"/>
    </p>
   
    <p>
     The default setting for <codeph>mem_low_wat</codeph> is 75%. The default setting for
     <codeph>mem_high_wat</codeph> is 85%. These settings give items from <i>active</i>
     vBuckets a 40% chance of ejection; and give items from <i>replica</i> vBuckets a
     60% chance of ejection. The default settings can be changed by means of the
     <codeph>cbepctl</codeph> utility. See
     <xref href="../../cli/cbepctl/set-flush_param.dita" scope="local" format="dita">set flush_param</xref>.
     
    </p>
   
  </section>
   
  
  <section id="expiry-pager">
   
   <title>
    Expiry Pager
   </title>
   <p>
    Scans for items that have expired, and erases them from memory and disk; after
    which, a <i>tombstone</i> remains for a default period of 3 days. The expiry pager runs
    every 60 minutes by default: for information on changing the interval, see <codeph>cbepctl</codeph>
    <xref href="../../cli/cbepctl/set-flush_param.dita" scope="local" format="dita">set flush_param</xref>.
    For more information on item-deletion and tombstones, see 
    <xref href="../buckets-memory-and-storage/expiration.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Expiration</xref>.
   </p>
  </section>  
  
  <section id="active-memory-defragmenter">
   
   <title>
    Active Memory Defragmenter
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Over time, Couchbase Server-memory can become 
    fragmented.
    Each page in memory is typically responsible for holding documents of a specific 
    size-range. Over time, if memory pages assigned to a specific size-range become sparsely populated 
    (due to documents of that size being ejected, or to items changing in size), the unused space in 
    those pages cannot be used for documents of other sizes, until a complete page is free, and that page 
    is re-assigned to a new size. Such effects, which are highly workload-dependent, may result in memory 
    that cannot be used efficiently. 
   </p> 
   
   <p>
    Couchbase Server provides an <i>Active Memory Defragmenter</i>, which periodically scans the 
    cache, to identify pages that are sparsely used. It then repacks the items on those pages, to 
    free up space.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  
 </body>
</topic>
