<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "reference.dtd">
<reference xml:lang="en-us" id="cbhealthchecker_tool">
	<title><cmdname>cbhealthchecker</cmdname></title>
	<shortdesc>The <codeph>cbhealthchecker</codeph> tool generates a health report named <i>Cluster
		Health Check Report</i> for a cluster.</shortdesc>
	<refbody>
		<section><title>Syntax</title>
			<p>The format of the <codeph>cbhealthchecker</codeph> command is:</p>
			<codeblock>cbhealthchecker CLUSTER -u [username] -p [password] [options]</codeblock>
		</section>
		
		<section><title>Description</title><p>The <codeph>cbhealthchecker</codeph> report provides data
				that helps administrators, developers, and testers determine whether the cluster is
				healthy or has any issues. These issues might require that you address them soon to
				prevent future problems or to address them immediately.</p>The tool first retrieves
			data from the Couchbase Server monitoring system, and then aggregates it over a time
			scale, analyzes the statistics against thresholds, and generates a report. Unlike other
			command line tools such as <codeph>cbstats</codeph> and <codeph>cbtransfer</codeph> that
			use the TAP protocol to obtain data from the monitoring system,
				<codeph>cbhealthchecker</codeph> obtains data by using the REST API and the
			memcached protocol.<p>You can generate reports on the following time scales: minute,
				hour, day, week, month, and year. The tool outputs an HTML file, a text file, and a
				JSON file. Each file contains the same information — the only difference between
				them is the format of the information. All <codeph>cbhealthchecker</codeph> output
				is stored in a <codeph>reports</codeph> folder. The tool does not delete any files
				from the folder. You can delete files manually if the <codeph>reports</codeph>
				folder becomes too large. The path to the output files is displayed when the run
				finishes.</p><note type="note"><codeph>cbhealthchecker</codeph> is automatically
				installed with Couchbase Server. You can find the tool in the following locations,
				depending on your platform:</note></section>
		
		<section><title>Options</title>
			<p>This tool has the following options:</p>
			
			<table>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
					<colspec colname="col2" colwidth="2.56*"/>
					<colspec colname="col3" colwidth="2.44*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Option</entry>
							<entry>Syntax</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>CLUSTER</entry>
							<entry><codeph>-c HOST[:PORT]</codeph>
								<codeph>--cluster=HOST[:PORT]</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Hostname and port of a node in the cluster. The default port is
								8091.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>USERNAME</entry>
							<entry><codeph>-u USERNAME</codeph>
								<codeph>--user=USERNAME</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Admin username of the cluster.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>PASSWORD</entry>
							<entry><codeph>-p PASSWORD</codeph>
								<codeph>--password=PASSWORD</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Admin password of the cluster.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>OPTIONS</entry>
							<entry><codeph>-b BUCKETNAME</codeph>
								<codeph>--bucket=BUCKETNAME</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Specific bucket on which to report. The default is all
								buckets.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry/>
							<entry><codeph>-i FILENAME</codeph>
								<codeph>--input=FILENAME</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Generate an analysis report from an input JSON file.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry/>
							<entry><codeph>-o FILENAME</codeph>
								<codeph>--output=FILENAME</codeph></entry>
							<entry>File name for the HTML report. The default output file name is
								the report time stamp, for example:
									<codeph>2013-07-26_13-26-23.html</codeph>.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry/>
							<entry><codeph>-h</codeph>
								<codeph>--help</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Show the help message and exit.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry/>
							<entry><codeph>-s SCALE</codeph>
								<codeph>--scale=SCALE</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Time span (scale) for the statistics: minute, hour, day, week,
								month or year. The default time span is
								<codeph>day</codeph>.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry/>
							<entry><codeph>-j</codeph>
								<codeph>--jsononly</codeph></entry>
							<entry>Collect data and output only a JSON file. When you use this
								option, the analysis report is not generated.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		
		
		<table>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="col1"/>
				<colspec colname="col2"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Operating System</entry>
						<entry>Location</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><b>Linux</b></entry>
						<entry><filepath>/opt/couchbase/bin/</filepath></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><b>Windows</b></entry>
						<entry><filepath>C:\Program Files\Couchbase\Server\bin\</filepath></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><b>Mac OS X</b></entry>
						<entry><filepath>/Applications/Couchbase Server.app/Contents/Resources/couchbase-core/bin/</filepath></entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		</section>
		
	
		
		
		<section><title>Examples</title>Runs a report on all buckets in the cluster for the past
				day:<codeblock>cbhealthchecker -c 10.3.1.10:8091 -u Administrator -p password

bucket: default
  node: 10.3.1.10 11210
  node: 10.3.1.11 11210
................................

The run finished successfully.
Please find html output at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/2013-07-23_16-29-02.html'
and text output at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/2013-07-23_16-29-02.txt'.
</codeblock><p>Runs
				a report on all buckets in the cluster for the past
				month:</p><codeblock>cbhealthchecker -c 10.3.1.10:8091 -u Administrator -p password -s month

The run finished successfully.
Please find html output at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/2013-07-26_13-26-23.html'
and text output at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/2013-07-26_13-26-23.txt'.
</codeblock><p>Runs
				a report only on the <codeph>beer-sample</codeph> bucket for the past year and
				outputs the HTML report to a file named
				<codeph>beer-health-report.html</codeph>.</p><codeblock>cbhealthchecker -c 10.3.1.10:8091 -u Administrator -p password -o beer-health-report.html \
      -b beer-sample -s year

The run finished successfully.
Please find html output at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/beer-health-report.html'
and text output at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/2013-07-26_15-57-11.txt'.
</codeblock><p>Generates
				only the statistics and outputs them in a JSON
			file:</p><codeblock>cbhealthchecker -c 10.3.1.10:8091 -u Administrator -p password -j

The run finished successfully.
Please find collected stats at '/opt/couchbase/bin/reports/2013-07-26_13-30-36.json'.
</codeblock></section>
		
		
		
		<section><title>HTML Report</title>
		<p>You can view the HTML report in any web browser. If you copy the report to another
			location, be sure to copy all the files in the reports folder to ensure that the report
			is displayed correctly by the browser. When you have multiple HTML reports in the
			folder, you can use the tabs at the top of the page to display a particular report. (If
			the tabs do not function in your browser, try using Firefox.)</p>
		<p>Throughout the report, normal health statuses are highlighted in green, warnings are
			highlighted in yellow, and conditions that require immediate action are highlighted in
			red. When viewing the report, you can hover your mouse over each statistic to display a
			message that describes how the statistic is calculated.</p>
		<p>The report begins with a header that lists the statistics scale, the date and time the
			report was run, and an assessment of the overall health of the cluster. The following
			figure shows the report header:</p>
		<fig>
				<image href="../images/health-report-header.png" width="480"></image>
			</fig>
		
			<p>The body of the report is divided into several sections: Couchbase — Alerts</p>
		
		<p>The alerts section contains a list of urgent issues that require immediate attention. For
			each issue, the report lists the symptoms detected, the impact of the issue, and the
			recommended corrective action to take. This section appears in the report only when
			urgent issues are detected. The following figure shows a portion of the alerts section
			of a report:</p>
		
		<fig><image href="../images/health-report-alerts.png" width="480">
			</image></fig>
			
			
	<dl>
		<dlentry>
			<dt>Couchbase Server cluster overview</dt>
			<dd>The cluster overview section contains cluster-wide metrics and metrics for each bucket
				and node in the cluster. This section appears in all reports. The following figure shows
				a portion of the cluster overview section of a report:
				
				<fig><image href="../images/health-report-cluster-overview.png" width="480">
				</image></fig></dd>
		</dlentry>
	</dl>		
		<dl>
			<dlentry>
				<dt>Couchbase — Warning Indicators</dt>
				<dd>The warning indicators section contains a list of issues that require attention. For each
					issue, the report lists the symptoms detected, the impact of the issue, and the
					recommended corrective action to take. This section appears in the report only when
					warning indicators are detected. The following figure shows a portion of the warning
					indicators section of a report:
					
					<fig><image href="../images/health-report-warnings.png" width="480">
					</image></fig></dd>
			</dlentry>
		</dl>	
			
			
		
		
		
		
		</section>
		
	</refbody>

</reference>
