<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="concept_ybj_tqs_zs">
    <title>Error Types</title>
    <body>
        <section id="devguide-data-errors">
            <title>Data errors</title>
            <p>Data errors are errors returned by the data store because a certain data condition
                was not met. Data errors typically have very clear corrective paths.</p>
            <p><b>Item not found</b></p>
            <p>If an item is not found, then it has either not yet been created or has since been
                deleted. It is received on retrieval (<i>get</i>) operations (get an item),
                    <i>replace</i> operations (replace an item that already exists), and
                    <i>remove</i> operations (delete an existing item).</p>
            <p>If this error is received when attempting to retrieve an item, then the item should
                either be created (if possible) or return an error to the user.</p>
            <p>If this error is received when replacing an item, then it indicates an issue in the
                application state (perhaps you can raise an exception up the stack). If you do not
                care that the item exists, the <i>upsert</i> method may be used instead.</p>
            <p>If receiving this error when removing an item, it may safely be ignored: not-found on
                remove essentially means the item is already removed.</p>
            <p>The Not Found error is returned by the server.</p>
            <p><b>Item already exists</b></p>
            <p>The <i>insert</i> operation require that the item not yet exist; it is intended to
                create a new unique record (think about inserting a “new user ID”). This error is
                returned by the server when an item already exists. Applications at this point
                should probably return an error up the stack to the user (when applicable); for
                example indicating that a new account could not be registered with the given user
                name, since it already exists.</p>
            <p><b>CAS mismatch</b></p>
            <p>A <xref href="http://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/4.5/developer-guide/cas-concurrency.html" format="html" scope="external">CAS</xref> mismatch error is
                returned when an operation was executed with a CAS value (supplied by the
                application) and the CAS value passed differs from the CAS value on the server. The
                corrective course of action in this case is for the application to re-try the
                read-update cycle as explained in detail in the CAS documentation.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="devguide-transient-errors">
            <title>Transient and resource errors</title>
            <p>These errors may be received because of resource starvation.</p>
            <p><b>Temporary failure</b></p>
            <p>This item is received during mutations when the cluster node has run out of memory.
                Its disk and replication queues are full and must wait until items in those queues
                are stored and replicated before it can begin receiving new operations.</p>
            <p>While this condition is rare, it may happen under massively concurrent writes from
                clients and a limited memory allocation on the server.</p>
            <p>The short-term corrective action for this error is to throttle and slow down the
                application, giving Couchbase some time for pending operations to complete before
                issuing new operations. The long term corrective action is to increase memory
                capacity on the cluster, either by adding more RAM to each node, or by adding more
                nodes.</p>
            <p>The temporary failure error is returned from the server.</p>
            <p><b>Timeouts</b></p>
            <p><b>Network errors</b></p>
            <p><b>Missing nodes</b></p>
            <p>
                <note>See: Handling missing node errors:</note>
            </p>
        </section>
        
    </body>
</topic>
