<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="toplevel">
  <title>Flushing Buckets</title>
  <body>
    <p id="management-intro">The primary means for managing clusters is through the Couchbase Web UI which provides an
            easy to use interface for adding, removing, monitoring and modfying buckets. In some
            instances you may wish to have a programmatic interface, for example if running as part
            of a setup script, or if setting up buckets for testing.</p>
        <p id="after-creation">Once the bucket has been created, you must wait for it to become
            ready. This is because the bucket is actually created in the background. You may need to
            wait some time until the bucket becomes ready by repeatedly trying to connect to it,
            until it succeeds.</p>
      <p id="flush-intro">When a bucket is flushed, all its content is removed. Because this
            operation is dangerous it is disabled by default for each bucket. Bucket flusing may be
            useful in test environments where it becomes a simpler alternative to removing and
            creating a test bucket. You may enable bucket flushing on a per-bucket basis using the
            Couchbase Web Console or when creating a bucket.</p>
      <p id="index-management">You can create and drop N1QL indexes using the SDK. This is
            especially useful when setting up new applications, or simply when ensuring that a given
            bucket has certain indexes defined. Indexes can be defined using actual N1QL statements
            or by using convenience functions within the SDK.</p>
        <p id="ddoc-intro">You can create, delete, retrieve, and publish design documents (used for MapReduce views)
            using the SDK. This is useful when setting up new applications, updating view
            definitions, or running tests.</p>
      <note id="ddoc-async-warning">Management APIs are considered to be asynchronous, which means you may need to
          wait some time (or poll manually) until the design document becomes available. This
          is done by repeatedly querying the newly created view until it no longer fails with
          a <i>not found</i> error.</note>
  </body>
</topic>
