<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_mcl_p5p_k4">
  <title>Configuring XDCR replications</title>
  <shortdesc>XDCR replications are configured on a per-bucket basis.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Configure the replications from the <uicontrol>XDCR</uicontrol> tab of the Couchbase Web
      Console on a bucket basis. To replicate data from all buckets in a cluster, individually
      configure replication for each bucket.</p>
    <section><title>Before configuring XDCR</title>
   
    <ul>
      <li>Configure all nodes within each cluster to communicate with all the nodes on the
        destination cluster. XDCR uses any node in a cluster to replicate between the two
        clusters.</li>
      <li>Ensure that all Couchbase Server versions and platforms match. For instance, if you want to replicate
        from a Linux-based cluster, you need to do so with another Linux-based cluster.</li>
      <li><!-- When XDCR performs replication, it exchanges data between clusters over TCP/IP port 8092;-->Couchbase Server uses TCP/IP port 8091 to exchange cluster configuration information. If
          you are communicating with a destination cluster over a dedicated connection or the
          Internet, you should ensure that all the nodes in the destination and source clusters can
          communicate with each other over ports 8091 and 8092.</li>
    </ul>
    <p><codeph>Ongoing Replications</codeph> are the ones that are configured and operating
        currently. You can monitor the current configuration, current status, and the last time a
        replication process was triggered for each configured replication.</p><p>Under the XDCR tab you
        can also configure <codeph>Remote Clusters</codeph> for XDCR; these are named destination
        clusters you can select when you configure replication. When you configure XDCR, the destination
        cluster reference should point to the IP address of one of the nodes in the destination
        cluster.</p>
      
      <!-- <p>Before you set up replication via XDCR, be certain that a destination bucket already exists. If
        this bucket does not exist, replication via XDCR may not find some vBuckets on the destination
        cluster. Only some data from the source bucket is replicated, and replication will be
        significantly delayed. You will be  required to retry replication multiple times in order to
        fully replicate the source bucket to the destination.</p>
    <p>Therefore, make sure that you check that a destination bucket exists. The recommended
        approach is to read on any key from the bucket. If you receive the error <systemoutput>key
          not found</systemoutput>  or the document for the key, the bucket exists and is available
        to all nodes in a cluster. You can do this via a Couchbase SDK with any node in the cluster. </p>  -->
 
      <fig>
        <image href="../images/ui-xdcr-panel.png" width="720" align="left"/>
      </fig></section>
    
    
    
    
  </body>
</topic>
