<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic1880">
	<title>View Basics</title>
	<shortdesc>Views allow you to extract specific fields and information from data and create an
		index.</shortdesc>
	<body>
		<p>The purpose of a view is to take the unstructured or semistructured data stored within your
			Couchbase Server database, extract the fields and information that you want, and produce an
			index of the selected information. Storing information in Couchbase Server using JSON makes
			the process of selecting individual fields for output easier. The resulting generated
			structure is a view on the stored data. The view that is created during this process lets
			you iterate, select, and query the information in your database from the raw data objects
			that have been stored.</p>
		<p>The following diagram shows a brief overview of this process.</p>

		<image href="images/views-basic-overview.png" width="600px" />

		<p>In the above example, the view takes the Name, City and Salary fields from the stored
			documents and then creates an array of this information for each document in the view. A
			view is created by iterating over every document within the Couchbase bucket and outputting
			the specified information. The resulting index is stored for future use and updated with
			new data stored when the view is accessed. The process is incremental and therefore has a
			low ongoing impact on performance. Creating a new view on an existing large data set might
			take a long time to build, but updates to the data are quick.</p>
		<p>The view definition specifies the format and content of the information generated for each
			document in the database. Because the process relies on the fields of stored JSON, if the
			document is not JSON or the requested field in the view does not exist, the information is
			ignored. This enables the view to be created even if some documents have minor errors or
			lack the relevant fields altogether.</p>
		<p>One of the benefits of a document database is the ability to change the format of documents
			stored in the database at any time without requiring a wholesale change to applications or
			a costly schema update before doing so.</p>
	</body>
</topic>
