<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_cjj_ks4_1v">
  <title>Search Facets</title>
  <body>
    <p>Facets are aggregate information collected on a particular result set. So, you have to
      already have a search in mind, and then you collect additional facet information along with
      it. All of the facet examples below are for the query "<codeph>water</codeph>" on the
      beer-sample dataset.</p>
    <p>FTS supports 3 types of facets: <ul>
        <li>Term Facet - A term facet counts up how many of the matching documents have a particular
          term in a particular field. Most of the time this only makes sense for relatively low
          cardinality fields, like a type or tags. It would not make sense to use it on a unique
          field like an ID.</li>
        <li>Numeric Range Facet - A numeric range facet works by the user defining their own buckets
          (numeric ranges). The facet then counts how many of the matching documents fall into a
          particular bucket for a particular field.</li>
        <li>Date Range Facet - same as numeric, but on dates instead of numbers <note>For Developer
            Preview, Date Range Facets are not supported.</note></li>
      </ul><note>Most of the time, when building a term facet you want to use the keyword analyzer.
        Otherwise multi-term values get tokenized and the results are not what you
      expect.</note></p>
    <section><title>Examples</title>
      <ol>
        <li>Term Facet - computes facet on the type field which has 2 values: <codeph>beer</codeph>
          and <codeph>brewery</codeph>.
          <codeblock>curl -X POST -H "Content-Type: application/json" \
http://localhost:9110/api/index/bix/query \
-d '{
  "size": 10,
  "query": {
    "boost": 1,
    "query": "water"
  },
  "facets": {
    "type": {
      "size": 5,
      "field": "type"
     }
   }
}'</codeblock>
          The result snippet below only shows the facet section for clarity. Run the curl command to
          see the HTTP response containing the full results.
          <codeblock>"facets": {
    "type": {
      "field": "type",
      "total": 91,
      "missing": 0,
      "other": 0,
      "terms": [
        {
          "term": "beer",
          "count": 70
        },
        {
          "term": "brewery",
          "count": 21
        }
       ]
     }
}</codeblock></li>
        <li>Numeric Range Facet - computes facet on the <codeph>abv</codeph> field with 2 buckets
          describing <codeph>high</codeph> (greater than 7) and <codeph>low</codeph> (less than 7).
          <codeblock>curl -X POST -H "Content-Type: application/json" \
http://localhost:9110/api/index/bix/query \
-d '{
  "size": 10,
  "query": {
    "boost": 1,
    "query": "water"
  },
  "facets": {
    "abv": {
      "size": 5,
      "field": "abv",
      "numeric_ranges": [
        {
          "name": "high",
          "max": 7
        },
        {
          "name": "low",
          "min": 7
         }
       ]
     }
   }
}'</codeblock>
          Results:
          <codeblock>facets": {
    "abv": {
      "field": "abv",
      "total": 70,
      "missing": 21,
      "other": 0,
      "numeric_ranges": [
        {
          "name": "high",
          "max": 7,
          "count": 57
        },
        {
          "name": "low",
          "min": 7,
          "count": 13
         }
      ]
    }
}</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
