<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_cmy_jzk_1v">
  <title>Index Mapping</title>
  <body><section><title>Default Index Mapping</title>
    <p>The simplest way to create an index is to use the default index mapping with no further customization.  This is what you did in the <xref href="fts-quick-start.dita">quick start</xref>. <term>Default index mapping</term> refers to the index mapping that Couchbase Server uses for JSON documents that don’t match a more specific document mapping based on document type. This example relies on dynamic mapping, explained later, to decide how to index the individual fields in the documents. <note type="warning">Using the default index mapping with dynamic mapping is a good way to ensure that full text search is working properly on a small set of data, but it’s not very selective so it tends to write a lot of information into the index. For this reason, default index mapping may be slow or result in high load if used on a production-sized dataset. </note></p><ol>
      <li>Click the button <uicontrol>New Full Text Index</uicontrol>. <image placement="break"
            href="pict/fts-create-index.png" width="570" id="image_x44_s1l_1v"/></li>
      <li>Give your index a name like “<userinput>beer-sample-idx</userinput>” and select the bucket
          you want to index from the dropdown. If you click on “<uicontrol>Type
          Mappings</uicontrol>,” you will only see one type listed, which is
            “<systemoutput>default</systemoutput>.” <image placement="break"
            href="pict/fts-create-index-2.png" width="300" id="image_s1h_x1l_1v"/></li>
      <li>Click the “<uicontrol>Create Index</uicontrol>” button. You will then see a screen that
          shows you how many documents are in your index and the percentage complete. <image
            placement="break" href="pict/fts-create-index-3.png" width="300" id="image_zn3_1bl_1v"
          /></li>
      <li>Click on the <uicontrol>Full Text</uicontrol> link again to search the index you just created.</li>
      <li>Your search shows the list of document IDs that contain the best matches for whatever search you ran, in order of score, with the highest scoring document listed first.</li>
    </ol>
  </section>
    
  </body>
</topic>
