<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_rfg_qjt_xs">
  <title>Deploying Couchbase on Google Cloud Launcher</title>
  <body>
    <section><title>Prerequisites</title>
    <ul>
      <li>You must have a Google account with access to Google Cloud Platform. If not, sign up for
        one <xref href="https://console.cloud.google.com/start" format="html" scope="external"
            >here</xref> before proceeding.</li>
      <li>The free trial version of Google Cloud Platform limits to using no more than 8 cores
          running at the same time. You can proactively request quota adjustments from the <xref
            href="https://console.cloud.google.com/projectselector/iam-admin/quotas" format="html"
            scope="external">Quotas</xref> page in the Cloud Platform Console. </li>
    </ul></section>
    <section><title>Deploying Couchbase Enterprise</title>
      <note type="important">The templates are provided as a starting point for development and
        testing purposes, and may be customized as needed. Note that additional post deployment
        setup may be required. </note>
      <ol>
        <li>Log in to your Google Cloud Platform account and navigate to the Google Cloud Launcher
          page for <xref
            href="https://console.cloud.google.com/launcher/details/couchbase-public/couchbase-enterprise-edition"
            format="html" scope="external">Couchbase Enterprise Edition</xref>. If you wish to bring
          your own license, navigate to <xref
            href="https://console.cloud.google.com/launcher/details/couchbase-public/couchbase-enterprise-edition-byol"
            format="html" scope="external">Couchbase Enterprise Editon - BYOL</xref> instead. <image
            placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-cloud-launcher-couchbase-enterprise.png" width="570"
            id="image_z2g_wnx_4bb"/></li>
        <li> Click <uicontrol>Launch on Compute Engine</uicontrol>. On the <uicontrol>New Couchbase
            Enterprise Edition deployment</uicontrol> screen, configure the VM settings. <image
            placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-new-couchbase-ee-deploy-config-regions.png" width="570"
            id="image_fxz_hrf_pbb"/><p>
            <image placement="break"
              href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-new-couchbase-ee-deploy-config-vm.png" width="570"
              id="image_ypx_nrf_pbb"/>
          </p><table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table-gcp-deployment-settings">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
              <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.51*"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Field Name</entry>
                  <entry>Description</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Deployment name</entry>
                  <entry>Provide a deployment name. We recommend using a shorter name as the
                    deployment name has a character limit and the template will truncate longer
                    names automatically. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Regions</entry>
                  <entry>Google Cloud Platform has a wide range of locations available. Pick a
                    location where you want your cluster to be deployed.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Couchbase Server</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Server Node Count</entry>
                  <entry>
                    <p>Enter the number of Server Nodes to deploy.</p>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Server Node Type</entry>
                  <entry>
                    <p>Select the machine type for your server nodes. You can choose to customize
                      your machine type using the Customize link.</p>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Server pd-ssd disk size in GB</entry>
                  <entry>Enter the disk size for each of the server nodes. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Server Version</entry>
                  <entry>Choose the Couchbase Server version to deploy. <note>The <xref
                    href="https://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/mobile/current/installation/index.html#story-h2-1"
                    format="html" scope="external">Compatibility Matrix</xref> summarizes the
                    compatible versions of Sync Gateway and Couchbase Server.</note></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">Couchbase Sync Gateway</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Sync Gateway Node Count</entry>
                  <entry>Enter the number of Sync Gateway Nodes to deploy.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Sync Gateway Node Type</entry>
                  <entry>Select the machine type for your sync gateway nodes. You can choose to
                    customize your machine type using the Customize link.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Sync Gateway pd-ssd disk size in GB</entry>
                  <entry>Enter the disk size for each of the sync gateway nodes. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Couchbase Sync Gateway Version</entry>
                  <entry>Choose the Couchbase Sync Gateway version to deploy. <note>The <xref
                        href="https://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/mobile/current/installation/index.html#story-h2-1"
                        format="html" scope="external">Compatibility Matrix</xref> summarizes the
                      compatible versions of Sync Gateway and Couchbase Server.</note></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></li>
        <li>Click Deploy. Deployment begins and you will be redirected to the Deployment Manager
          where the deployment status is displayed. <image placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-new-couchbase-ee-deploy-inprogress.png" width="570"
            id="image_adm_jl1_qbb"/></li>
        <li>You should see a green check mark once deployment completes successfully. <note type="important">Note the
            Couchbase Username and Password displayed on the screen.</note><image placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-new-couchbase-ee-deploy-done.png" width="570"
            id="image_r4k_pl1_qbb"/>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>That's it! It may take a short while for Couchbase to be up and running. </p>
      <p>At this point a number of Instance Group Managers have been deployed. It may take several
        minutes for the VMs that the Instance Group Managers manage to start, and for their start-up
        scripts to complete installing and configuring Couchbase.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="logging-in">
      <title>Logging in to Your Couchbase Cluster</title>
      <p>You can log in to the Couchbase cluster and explore the items created. <ol>
        <li>To inspect the resources that have been deployed and log in to Couchbase Server:<ol
        id="ol_fwp_4m1_qbb"><li>Click the Products &amp; services icon <image placement="inline"
          href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-icon-prdt-services.png" width="32" height="32"
          id="image_gbp_zm1_qbb"/> at the top left of the screen to pull down the sidebar and
          select <uicontrol>Compute Engine</uicontrol> > <uicontrol>Instance Groups</uicontrol>.
          You can see a list of all the Instance groups being deployed. Depending on how quickly
          you get to this step after starting deployment, the instance groups may still be
          deploying. <image placement="break" href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-instance-groups.png"
            width="570" id="image_d1r_y41_qbb"/></li>
        <li>Click a server instance group to view details such as CPU utilization and the VM
                instances in that group. Note the <b>External IP</b> of one of the deployed
                  VMs.<image placement="break"
                  href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-server-igm-details.png" width="570"
                  id="image_ppx_tp1_qbb"/></li>
        <li>Open a browser tab and enter the copied External IP along with port 8091 as
                    <filepath>&lt;<varname>external-ip</varname>>:8091</filepath> to open the
                Couchbase Server Web Console. <image placement="break"
                  href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-web-console-login.png" width="570"
                  id="image_dsy_5r1_qbb"/></li>
          <li>Enter the user name and password noted when deployment completed. <note type="tip">If
                  you forgot to note the credentials, you can retrieve them by examining the Custom
                  metadata > startup-script for the server instance template. <image
                    placement="break"
                    href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-instance-template-startup-script.png"
                    width="450" id="image_ir3_lbb_qbb"/></note> The dashboard shows the current view
                of the cluster. If you've gotten to this step quickly, the cluster may still be
                adding nodes and rebalance may be in progress. Once the process complete, the
                dashboard will look something like the following screen capture.<image
                  placement="break" href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-web-console-dashboard.png"
                  width="570" id="image_tyy_f51_qbb"/>Click the Servers tab to explore the server
                nodes that have been created. <image placement="break"
                  href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-web-console-servers.png" width="570"
                  id="image_h3b_x51_qbb"/></li>
        </ol><p>You can click around to explore, load sample buckets and run queries from the Query Workbench. You
          can also setup XDCR links between the different clusters created by the deployment.</p></li> <li>To log in to the Sync Gateway Admin portal: <ol id="ol_fzy_nw1_qbb">
              <li>Click the Products &amp; services icon <image placement="inline"
                  href="images/gcp/deploying/gcp-icon-prdt-services.png" width="32" height="32"
                  id="image_e51_4w1_qbb"/> at the top left of the screen to pull down the sidebar
                and select <uicontrol>Compute Engine</uicontrol> > <uicontrol>Instance
                  Groups</uicontrol>. You can see a list of all the Instance groups being deployed.
                Depending on how quickly you get to this step after starting deployment, the
                instance groups may still be deploying. <image placement="break"
                  href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-instance-groups.png" width="570"
                  id="image_f51_4w1_qbb"/></li>
              <li>Click a sync gateway instance group to view details such as CPU utilization and
                the VM instances in that group. Note the <b>External IP</b> of one of the deployed
                VMs. <image placement="break"
                  href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-sync-gateway-igm-details.png" width="570"
                  id="image_wnw_tw1_qbb"/></li>
              <li>Open a browser tab and enter the copied External IP along with port 4984 as
                    <filepath>&lt;<varname>external-ip</varname>>:4984</filepath>. This opens the
                interface for Couchbase Sync Gateway which is already setup and configured to
                connect to an empty bucket on the cluster. </li>
              <li>Open another browser tab and enter
                  <filepath>&lt;<varname>external-ip</varname>>:4984/_admin/</filepath> to open the
                Couchbase Sync Gateway Admin Portal. <image placement="break"
                  href="images/gcp/logging-in/gcp-sync-gateway-admin-portal.png" width="570"
                  id="image_s3r_3x1_qbb"/></li>
            </ol></li></ol></p>
    </section>
    <section id="scaling"><title>Scaling Your Couchbase Cluster</title>
      <p>Scaling Couchbase is simplified greatly on Google Cloud Platform. This section describes
        how to scale up your cluster up in three simple steps.</p> 
      <ol
          id="ol_fnc_myn_nbb">
          <li>Log in to Google Cloud Platform and navigate to <uicontrol>Compute Engine</uicontrol>
          > <uicontrol>Instance Groups</uicontrol> and select the server instance that you want to
          scale. <image placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/scaling/gcp-server-instance-group-members.png" width="570"
            id="image_xhf_wy1_qbb"/></li>
        <li>On the <uicontrol>Details</uicontrol> tab, click <uicontrol>Edit Group</uicontrol> and
          edit the number of instances.<image placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/scaling/gcp-server-instance-group-details.png" width="570"
            id="image_ccy_bz1_qbb"/><image placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/scaling/gcp-server-instance-group-edit-number.png" width="570"
            id="image_zlz_2z1_qbb"/></li>
        <li>Click <uicontrol>Save</uicontrol>. You'll see a notification that the group is being
          updated. <image placement="break"
            href="images/gcp/scaling/gcp-server-instance-updating.png" width="570"
            id="image_s1g_jz1_qbb"/><p>Once updated, you can see the updated number of instances
            reflected on the server Instance group Details tab.<image placement="break"
              href="images/gcp/scaling/gcp-server-instance-updated.png" width="570"
              id="image_m3j_tz1_qbb"/></p><p>On a different browser tab, you can log in to the
            Couchbase Server Web Console to see the additional server nodes that were added to your
            cluster. <image placement="break"
              href="images/gcp/scaling/gcp-web-console-servers-rebalance.png" width="570"
              id="image_a5c_zz1_qbb"/></p></li></ol>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
