<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic1805">
  <title>Replication via memcached protocol</title>
  <shortdesc>XDCR can replicate data through the memcached protocol at a destination cluster.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>XDCR replication via memcached protocol utilizes highly efficient memcached protocol on the
      destination cluster for replicating changes. The new mode of XDCR increases XDCR throughput
      reducing the CPU usage on the destination cluster and improving XDCR scalability. </p>
    
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>CAPI mode
          XDCR</dt>
        <dd>In earlier versions of Couchbase Server, only the REST protocol could be used for
          replication. On a source cluster, a work process batched multiple mutations and sent the batch
          to a destination cluster using the REST interface. The REST interface at the destination node
          unpacked the batch of mutations and sent each mutation via a single memcached command. The
          destination cluster then stored mutations in RAM. This process is known as <term>CAPI mode
            XDCR</term> since it relies on the REST API known as <codeph>CAPI</codeph>.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
   <dl>
     <dlentry>
       <dt>XMEM mode XDCR</dt>
       <dd>This mode available for XDCR is known as <term>XMEM mode XDCR</term>. It bypasses the
          REST interface and replicates mutations via the memcached protocol at the destination
          cluster: </dd>
         <dd>
          <image href="../images/XDCR_xmem.png" id="image_ljx_xx2_xq" placement="break" align="left"
            width="500"/>
        </dd>
       <dd>In <codeph>XMEM mode XDCR</codeph>, every replication process at the source cluster
          delivers mutations directly via the memcached protocol on the remote cluster. This mode
          does not impact the current XDCR architecture; rather it is implemented completely within
          the data communication layer used in XDCR. Any external XDCR interface remains the same.
          The benefit of using this mode is improved performance, achieved by increasing XDCR
          throughput, improving XDCR scalability, and reducing CPU usage at the destination cluster
          during replication.</dd>
     </dlentry>
   </dl>
   
    <p>XDCR can be configured to operate via the new <codeph>XMEM</codeph> mode, which is the
      default, or with <codeph>CAPI</codeph> mode. To change the replication mode, change the
      setting for <codeph>xdcr_replication_mode</codeph> via the Couchbase Web Console or REST API. </p>
  </body>
  <related-links>
    <linklist>
      <link href="../REST/rest-xdcr-intro.dita"></link>
    </linklist>
  </related-links> 
</topic>
