<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic2809">
 <title>Production Views</title>
 <shortdesc>Production views are used in a deployed environment.</shortdesc>
 <body>
  <p>Due to the nature of the Couchbase cluster and because of the size of the datasets that can be
   stored across a cluster, the impact of view development needs to be controlled. Creating a view
   implies the creation of the index which could slow down the performance of your server while the
   index is being generated. However, views also need to be built and developed using the actively
   stored information.</p>
  <p>To support both the creation and testing of views, and the deployment of views in production,
   Couchbase Server supports two different view types, Development views and Production views. The two
   view types work identically, but have different purposes and restrictions placed upon their
   operation.</p>
  <ul>
   <li><b>Production views</b></li>
  </ul>
  <p>Production views are optimized for production use. A production view has the following
   attributes:</p>
  <ul>
   <li>Production views always operate on the full dataset for their respective bucket.</li>
   <li>Production views can either be created from the Web Console or through REST API. From the Web
    Console, you first create development views and then publish them as production views. Through
    REST API, you directly create the production views (and skip the initial development
    views).</li>
   <li>Production views cannot be modified through the UI. You can only access the information
    exposed through a production view. To make changes to a production view, it must be copied to a
    development view, edited, and re-published.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>Views can be updated by the REST API, but updating a production design document immediately
   invalidates all of the views defined within it.</p>
  <ul>
   <li>Production views are accessed through a different URL to development views.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>The support for the two different view types means that there is a typical work flow for view
   development, as shown in the figure below:</p>

  <fig>
   <image href="images/view-types-workflow.png" width="480"/>
  </fig>

  <p>The above diagram features the following steps:</p>
  <ol>
   <li>Create a development view and view the sample view output.</li>
   <li>Refine and update your view definition to suit your needs, repeating the process until your
    view is complete. During this phase you can access your view from your client library and
    application to ensure it suits your needs.</li>
   <li>Once the view definition is complete, apply your view to your entire Cluster dataset.</li>
   <li>Push your development view into production. This moves the view from development into
    production, and renames the index (so that the index does not need to be rebuilt).</li>
   <li>Start using your production view.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Individual views are created as part of a design document. Each design document can have
   multiple views, and each Couchbase bucket can have multiple design documents. You can therefore
   have both development and production views within the same bucket while you development different
   indexes on your data.</p>

  <p>For information on publishing a view from development to production state.</p>

 </body>
 

</topic>
