<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_xvc_fcq_dt">

 <title>Data Modeling</title>

 <shortdesc>Couchbase Server is a multi-model database that natively manipulates data in key-value form or in JSON documents. Unlike relational databases which require strict predefined schema with tables and columns, Couchbase Server requires no predefined schema. Each JSON document represents its own schema and can specify its own set of attributes per document.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  <p>With Couchbase Server, applications can define their schema at the application layer and freely evolve their schema with no added administrative action. Schema changes do not require scheduling downtime nor do they trigger long running, offline updates to existing data.</p>
  <p>Couchbase Server supports both document and key-value data natively. Document-based data
   representation allows complex objects to be natively represented with full fidelity in Couchbase
   Server. Key-value representation can be mixed with document-centric design and is typically used
   to optimize access for extreme low latencies. </p>
  <!--<p>At a high level, a data modeling exercise is typically done in 2 phases: <ul>
   <li><b>Logical data modeling</b>: This phase focuses on describing your entities, their attributes and relationships. Logical data modeling phase is independent of the underlying containers your database platform provides.</li>
   <li><b>Physical data modeling</b>: In this phase you take the logical design and apply the entities and relationships to the containers provided to you by the Couchbase Server platform. Based on the access patterns, performance requirements, and atomicity and consistency requirements, you can choose which type of containers to use to represent your logical data model.</li>
  </ul></p>-->
  <section> <title>Relational Data Modeling vs Document Oriented Data Modeling</title>
   <p>In a relational database system you must define a schema before adding records to a database. The schema is the structure described in a formal language supported by the database and provides a blueprint for the tables in a database and the relationships between tables of data. Within a table, you need to define constraints in terms of rows and named columns as well as the type of data that can be stored in each column.</p>
   <p>In contrast, a document-oriented database contains documents, which are records that describe the "schema" of the data in the document, as well as the actual data. Documents can be as complex as you choose; you can use nested data to provide additional sub-categories of information about your object. You can also use one or more documents to represent a real-world object. The following example compares a conventional table with document-based objects. </p>
   <fig id="fig_tpv_jjz_bw" >
    <title>1-to-many relationship comparison between relational table and JSON documents</title>
    <image href="images/relational-1-many-hotels.png" id="image_upv_jjz_bw" width="500"
     placement="break"/>
    <image href="images/nosql-1-many-hotels.png" id="image_onh_njz_bw" width="500"/>
   </fig> 
   <p>In this example we have a table that represents “hotels” and their respective attributes: name, address, city, and so forth. The relational model conforms to a schema with a specified number of fields which represent a specific purpose and data type. There is also a one-to-many relationship that is normalized to the “hotel reviews” table which also contains its own attributes from date of the review to the ratings. Normalization is common practice in the relational model that requires you to decompose data into smaller related tables</p>
   <p>The equivalent document-based model has an individual document per “hotel”. Each document contains the <!--same type of -->information for a specific “hotel” and embeds the “hotel reviews” in the document as an array.</p>
   <p>In a document-oriented model, data objects are stored as documents; each document stores your data and enables you to update the data or delete it. Instead of columns with names and data types, you describe the data in the document, and provide the value for that description. If you want to add attributes to a “hotels” or “hotel reviews” table in a relational model, you need to modify the database schema to include the additional columns and their data types. In the case of document-based data, you just add the additional key-value pairs representing the new fields to your document.</p></section>
  <section><title>Using JSON Documents</title><p>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a lightweight
    data-interchange format which is easy to read and change. JSON is language-independent although
    it uses similar constructs to JavaScript. JSON documents enable you to benefit from all new
    Couchbase features, such as indexing and querying; they also to provide a logical structure for
    more complex data and enable you to provide logical connections between different
    records.</p><p>JSON supports the following basic data types: <ul>
     <li>Numbers, including integer and floating point</li>
     <li>Strings, including all unicode characters and backslash escape characters</li>
     <li>Boolean: true or false</li>
     <li>Arrays, enclosed in square brackets: [“one”, “two”, “three”]</li>
     <li>Objects, consisting of key-value pairs, and also known as an associative array or hash. The
      key must be a string and the value can be any supported JSON data type. </li>
    </ul></p><p>For more information on creating valid JSON documents, see <xref
     href="http://www.json.org" format="html" scope="external"/>.</p><p>When you use JSON documents
    to represent your application data, you should think about the document as a logical container
    for information. This involves thinking about how data from your application fits into natural
    groups. It also requires thinking about the information you want to manage in your application.
    Data modeling for Couchbase Server is similar to the process that you would follow for
    traditional relational databases; however, there is much more flexibility and you can change
    your data structures later on. </p><p>A sample entity may be a “hotel” you represent for a
    travel web site that provides information on many hotels. The "hotel" entity may contain many
    attributes such as name and address, and may contain embedded structured like reviews that can
    represent individual reviews users have submitted for a given hotel.
    <codeblock>{  
   “type”:“hotel”,
   "address":"Capstone Road, ME7 3JE",
   "city":"Medway",
   "country":"United Kingdom",
   "hotel_name":"Medway Youth Hostel",
   "reviews":[  
      {  
         "author":"author::Ozella_Sipes",
         "content":"This was our 2nd trip here and we enjoyed it as much or more than last year. ",
         "date":"2013-06-22 18:33:50 +0300",
         "ratings":{  
            "Cleanliness":5,
            "Location":4,
            "Overall":4,
            "Rooms":3,
            "Service":5,
            "Value":4
         }
      },
      {  
         "author_id":"author::Barton_Marks",
         "content":"We found the hotel de la Monnaie through Interval and we thought we'd give it a try while we attended a conference in New Orleans. This place was a perfect location and it definitely beat staying downtown at the Hilton with the rest of the attendees",
         "date":"2015-03-02 19:56:13 +0300",
         "ratings":{  
            "Business service (e.g., internet access)":4,
            "Check in / front desk":4,
            "Cleanliness":4,
            "Location":4,
            "Overall":4,
            "Rooms":3,
            "Service":3,
            "Value":5
         }
      }
   ]
},</codeblock></p><p>In
    traditional relational database modeling, you would create tables that contain a subset of
    information for an entity. Just like the example above, a hotel may contain many reviews which
    are stored in a separate table and referenced by the <parmname>hotel_id</parmname>. In case of
    JSON documents, you use key-values pairs, or even nested key-value pairs and don’t have to break
    “hotels” and “hotel reviews” apart. </p>Given the boundary-less nature of the document model,
   there are several considerations to have in mind when you design your JSON document: <ul
    id="ul_dxd_xpz_bw">
    <li>Whether you want to use a type field at the highest level of your JSON document in order to
     group and filter object types, for instance the above example includes a “type” attribute that
     has the value “hotel”.</li>
    <li>What particular keys, ids, prefixes or conventions do you want to use for items, for
     instance ‘Hotel::Medway_Youth_Hostel.’</li>
    <li>If want to use a document to access other documents. In other words, you can store keys that
     refer other documents in a JSON document and get the keys through this document. For instance,
     the above example includes <parmname>author_id</parmname> under reviews that refer to the
     detailed information on authors.</li>
   </ul></section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
