<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="analytics_service">
 
 <title>Analytics Service</title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  The <i>Analytics Service</i> provides a parallel data-management capability; allowing
  the running of complex analytical queries.
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Understanding Analytics
   </title>
  
    <p>
     The Analytics Service supports large <i>join</i>, <i>set</i>, <i>aggregation</i>, and
     <i>grouping</i> operations: these activities are anticipated often to employ large amounts
     of data, and therefore to be highly
     consumptive of processor, networking, and memory resources; highly demanding in terms of 
     cross-node coordination; and of extensive duration. 
    </p>
   
   <p>
    <i>Analytic queries</i> can be either <i>predetermined</i> or <i>ad hoc</i>; 
    <i>predetermined</i> queries often providing greater efficiency. The Analytics Service
    further enhances efficiency by supporting parallel query-processing and bulk data-handling;
    and by allowing analytic queries to be run on <i>indexes</i>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Deploying the Analytics Service
   </title>
   
   <p>
    The Analytics Service relies on the 
    <xref href="./data-service.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Data Service</xref>, 
    which must therefore be running on at least
    one of the cluster nodes. For the Analytics Services to use
    <i>indexes</i>, the
    <xref href="./index-service.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Index Service</xref>
    must also be running on at least one of the cluster nodes.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Due to the large scale and duration of operations it is likely to perform, the Analytics Service should be 
    run <i>alone, on its own cluster node, with no other Couchbase Service running on that node</i>.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    For the practical steps required to initialize or join a cluster, and to deploy services, see
    <xref href="../../../install/init-setup.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Initialize the Cluster</xref>.
    For information on how to run analytic queries, see the
    <xref href="../../../analytics/introduction.html" scope="local" format="html">Introduction</xref> to
    Couchbase Analytics.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
 </body>
</topic>
