<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="concept_tcf_byn_vs2">
 
 <title>
  Data Service
 </title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  The Data Service provides access to data. 
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
 
 <section>
  <title>
   Understanding the Data Service
  </title>
  
  <p>
   The <i>Data Service</i> is the most fundamental of all Couchbase services, providing access
   to data in memory and on disk. The memory allocation for the Data Service is configurable. The
   Data Service must run on at least one node of every cluster.
  </p>
  
  <p>
   The architecture of the Data Service is illustrated as follows:
  </p>
  
  <p>
   <image href="./images/dataServiceArchitecture.png" id="data_service_architecture" align="left" width="780"/>
  </p>
  
  <p>
   The principal components are:
  </p>
  
  <p>
   
  </p>
  
  <ul>
   <li>
    <b>Dispatcher</b>: Manages networking, by handling each <b>Request</b> for data, and providing the
    <b>Response</b>. Also streams data to other nodes within the cluster, and to other clusters, by means
    of the <b>DCP</b> protocol; and handles <b>Authentication</b>.
    
    <p>
     For information on <b>DCP Streaming</b>, see
     <xref href="../../clusters-and-availability/clusters-and-availability.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Clusters and Availability</xref>.
     For information on <b>Authentication</b>, see
     <xref href="../../../security/security-authentication.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Authentication</xref>.
     For information on ports used by the dispatcher, see
     <xref href="../../../install/install-ports.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Network Configuration</xref>.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    </p>
   </li>
   
   <li>
    <b>KV Engine</b>: A collection of facilities that is provided for each bucket on the cluster. These are:
    
    <p>
    </p>
    
    <ul>
     <li>
      <b>Managed Cache</b>: The memory allocated for the bucket, according to an established quota. 
      This contains <i>Partition Hash Tables</i>, whereby
      the location of bucket-items, in memory and on disk, on different nodes across the cluster, is recorded. When
      written, items enter the cache, and subsequently are placed onto a replication queue, so as to be replicated
      to one or more other nodes; and (in the case of items for Couchbase buckets) onto a disk queue, so as to
      be written to disk. 
      
      <p>
       For information on memory quotas, see
       <xref href="../../buckets-memory-and-storage/memory.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Memory</xref>. 
       For information on how items from a bucket are assigned to <i>vBuckets</i> across a cluster, see
       <xref href="../../buckets-memory-and-storage/vbuckets.dita" scope="local" format="dita">vBuckets</xref>.
       For illustrations of how items are written and updated for Couchbase buckets, see
       <xref href="../../buckets-memory-and-storage/memory-and-storage.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Memory and Storage</xref>.
      </p>
      <p>
       
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Checkpoint Manager</b>: Keeps track of item-changes, using data structures named <i>checkpoints</i>. Changes
      already made to items in memory, but not yet placed on the replication and disk queues, are recorded.
      <p>
       
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Item Pager</b>: Ejects from memory items that have not recently been used, in order to free up space, as required.
      For further information, see
      <xref href="../../buckets-memory-and-storage/memory.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Memory</xref>. 
      <p>
       
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Flusher</b>: Deletes every item in the bucket. For information on how to activate, see
      <xref href="../../../clustersetup/bucket-flush.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Flush a Bucket</xref>.
      <p>
       
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Expiry Pager</b>: Scans for items that have expired, and erases them from memory and disk; after
      which, a <i>tombstone</i> remains for a default period of 3 days. The expiry pager runs
      every 60 minutes by default: for information on changing the interval, see <codeph>cbepctl</codeph>
      <xref href="../../../cli/cbepctl/set-flush_param.dita" scope="local" format="dita">set flush_param</xref>.
      For more information on item-deletion and tombstones, see 
      <xref href="../../buckets-memory-and-storage/expiration.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Expiration</xref>.
      <p>
       
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Batch Reader</b>: Enhances performance by combining changes made to multiple items into <i>batches</i>, 
      which are placed on the disk queue, to be written to disk.
      <p>
       
      </p>
     </li>
    </ul>
    
    <p>
     
    </p>
   </li>
   
   <li>
    <b>Scheduler</b>: A pool of threads, mainly purposes for handling I/O. The threads are divided into four kinds, which
    run independently of and without effect on one another:

    <p>
    </p>
    
    <ul>
     <li>
      <b>Non IO</b>: Tasks private to the scheduler that do not require disk-access; including
      connection-notification, checkpoint removal, and hash-table resizing.
      
      <p>
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Aux IO</b>: Fetch, scan, and backfill tasks.
      
      <p>
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Reader IO</b>: Threads that read information from disk.
      
      <p>
      </p>
     </li>
     
     <li>
      <b>Writer IO</b>: Threads that write information to disk.
      
      <p>
      </p>
     </li>
     
    </ul>
    
    <p>
     For more information on the Data Service' threading model, see
     <xref href="../../buckets-memory-and-storage/storage.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Storage</xref>.
    </p>
   
   </li>
   
  </ul>
  
 </section>
 

  
  
 </body>
 
</topic>
