<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_gfm_j5f_ps">
 <title>Couchbase Server architecture</title>
	<shortdesc> Couchbase Server is an open source scalable NoSQL database engine. The core architecture is designed to simplify building modern applications with a flexible data model and core database platform abilities ranging from high availability, high scalability, high performance all the way to security.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
<p>Couchbase Server consists of a single package that is installed on all nodes. Using SDKs (also known as smart client connectivity libraries), you can write applications in the language of your choice (Java, node.js, .NET, or others). The applications connect to a Couchbase Server cluster to perform read and write operations, and run queries with low latencies (sub millisecond) and high throughput (millions of operations per second).</p>
<p>To understand the Couchbase Server’s runtime behavior, it is important to understand the high level connectivity, replication, storage, caching, and security runtimes. For more information about the core runtime behavior, see the following topics: <ul>
   <li><xref href="connectivity-architecture.dita">Connectivity architecture</xref></li>
   <li><xref href="high-availability-replication-architecture.dita">Replication architecture</xref></li>
   <li><xref href="storage-architecture.dita">Storage architecture</xref></li>
   <li><xref href="managed-caching-layer-architecture.dita">Caching layer architecture</xref></li>
   <li><xref href="../security/security-intro.dita">Security architecture</xref></li>
  </ul></p><p>The Couchbase Server consists of the following core components: Cluster Manager, Data service, Index service, and Query service. The runtime behaviors such as replication, storage, caching, and so on can be tuned to the needs of the different services. For more information about the core components, see the sections under <xref href="cluster-manager.dita">Cluster manager</xref> and <xref href="services-archi-multi-dimensional-scaling.dita">Services architecture</xref>. <fig id="fig_bpd_dpn_vs">
    <title>Nodes, services, and cluster</title>
    <image placement="break" href="images/server-cluster-single-node-type.png" width="600"
     align="left" id="image_cpd_dpn_vs"/>
   </fig>
  </p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
