<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
  
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="compression">
 
 <title>
  Data Compression
 </title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  Couchbase Server supports <i>data compression</i> in its communications
  with internal and external clients, and in its internal handling of documents.
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
  
  <section id="data-compression-overview">
   
   <title>
    Overview
   </title>
   
   <p>
    The compression of data allows RAM and disk-space to be used with increased efficiency. It may
    also reduce consumption of network bandwidth. Higher consumption of CPU resources may result.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Compression, provided by the open-source library
    <xref href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snappy_(compression)" scope="external" format="html">Snappy</xref>,
    is applied to documents based both on the client's capabilities and on the compression <i>mode</i> established
    by the user for the given bucket.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Compression is available only in Couchbase Enterprise Edition, and can be applied only to Couchbase and 
    Ephemeral buckets.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section id="where-data-compression-can-be-used">
   
   <title>
    Where Compression is Used
   </title>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./images/compression-overview-diagram.png" id="compression-overview-diagram" align="left" width="600" />
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Clients based on the Couchbase SDK (<b>1</b>), nodes within a cluster that participate
    in intra-cluster replication (<b>4</b>), internal Couchbase Services (<b>5</b>),
    external DCP clients (<b>6</b>), and remote clusters that participate in Cross Data-Center
    Replication (<b>7</b>) communicate their ability to send and receive compressed
    documents by using the <codeph>HELO</codeph> command, with a flag that confirms support of the <i>Snappy
     Compression</i> data type. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Couchbase Server may (depending on the mode of the bucket) store documents in compressed form in 
    memory (<b>2</b>). The server always compresses
    documents when storing them on disk (<b>3</b>).
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section id="compression-modes">
   
   <title>
    Compression Modes
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Each bucket
    is configured to support one of three <i>modes</i>. After a client has communicated
    its ability to send and receive compressed data, the server's running of compression and decompression routines 
    depends on the
    mode supported by the specified bucket. The modes are as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    
   </p>
   
   <ul>
    
    <li>

     <b>Off</b>: Provides the
     behavior of Couchbase Server pre-5.5. On receipt of a compressed document,
     Couchbase Server decompresses the document when storing in memory; and recompresses it
     when storing on disk. Couchbase Server
     sends the document in uncompressed form.  
     This mode is assigned by default to buckets <i>upgraded</i> from a previous
     version of Couchbase Server.
     The mode is recommended for use where clients cannot benefit from compression, and
     where neither memory-resources nor network-bandwidth will be negatively impacted by the size and
     quantity of documents to be handled. Note also that this is the only mode under which Memcached buckets
     operate.
     

    </li>
    
    <li>
      <b>Passive</b>: On receipt of a compressed document,
      Couchbase Server stores it in compressed form both in memory
      and on disk. Couchbase Server
      sends the document back to the client in compressed form if this is requested by the client; otherwise,
      it sends the document back in uncompressed form.
      On receipt of an uncompressed document, Couchbase Server
      stores it in memory in uncompressed form, and stores it on disk in compressed form. 
      It returns the document to the client in uncompressed form.
      This mode is assigned by default to <i>new</i> buckets, in
      Couchbase Server 5.5 and beyond. It supports clients that themselves handle compresion, and
      additionally allows Couchbase Server to
      to limit its use of memory-resources and network-bandwidth. At the same time, it does not force 
      Couchbase Server to use CPU
      resources for the compression and decompression of documents that clients do not
      themselves require in compressed form.
     
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
       <b>Active</b>: Couchbase Server actively compresses documents for storage in memory
       and on disk, even if the documents are received in uncompressed form. 
       Documents are decompressed before being sent back to those clients that do not
       support the receiving of compressed data. Documents are sent
       in compressed form to clients that do support the receiving of compressed data, even if those
       clients originally sent the
       documents to the server in uncompressed form.
       This mode allows the server to practice the maximum conservation of memory-resources 
       and network-bandwith. Consequently, more documents can be held in memory simultaneously, and thereby
       accessed with improved, overall efficiency (since the processing-time required for compression and
       decompression is significantly less than that required for fetching data from disk). Nevertheless, in some circumstances,
       clients that do not themselves require the compression and decompression of documents may be negatively affected by 
       the compression and decompression performed by the server on documents resident in memory.
    </li>
    
   </ul>
   
  </section>

  
  <section id="switching-between-data-compression-modes">
   
   <title>
    Switching Between Compression Modes
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Buckets can be switched between modes. The following behavior-changes
    should be noted:
   </p>
   
   <ul>
    
    <li>
     When a bucket formerly in Passive mode has been switched to Off mode,
     any compressed document that Couchbase Server receives for that bucket
     is stored in memory in uncompressed form. If the server
     needs to send from the bucket a document that is currently compressed, the server decompresses
     the document before sending: however, to preserve 
     memory-efficiency, the
     document remains compressed in memory.
     
     <p>
      
     </p>
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
     When a bucket has been switched from Passive to Active mode, it
     periodically runs a task that compresses uncompressed documents.
     
     <p>
      
     </p>
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
     When a bucket formerly in Active mode is switched to Off mode,
     this disables 
     the task that was periodically run to compress uncompressed documents.
     Compressed documents can continue to be received for the bucket, and are
     decompressed for storage in memory. Compressed documents within the bucket are
     decompressed before sending: however, to ensure continued 
     memory-efficiency, the
     document remains compressed in memory.
     
     <p>
      
     </p>
     
    </li>
    
   </ul>
   
  </section>
  
  
  
  <section id="enabling-compression">
   
   <title>
    Enabling Compression
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Couchbase Server allows authorized users to configure 
    compression by means of the following.
   </p>
   
   <ul>
    
    <li>
      <p>
       The Couchbase Web Console, 
       the Couchbase CLI, and the Couchbase REST API, which allow buckets each to be assigned a compression mode; and which allow 
       Cross Data-Center Replication (XDCR) to handle compressed documents.
      </p>
     
      <p>
       For information on using the Couchbase Web Console to create buckets, see
       <xref href="../clustersetup/create-bucket.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Create a Bucket</xref>; and
       for information on using it to set up XDCR, see
       <xref href="../xdcr/xdcr-create.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Managing XDCR</xref>
      </p>
     
     <p>
      
     </p>
    </li>
    
    
    <li>
     <p>
      The <codeph>cbbackup</codeph>, <codeph>cbrestore</codeph>, and 
      associated tools, which allow
      compressed documents to be requested in the backup stream.
     </p>
     <p>
      
     </p>
    </li>
    
    <li>
     <p>
      The Couchbase SDK, which can elect to send and receive compressed documents.
     </p>
     <p>
      
     </p>
    </li>
    
   </ul>
   
   <p>
    For information on roles that allow modification of bucket-settings, see
    <xref href="../security/security-authorization.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Authorization</xref>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
 </body>
 
</topic>
