<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_e5c_kf4_vs">
 <title>Global Secondary Indexes (GSIs)</title>
 <shortdesc>Global secondary index (GSI) is a powerful solution for secondary lookup queries that are required for interactive applications that require low latencies. Global secondary indexes (GSIs) are defined using the CREATE INDEX statement in N1QL. The CREATE INDEX statement supports the use of document attributes, N1QL expressions including functions, and a filter (a WHERE clause to limit the documents being indexed) in the index key.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  <p>The indexer for GSI processes the mutations to the bucket and creates a B+ tree for fast scans on the index key. Queries that filter on a range can use GSI to quickly acquire the document keys that satisfy the filter expression. They can then query the bucket to get the full document values and project the final query result.</p>
  <section><title>Indexing with Global Secondary Indexes</title><p>Global secondary indexes (GSIs)
    are defined using the CREATE INDEX statement in N1QL. The CREATE INDEX statement supports the
    use of document attributes and N1QL expressions including functions in the index key. Using
    CREATE INDEX, you can also define a filter (that is, a “WHERE” clause with WHERE
    type=”person_document”) to limit the index to person documents in the bucket) which in turn
    limits the documents being indexed. There can only be zero or one index key output per document
    key.</p><p>For example, you can create a global secondary index, also referred to as
     <i>index</i>, on name that indexes beer name attributes for documents of type “beer” using the
    following CREATE INDEX statement in N1QL.
    <codeblock>    CREATE INDEX Index1_beer_name 
    ON `beer-sample`(name) 
    WHERE type=”beer” USING GSI;</codeblock></p>GSI
   processes mutations in the bucket by coordinating with the following processes: <dl>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Projector and Router</dt>
     <dd>This process is responsible for processing incoming mutations on the bucket. It resides on
      the nodes that run data service and thus contains active vBuckets. This process understands
      the indexes that exist on the bucket at any given time and processes incoming mutation to only
      send the relevant information to the Supervisor process for maintaining indexes. <p>Every node
       has a single projector and router process which runs the data service. It can listen on all
       buckets on the node, if there are indexes on these buckets. Projector and router process
       sends a stream of changes per bucket to each node running the index service. Indexes may
       index only a small set of the attributes in a document and may filter documents to index a
       subset of the documents in a bucket. The stream of changes is optimized to only contain
       relevant information for the indexes created on the nodes running the index service.
      </p></dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
     <dt>Supervisor</dt>
     <dd>This process is responsible for both processing mutations sent by the projector and router
      process for the indexes it maintains, and for responding to scan requests from N1QL queries
      that are executed as part of the query service. It resides on the nodes that run the index
      service. <p>Each node running the index service can contain different indexes (for example,
       index 1 and 2 can be on node A while index 3 and 4 can be on node B). Each index only indexes
       mutations from one bucket but each node running the index service may contain indexes from
       multiple buckets (for example, index 1 and 3 can be indexes on bucket X and index 2 and 4 can
       be indexes on bucket Y). Indexes may index a small set of the attributes in a document and
       may filter to documents to only index a subset of the documents in a bucket.</p><p>Every node
       has a single supervisor process which runs the index service. The supervisor process listens
       to change streams from the projector and router processes from all nodes running the data
       service. It evaluates the incoming stream of changes for the specific indexes created on the
       node running the index service. The stream of changes is optimized to only contain relevant
       information for the indexes created on the nodes running the index service. This ensures
       optimized data exchange and faster indexing between the projector and router process and
       supervisor process. This is especially important when using multidimensional scaling to
       deploy data service and index service to independent set of nodes within the cluster creating
       dedicated zones inside the cluster.</p><p>When a mutation arrives at the bucket, the mutation
       is processed in memory by the vBucket manager that is responsible for the document key in the
       data service. The mutation is then queued for replication with DCP to propagate the mutation
       to replica vBuckets, to the views on the bucket, and to the projector and router process for
       GSI processing. The projector and router process picks up the mutation from DCP and removes
       the attributes that are not part of index filter or definition on any of the GSI indexes
       being maintained on nodes running the index service. The supervisor process picks up the
       stream of changes and applies them to the indexes maintained locally on the node. <fig
        id="fig_l4h_t4h_zs">
        <title>Execution flow of Global Secondary Indexes (GSIs)</title>
        <image placement="break" href="images/global-secondary-indexes.png" width="600"
         id="image_m4h_t4h_zs"/>
       </fig></p></dd>
    </dlentry>
   </dl></section>
  <section><title>Index storage </title>
   <p>The supervisor process uses the ForestDB storage engine to persist changes to the individual indexes to disk. Each index gets a dedicated file. An append only write operation is used to maintain the files. This optimizes writes and requires compaction to clean up the orphaned space, much like the Couchstore storage subsystem used in the data service for the database engine. For more information about compaction and differences between ForestDB and Couchstore, see <xref href="storage-architecture.dita">Storage Architecture</xref>.</p>
  </section>
  <section><title>GSI and high availability </title>
  <p>Unlike the database engine or the views engine, Global Secondary Indexes do not provide automatic built-in replicas. As an administrator, you can manually create replicas with GSIs by using the index service to create identical indexes on separate nodes. To create redundant copies of an index, you can create the same index definition with different index names on different nodes that are running the index service. 
  </p>
   <p>If one of the copies of the index is not available due to a node failure, N1QL queries automatically redirect and use the available identical index for the execution of the query. This ensures that the index service has an index available for faster query execution as long as a one copy of the index is available on one of the index service nodes.</p>
   <p>The following example shows how to place two indexes on two separate nodes (nodeA and nodeB)
    that have identical definitions using the WITH clause.
    <codeblock>     CREATE INDEX Index1_beer_name 
     ON `beer-sample`(name) 
     WHERE type=”beer” USING GSI WITH {"nodes":"nodeA:8091"};
     CREATE INDEX Index2_beer_name 
     ON `beer-sample`(name)
     WHERE type=”beer” USING GSI WITH {"nodes":"nodeB:8091"};  </codeblock></p>
  </section>
  <section><title>GSI and index mirroring and partitioning </title>
   <p>With global secondary indexes, you can place each index only on a single node. However, as an administrator, you can create an identical index definition and place each index on a separate node to engage multiple nodes when executing highly concurrent queries. When identical index definitions on separate nodes are available, N1QL queries use the round-robin algorithm to load balance the index scan operations. This ensures each index on each node takes an equal share of the index scan workload and engages both the nodes for best performance. As an administrator, you can create more indexes with identical definitions to scale-out the index scans to additional nodes. See the example described in the previous section on "GSI and high availability".</p>
   <p>An index definition can define a filter to limit the documents being indexed. As an administrator, you can partition indexes by splitting them into multiple smaller segments and placing the individual segments in separate nodes to engage multiple nodes for processing highly concurrent queries. </p>
   <p>The following example illustrates partitioning the beer_name index into segments using a
    BETWEEN clause. Index1_beer_name1 specifies names that are between “A” and “C”, while
    Index1_beer_name2 specifies names between “C” and “F”, and so on.
    <codeblock>    CREATE INDEX Index1_beer_name1 
    ON `beer-sample`(name) 
    WHERE type="beer" AND name BETWEEN "A" AND "C"
    USING GSI WITH {"nodes":"nodeA:8091"};
    
    CREATE INDEX Index1_beer_name2 
    ON `beer-sample`(name) 
    WHERE type="beer" AND name BETWEEN "C" AND "F"
    USING GSI WITH {"nodes":"nodeB:8091"};
    ...  </codeblock></p>
   <p> The first query below uses Index1_beer_name1 index to return the result which only engages
    nodeA as the index is created on nodeA, while the second query scans Index_beer_name2 index
    which is on nodeB.
    <codeblock>     SELECT * FROM `beer-sample` 
     WHERE type="beer" AND name = "Blackberry";
     
     SELECT * FROM `beer-sample` 
     WHERE type="beer" AND name = "Downtown Brown";  </codeblock>
   </p>
  </section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
