<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA General Task//EN" "generalTask.dtd">
<task id="kafka-3-quickstart">
    <title>Quickstart</title>
    <shortdesc>This section shows how to add the connector to your application.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
        <section>
            <title>Installing the Kafka Connector</title>
            <p>At a minimum, Java 6 is required, but any newer version is also supported (including Java 8).</p>
            <p>The connector is shipped as a zip archive and available here for download:
            <xref href="http://packages.couchbase.com/clients/kafka/3.1.0/kafka-connect-couchbase-3.1.0.zip"
                    format="html" scope="external">kafka-connect-couchbase-3.1.0.zip</xref></p>
            <p>The location of the archive contents depends on how the <xref
            href="http://docs.confluent.io/current/installation.html" format="html" scope="external">Confluent
            Platform</xref> was installed. In general it should be placed so that the
            <codeph>share/java/kafka-connect-couchbase</codeph> directory of the archive is at the same level as
            <codeph>kafka-connect-jdbc</codeph>.</p>
            <p>If you are only using <xref href="https://kafka.apache.org/"
            format="html" scope="external">Apache Kafka</xref>, the connector should be in the path
            (e.g. <codeph>kafka_2.11-0.10.1.0/libs</codeph>. The Apache Kafka version of this sample will be almost the
            same except it cannot use Confluent-specific features provided by the <xref
            href="http://docs.confluent.io/3.1.1/control-center/docs/index.html" format="html" scope="external">Control
            Center</xref> or <xref href="http://docs.confluent.io/3.1.1/schema-registry/docs/index.html" format="html"
            scope="external">Schema Registry</xref> products.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Sample</title>
            <p>To see basic functionality of the connector, we'll copy a single bucket from a local Couchbase instance.
            Start by loading one of the sample buckets, or pick your own. In this simple example we will use
            <codeph>travel-sample</codeph> from the server distribution.</p>
            <p>We create a configuration file that will load data from this database. This file is included with the connector 
                in <filepath>config/quickstart-couchbase.properties</filepath> and contains the following settings:</p>
            <codeblock outputclass="language-properties"><![CDATA[name=test-couchbase
connector.class=com.couchbase.connect.kafka.CouchbaseSourceConnector
tasks.max=2
connection.cluster_address=127.0.0.1
connection.bucket=default
connection.timeout.ms=2000
# connection.ssl.enabled=true
# connection.ssl.keystore.location=/tmp/keystore
# connection.ssl.keystore.password=secret
topic.name=test-default
use_snapshots=false
]]></codeblock>
            <p>For our case, we will only modify <codeph>connection.bucket</codeph> to <codeph>travel-sample</codeph>
            (or the bucket loaded on the first step).</p>
            <p>The first three settings are common for all connectors. The
            <codeph>connection.cluster_address</codeph> specifies the comma-separated list of cluster nodes, which
            should be used to bootstrap the connector. The <codeph>use_snapshots</codeph> setting indicates how we want to
            handle the stream of changes from the server. In this case, we have told the connector to send each event to
            the Kafka topic immediately, while setting this property to <codeph>true</codeph> will tell the connector task
            to accumulate events in local memory until the whole snapshot is received. The <codeph>topic.name</codeph>
            contains the name of the Kafka topic, where all the events will be stored. For simplicity, we don't
            configure secure connections in this sample, it will be shown later.</p>
            <p>Run the connector in a standalone Kafka Connect worker in another terminal (this uses
            <filepath>config/connect-standalone.properties</filepath> from the connector distribution and assumes that
            Kafka and the Schema Registry are running locally on the default ports):</p>
            <codeblock outputclass="language-bash"><![CDATA[$ ./bin/connect-standalone config/connect-standalone.properties \
        config/quickstart-couchbase.properties]]></codeblock>
            <p> You should see the process start up and log some messages.  Then it will begin receiving events from
            Couchbase Server and sending the results to Kafka. In order to check that it has copied the data that was
            present when we started Kafka Connect, start a console consumer, reading from the beginning of the topic:</p>
            <codeblock outputclass="language-text"><![CDATA[$ ./bin/kafka-avro-console-consumer --new-consumer --bootstrap-server localhost:9092 \
        --topic test-default --from-beginning
{"event":"mutation","partition":104,"key":"route_60137","cas":1479128706711552,"bySeqno":1,"revSeqno":1,"expiration":{...
{"event":"mutation","partition":104,"key":"airport_5736","cas":1479128706973696,"bySeqno":2,"revSeqno":1,"expiration":{...
{"event":"mutation","partition":104,"key":"landmark_5574","cas":1479128707104768,"bySeqno":3,"revSeqno":1,"expiration":{...
...
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The output will display about 31,000 lines, each containing mutation (assuming sample bucket hasn't been modified after creation). 
                The shape of the payload is controlled by the <codeph>dcp.message.converter.class</codeph> property of the connector config. 
                By default it set to <codeph>com.couchbase.connect.kafka.converter.SchemaConverter</codeph>, which formats events into structure 
                with meta information on the top level and optional value as bytestring in <codeph>content</codeph> property. 
                The Avro schema for this converter is shown below:</p>
            <codeblock outputclass="language-json"><![CDATA[{
  "type": "record",
  "name": "DcpMessage",
  "namespace": "com.couchbase",
  "fields": [
    {
      "name": "event",
      "type": "string"
    },
    {
      "name": "partition",
      "type": {
        "type": "int",
        "connect.type": "int16"
      }
    },
    {
      "name": "key",
      "type": "string"
    },
    {
      "name": "cas",
      "type": "long"
    },
    {
      "name": "bySeqno",
      "type": "long"
    },
    {
      "name": "revSeqno",
      "type": "long"
    },
    {
      "name": "expiration",
      "type": [
        "null",
        "int"
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "flags",
      "type": [
        "null",
        "int"
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "lockTime",
      "type": [
        "null",
        "int"
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "content",
      "type": [
        "null",
        "bytes"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "connect.name": "com.couchbase.DcpMessage"
}]]></codeblock>
            <p>Where the <codeph>event</codeph> property describes the kind of event, and can take one of the following values:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><codeph>mutation</codeph>: any change of the document, including creation and subdocument commands</li>
                <li><codeph>deletion</codeph>: removal or expiration of the document.</li>
                <li><codeph>expiration</codeph>: reserved for document expiration, but Server up to 4.5 does not use it.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>When all bucket contents have been transferred, open the Couchbase Admin Console and create a new
            document with ID <codeph>test</codeph> and body using the Documents UI. If you switch back to the console consumer you should see the new record added
            (and, importantly, the old entries are not repeated):</p>
            <codeblock outputclass="language-text"><![CDATA[{"event":"mutation","partition":127,"key":"test","cas":1480340133183488,"bySeqno":29,...
{"event":"mutation","partition":127,"key":"test","cas":1480340157956096,"bySeqno":30,"revSeqno":2,...]]></codeblock>
            <p>Removing the document <codeph>test</codeph> will generate a similar event:</p>
            <codeblock outputclass="language-text"><![CDATA[{"event":"deletion","partition":127,"key":"test","cas":1480340391526400,"bySeqno":32,"revSeqno":3,...]]></codeblock>
            <p>Of course, all the features of Kafka Connect, including offset management and fault tolerance, work with the source connector. You can restart and kill the processes 
                and they will pick up where they left off, copying only new data (taking into account the <codeph>use_snapshots</codeph> setting).</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Writing Data with Sink Connector</title>
            <p>Since release 3.1, the library implements Sink Connector, which allows to publish data from Kafka topics into Couchbase Server</p>
            <p>To show how it works, lets write data from the <codeph>test-default</codeph> topic we have just created
            into new empty bucket. We assume that a bucket named <codeph>receiver</codeph> exists on the server. Our configuration will look like this:</p>
    <codeblock outputclass="language-text"><![CDATA[name=test-sink-couchbase
connector.class=com.couchbase.connect.kafka.CouchbaseSinkConnector
tasks.max=1
topics=test-default
connection.cluster_address=127.0.0.1
connection.bucket=receiver]]></codeblock>
            <p>Now if you run this job, it will report some diagnostic information about processing data to standard
            output, and soon <codeph>receiver</codeph> bucket documents number will match the source
            <codeph>travel-sample</codeph>:
            <codeblock outputclass="language-bash"><![CDATA[$ ./bin/connect-standalone config/connect-standalone.properties \
        config/quickstart-couchbase-sink.properties]]></codeblock>
            </p>
        </section>
    </taskbody>
</task>
