<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="eventing_faq">
  
  <title>
    Frequently Asked Questions
  </title>
  
  <shortdesc> Some questions, frequently asked about the Eventing service and Functions. </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Frequently Asked Questions
      </title>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p> What languages are supported? </p>
          <p>Javascript is the language to be used while creating Functions. Node modules cannot be
            imported: only simple Javascript can be used. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is Eventing an MDS-enabled service? </p>
          <p>Yes. MDS enables workload isolation in a Couchbase cluster. Eventing nodes can be added
            as more Functions are added, or if the mutation rates are high. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Will all the updates to a document be seen in DCP? </p>
          <p>When a document is updated multiple times in a small time-window, not all updates are
            seen in DCP. This means that the event handlers see only those deduplicated events that
            are published in DCP. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is it supported for both text and binary formats of the documents? </p>
          <p>The value or the document must always be text in the form of a JSON document. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Can we determine what has changed on the document? </p>
          <p>No. But you can implement versioning as part of the application logic. If versioning is
            important, include it as part of the data architecture. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>What kind of node do I run my Eventing Service on? </p>
          <p>Eventing leverages the latest trends in multi-core CPUs; therefore nodes selected for
            Eventing should optimally have a higher number of cores than those for indexing. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>How does the Functions offering compare with the Couchbase’s Kafka Connector? </p>
          <p>The Functions offering is about server-side processing or compute; it does not require
            any middleware to be deployed or managed. Couchbase’s Kafka connector is an SDK
            component that needs an application container or middleware to run. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Are Functions similar to a Database Trigger? </p>
          <p>In a rough sense, Functions are similar to the Post-Triggers of the database world. But
            with Functions, the action is already completed at the data-layer, and the event handler
            gives an interface by which developers can key in the logic of what needs to happen
            ‘after’ the action is done. What a Function sees is the actual event of the change, and
            hence it does not directly correlate with Database Triggers. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Are Functions similar to a Rules Engine? </p>
          <p>Not exactly. A Rules Engine enforces ordering and other semantics that is not possible
            out of the box with Functions. However, Functions can be used to implement one - even
            Rules Engine. The Function in its purest form offers a rule to implemented closer to the
            data, but cannot trigger another Function directly. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Are Functions similar to a Stored Procedure? </p>
          <p>Stored Procedures enforce a request-response model. A stored procedure will not be
            invoked automatically; it has to be invoked by a calling method. Functions are based on
            the idea of events. Changes to the data are events. These events trigger Functions, and
            hence this is not a request-response model in its purest sense. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Do I need a separate middleware to consume the Functions? How do I consume changes in
            my middleware/application? </p>
          <p>Database changes are consumed using the Function defined: there is no other
            programmatic way of accessing the changes (such as by using an SDK, or some other form
            of middleware). REST endpoints are exposed, to perform administrative operations. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Can I import my own JS libraries or Node Modules? </p>
          <p>No. We do not allow import of node modules or external JS libraries. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Can a Function listen to all changes across Couchbase Server? </p>
          <p>A defined Function listens only to changes that are exposed using the DCP for the
            buckets (Couchbase and Ephemeral) in the data-nodes. Memcached buckets are not
            supported. The Function cannot listen to changes happening in other Couchbase
            components, such as FTS, Views, or GSI; nor can it listen to system events.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Can there be more than one Function listening to changes to a bucket? </p>
          <p>Yes. More than one Function can be defined for the same bucket. This lets you process
            the change according to the business logic that you enforce. But there is no ordering
            enforced; for example, if bucket 'wine' has three different Functions, which are
            FunctionA, FunctionB, and FunctionC, you cannot enforce the order in which these
            Functions are executed. Also, database triggers suffered from scalability and
            diagnosability issues. Functions offer multiple diagnosability solutions and is highly
            scalable and performant. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>What is the metadata bucket? Do I need to create a separate bucket? </p>
          <p>To provide better restartability semantics when an Eventing node is offline, some
            metadata needs to be stored: a Couchbase bucket solves this problem. Setting up the
            metadata bucket is a one-time activity that is done cluster-wide. It is recommended that
            the metadata bucket not be used for any other data-storage (which is to say, it should
            not be accessed by any other application). </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>What is in the "meta" Function parameter (OnUpdate, OnDelete)? Is this the metadata we
            currently write in order to figure out what has changed in the document? </p>
          <p>These are the meta fields associated with the document. For more information, refer to
            the <xref
              href="https://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/3.x/developer/dev-guide-3.0/keys-values.html"
              format="html" scope="external">Link</xref> section.  </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Are Functions supported for both KV and Document storage? </p>
          <p>The Eventing Service listens to changes that appear in the DCP. DCP is valid for the
            Data Service, and Functions operate on documents that are either in key-value or in
            document (JSON) format. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is it possible to get additional state during a Function execution? For example, can
            you read from the data service in a Function to fetch related data? For example, can we
            enrich the updated document with data from another document (using a document id)?</p>
          <p> Yes. You can read from any other bucket, and enrich the document. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Can I get old and new values of the document inside the Function? </p>
          <p>No. We do not support versioning of documents; therefore, this feature is not available
            out of the box. Though customers can have another ‘Mother’ bucket that stores documents
            that could be looked up, in order to determine the difference between the current
            document and the last modified. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Does a rebalance have any effect on the firing of events? </p>
          <p>No. Functions do not lose any mutations during a rebalance operations.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>What happens to the Eventing Service during a failover condition? </p>
          <p>When the Data Service experiences a failover condition, mutations may be lost and these
            lost mutations are not processed by the Eventing service. When the Eventing node
            experiences a failover condition, few mutations may be processed more than once. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Why can’t I create global variables? </p>
          <p>We restrict the language model in such a way that chances of going wrong are minimized.
            As Functions are stateless compute entities, global variables do not have a good
            use-case, and therefore, they are not supported. Though you can define Javascript
            functions inside a Function (outside the scope of OnUpdate and OnDelete) that can be
            invoked any number of times from either of the event handlers. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Is the ordering of document mutations enforced? </p>
          <p>All changes from a document are always processed in order. </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>What happens when a Function is debugged? </p>
          <p>We block one of the mutations alone and hand it over to the debugger session. The rest
            of the mutations continue to be serviced by the event handler.</p>
        </li>
        
      </ul>
      
     </section>
   
  </body>
</topic>
