<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="eventing_statistics">
  <title> Debugging and Diagnosability </title>
  <shortdesc> Debugging and diagnostics in the Eventing Service comprises of  debugging functions,
    logging functions, and log redaction.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <section id="debugging-functions"><title><b>Debugging Functions </b></title>Couchbase Server,
      for its Eventing Service framework, includes an online real-time Javascript Debugger. Debug is
      a special flag on a Function. The Debug option integrates seamlessly with the Google Chrome
      Debugger engine for running the Javascript code. <p><b>Debugging Workflow</b>
      </p><p>
        <ul id="ul_isj_ddz_m2b">
          <li>During a debug session, a single mutation received by the Function is considered and
            sent to the Debugger. This technique ensures that processing of the other data mutations
            in the cluster does not get blocked.</li>
          <li>The Worker in the Debugger pauses to trap the next event-instance, opens an ephemeral
            TCP port, and generates a Chrome dev-tools URL, with a session cookie that controls the
            debug worker.</li>
          <li>All other events are unaffected except the trapped event-instance.</li>
          <li>Using the Debug option, you can place breakpoints in the code and run the Function
            execution, one line at a time. The step-step execution helps while troubleshooting the
            deployed Function. </li>
          <li>If the debugged event-instance completes execution, no further event-instance gets
            trapped for debugging.</li>
          <li>Debugging is a convenience-feature intended to help during Function development: it is
            not designed for production environments. Debug mode should not be used in Product
            environments, as it affects the in-order processing of the document mutations. In a
            production environment, debug sessions introduce timing issues. If a debug session gets
            terminated during execution, then the mutation may be abruptly processed.</li>
        </ul>
      </p><p><b>Debugging a Function Using the Debug Option</b></p><p>
        <ol>
          <li>From the <b>Couchbase Web Console</b> > <b>Eventing </b>page, click on the name of a
            deployed Function. The deployed Function expands to provide additional options. Click
              <b>Edit JavaScript</b>.<p><image href="images/debug_1.png" width="600"
                id="image_hbm_xfn_n2b"/></p><p/></li>
          <li>From the <b>Edit Function</b> page, click <b>Debug</b>. A debug session gets
            activated. As a result, the next event-instance gets trapped and is forwarded to the
            Debugger.<p/>In the below screen, you can notice the message: "Waiting for mutation."
            <p/><p><image href="images/debug_2.png" width="300" id="image_f2l_ggn_n2b"
            /></p><p/></li>
          <li>Upon a data mutation, the debug URL in the Debugging pop-up gets
                populated.<p/><p><image href="images/debug_3.png" width="300" id="image_ics_lgn_n2b"
              /></p></li>
          <li>Copy the URL from the Debugging pop-up and paste it into your Google Chrome browser.
                <p><image href="images/debug_4.png" width="600" id="image_lh1_vgn_n2b"/></p></li>
          <li>From your Google Chrome browser, you can add breakpoints and run step-step diagnosis
            to debug and troubleshoot the deployed Function. From the Debugging pop-up, click
                <b><i>Stop Debugging</i></b> to terminate a debug session.</li>
        </ol>
      </p></section>
    <section id="logging-functions">
      <b>Logging Functions</b>
      <p dir="ltr">The Eventing Service creates two different types of logs:</p><ul
        id="ul_f5s_nzq_42b">
        <li>System Logs</li>
        <li>Application Logs</li>
      </ul><p><b>System Logs</b></p><p>For the Eventing Service, Couchbase Server creates a separate
        system log file, termed as eventing.log. The system log file captures all the Eventing
        Service related system errors depending on the level and severity of the reported problem.
        For every node, a single system log file gets created. </p><p>The <b>eventing.log</b>
        contains redactable user data and the log is collected using the <b>cbcollect_info</b> tool.
        For log rotation, refer to <xref href="../clustersetup/ui-logs.dita#topic180"/>.
          </p><p><b>Application Logs</b></p><p>Application logs allow you to identify and capture
        various Function related activities and errors. </p><p>All Function-related activities such
        as editing the handler code, debugging, or modifying feed boundaries conditions, get
        recorded in the Application logs. Couchbase Server creates an individual log file for every
        Function in the cluster. By default, the maximum size of an Application log file is 40MB,
        and the number of log files before rotation is 10. Unlike system logs, the Application logs
        are user configurable. You can access an Application log file using the command line
        interface. Couchbase Server creates different application log files depending on the level
        and severity of the reported problem, as configured during Function definition.</p><p>
        <note>The <b>cbcollect_info</b> tool does not collect the Application log files.</note>
      </p><p>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_gwz_g2z_m2b">
          <title>Application Logs Path in Platform</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Platform</entry>
                <entry>Location</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry dir="ltr">Linux</entry>
                <entry dir="ltr">/opt/couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/data/@eventing</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry dir="ltr">Windows</entry>
                <entry dir="ltr">C:\Program Files\Couchbase\Server\var\lib\couchbase\data\@eventing
                  (Assumes default installation location)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry dir="ltr">Mac OS X</entry>
                <entry dir="ltr">/Users/&lt;user>/Library/Application
                  Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/data/@eventing </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </p><p dir="ltr">To configure an Application log, use the REST endpoint settings option.
        </p><p dir="ltr"><b>Sample URL</b>:
          <codeph>192.168.1.5:8091/_p/event/api/v1/functions/&lt;Function_name>/settings
        </codeph></p><p dir="ltr"><b>Sample Payload</b>:
        <codeblock>{
  "settings":
    {
      "app_log_max_files": 10,
      "app_log_max_size": 10485760
    }
  }</codeblock></p><p
        dir="ltr">The sample payload above illustrates that the system stores 10 application log
        files and each file records about 10 MB of data. </p><p dir="ltr">At some point in time, old
        application log files that are no longer necessary need to be deleted to make way for new
        log records. When an Application log file reaches the set limit, a new log file gets
        created. All the recorded information from the active log file gets transferred to this
        newly created file.</p>For illustration, consider <b>enrich_ip_nums</b> as the name of the
      Function. A corresponding Application log file, <b>enrich_ip_nums.log</b>, gets created in the
      Couchbase cluster. Whenever the <b>enrich_ip_nums.log</b> reaches 10MB in size, assuming the
      maximum size of an Application log file is 10MB and the number of log files before rotation is
      10, the system automatically generates the <b>enrich_ip_nums.log.1</b> file, during its first
      iteration. The file <b>enrich_ip_nums.log</b> transfers all the log information to this new
      log file. For this illustration, since the number of log files is 10, the system stores 10
      such files, the currently active log file along with 9 truncated files, at any given
      instance.</section>
    <section id="log-redaction"><title>Log Redaction</title>
      <p>You can use logs for multiple purposes ranging from security, monitoring, and diagnostics.
        Suppression of sensitive data such as personally identifiable information (PII), hostnames,
        internal asset information, credit card details, during the logging operation is termed as
        log redaction. Organizations implement log redaction as part of their legal compliance and
        security risk mitigations.</p>
      <p>Couchbase Server provides a capability to redact sensitive user data from getting captured in the logs. All sensitive data are scrubbed and gets removed from the log files. Post redaction, log files can be shared for troubleshooting without disregarding any regulatory compliance.</p>
      <p>For details, see <xref href="../clustersetup/logging.dita#logging/understanding_redaction"/>.
        <!--<ol>
          <li>From the Couchbase Web Console Logs tab, select <uicontrol>Collect
              Information</uicontrol>.</li>
          <li>Select all nodes or use the <uicontrol>filter nodes…</uicontrol> option to select
            nodes from where you want to collect logs and diagnostic information.</li>
          <li>From the <b>Redact Logs</b> pane select <b>No Redaction</b> or <b>Partial
              Redaction</b>.<ul id="ul_h3y_f3v_42b">
              <li><b>No Redaction</b>: Select this option to enable capturing of log data that may
                include any sensitive information. </li>
              <li><b>Partial Redaction</b>. Select this option to enable abstraction of sensitive
                information in the log files.<p>When the Partial Redaction option is selected,
                  Couchbase automatically stores two types of files, one with redaction and another
                  without data redaction. Use the log file without data redaction for internal
                  troubleshooting purposes, and in case you are using the <b>Upload to Couchbase</b>
                  log option, use the log file with data redaction. The above information message
                  also gets displayed in the Web console UI as follows: <systemoutput>"Couchbase
                    Server will collect and save a redacted log file at the location you specify,
                    but also save an unredacted version which could be useful for further
                    troubleshooting. If you use the "Upload to Couchbase" feature below, ONLY the
                    redacted log will be uploaded."</systemoutput></p></li>
            </ul></li>
        </ol>--></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
