<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_h12_hqn_vs">
  <title>Cluster Settings</title><shortdesc>Use this screen to configure cluster
    settings.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    
    <p>Use the Cluster tab to configure the cluster name, RAM quota, index settings, and so on. </p>
    <p><image href="../admin/picts/settings-cluster.png" id="image_dcr_5zz_zs" align="left"
        width="720"/></p>
    <section><title>Configure Cluster</title>
      
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Cluster Name</dt>
          <dd>The name that was given during the initial setup, which you can edit in the UI, change
            with the CLI command or with a call to the REST API:
              <codeblock>couchbase-cli setting-cluster -c localhost -u Admin -p Pass --cluster-name=”New Cluster Name” </codeblock><p>or</p><codeblock>curl -u Admin:Pass -X POST http://localhost:8091/pools/default -d clusterName=”New Cluster Name”</codeblock></dd>
          
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Certificate</dt>
        <dd>The self-signed SSL certificate that is deployed across the cluster on each node. It is
            provided to set up secure communication in an XDCR environment, all nodes in a cluster
            have the same certificate. Click to display the certificate. It is also possible to
            retrieve the certificate using the <xref
              href="../rest-api/rest-xdcr-data-encrypt.dita#rest-xdcr-data-encrypt">REST API</xref>
            or save to a file with the CLI
              command:<codeblock> curl http://localhost:8091/pools/default/certificate</codeblock><p>or</p><codeblock> couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c localhost -u Admin -p Pass  --retrieve-cert=/tmp/cert.file</codeblock><p>You
              can re-generate he SSL certificate by clicking on <uicontrol>Regenerate</uicontrol>,
              trigger a new SSL certificate with  the <xref
                href="../rest-api/rest-xdcr-data-encrypt.dita#rest-xdcr-data-encrypt">REST
                API</xref> or generate a new certificate and save it to a file with the CLI
              command:</p><p>Example:</p><codeblock> curl -u Admin:Pass -X POST http://localhost:8091/controller/regenerateCertificate</codeblock><p>or</p><codeblock>  couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c localhost -u Admin -p Pass --regenerate-cert=/tmp/cert.file </codeblock></dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
      <note type="note">SSL Encryption is only available in the Enterprise Edition of Couchbase Server.</note>  
        
   
      
    </section>
    <section><title>Cluster RAM Quota</title>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>RAM Available</dt>
          <dd>The per-node RAM that is available to Couchbase services limited to the smallest node
            in the cluster.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Data RAM Quota</dt>
          <dd>Per node memory allocation for the key-value cache used by the data service. At a
            minimum, it cannot be made smaller than the sum per node bucket quota of all buckets
            combined. This value can be adjusted in the UI, with the CLI or with the REST API.
              <p>Example:</p><codeblock> couchbase-cli setting-cluster -c localhost -u Admin -p Pass --cluster-ramsize=600 </codeblock><p>or</p><codeblock>curl -u Admin:Pass -X POST http://localhost:8091/pools/default -d memoryQuota=600</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Index RAM Quota</dt>
        <dd>This setting controls the buffer cache size of the index storage layer. The specified
            memory is pre-allocated as soon as the indexer starts up, and is shared with all indexes
            created on the node. The total memory usage of the indexer process will be the buffer
            cache plus the size of various internal data structures and queues. You can adjust the
            per-node memory in the UI, with the CLI command or with the REST API.
              <p>Example</p><codeblock>couchbase-cli setting-cluster -c localhost -u Admin -p Pass --cluster-index-ramsize=300 </codeblock><p>or</p><codeblock>curl -u Admin:Pass -X POST http://localhost:8091/pools/default -d indexMemoryQuota=300</codeblock></dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>  
   <dl>
     <dlentry>
       <dt>Full Text RAM Quota</dt>
       <dd>This setting controls the RAM quota for Full Text search. It shows the amount of the main
            memory allocation for Full Text service per node.</dd>
     </dlentry>
   </dl>
   
   
   
   
    </section>
    <section> <title>Index Settings for Global and Memory-Optimized Indexes</title>

      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Indexer Threads </dt>
          <dd>he number of dedicated threads used by the Index Service. The number can be increased
            on multi-core machines to increase the amount of CPU available to the Indexer. The
            default is 4 and you can adjust it in the UI or with the REST API. <p>Example:
            </p><codeblock>curl -X POST -u Admin:Pass http://localhost:8091/settings/indexes -d indexerThreads=3</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
  <!--  <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>In Memory Snapshot Interval</dt>
        <dd>Frequency of in-memory snapshots which determines the earliest possibility an indexer
            scan can discover a data service Key/Value mutation. The default is 200 milliseconds and
            you  can adjust it in the UI or with the REST API.
            <p>Example:</p><codeblock>curl -X POST -u Admin:Pass http://localhost:8091/settings/indexes -d memorySnapshotInterval=300</codeblock></dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl> --> 
   <!-- <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt> Stable Snapshot Interval</dt>
        <dd>Frequency of a persisted snapshot for recovery. The default is 5000 milliseconds and you
            can adjust it in the UI or with the REST API.
            <p>Example:</p><codeblock>curl -X POST -u Admin:Pass http://localhost:8091/settings/indexes -d stableSnapshotInterval=4000</codeblock></dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl> --> 
 <dl>
   <dlentry>
     <dt>Max Rollback Points </dt>
     <dd>Maximum number of the committed rollback points. The default is 5 and you can adjust it in
            the UI or with the REST API.
            <p>Example:</p><codeblock>curl -X POST -u Admin:Pass http://localhost:8091/settings/indexes -d maxRollbackPoints=6</codeblock></dd>
   </dlentry>
 </dl>     
  <dl>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>Indexer Log Level </dt>
      <dd>Adjust the logging level from least to most verbose, the options are
              <codeph>Silent</codeph>, <codeph>Fatal</codeph>, <codeph>Error</codeph>,
              <codeph>Warn</codeph>, <codeph>Info</codeph>, <codeph>Verbose</codeph>,
              <codeph>Timing</codeph>, <codeph>Debug</codeph>, and <codeph>Trace</codeph>, with the
            default being <codeph>Debug</codeph>. It is advised to leave this setting as the default
            unless Couchbase Support directs you to change it.</dd>
    </dlentry>
  </dl>    
      </section>
      
  
  </body>
 
</topic>
