<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_h12_hqn_vs">
  <title>Configure Cluster Settings</title><shortdesc>The <uicontrol>Settings</uicontrol> menu sets the global settings for your Couchbase
    Server instance. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Full Administrators and Cluster Administrators can configure cluster settings.</p>
    <p>Use the <uicontrol>Settings > Cluster</uicontrol> tab to configure the cluster name, memory
      quotas, and index settings. You can define the settings using the Web Console, with the CLI
      command, or using the REST API.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      <image href="./pict/cluster-settings.png" id="image_dcr_5zz_zs" align="left" width="720"/>
    </p>
    
    <p>
      To configure cluster settings using Couchbase Web Console: 
    </p>
    
    <ol id="ol_uk4_cjw_zy">
      <li>Select the <uicontrol>Couchbase Web Console</uicontrol> > <uicontrol>Settings</uicontrol>
        menu. By default, the <uicontrol>Cluster</uicontrol> page is displayed.</li>
      <li>Enter the following settings and click <uicontrol>Save</uicontrol>:</li>
    </ol>
    <section>
      <title>Cluster Name</title>
      <table frame="all" id="table_cluster">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Cluster Name</entry>
              <entry>The name that was given during the initial setup. You can change it at any
                time. </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      
      <title>Couchbase Memory Quotas</title><p>The per-node memory that is available to Couchbase services limited to the smallest node in the
        cluster. These values can be adjusted in the UI, with the CLI or with the REST API.</p>
      <table frame="all" id="table_ram">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Data Service </entry>
              <entry>The per node memory allocation for the key-value cache used by the data
                service. At a minimum, it cannot be made smaller than the sum per node bucket quota
                of all buckets combined.  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Index Service </entry>
              <entry>This setting controls the buffer cache size of the index storage layer. The
                specified memory is pre-allocated as soon as the indexer starts up, and is shared
                with all indexes created on the node. The total memory usage of the indexer process
                will be the buffer cache plus the size of various internal data structures and
                queues. </entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry>Search Service</entry>
              <entry>This setting controls the RAM quota for Full Text search. It shows the amount
                of the main memory allocation for Full Text service per node.</entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry>Analytics Service</entry>
              <entry>This setting controls the RAM quota for Analytics. It shows the amount
                of the main memory allocation for the Analytics service per node.</entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry>Eventing Service</entry>
              <entry>This setting controls the RAM quota for Events. It shows the amount
                of the main memory allocation for the Events service per node.</entry>
            </row>
            
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Query Temp Disk Path
      </title>
      
      <p>
        The path to which temporary files are written, based on query activities. Specify a maximum size in
        megabytes.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Advanced N1QL Settings
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Specify either <b>Unrestricted</b> or <b>Restricted</b>, to determine which URLs are permitted to be
        accessed by the <codeph>curl</codeph> function. If <b>Unrestricted</b> (the default) is specified, all
        URLs can be accessed. If <b>Restricted</b> is specified, the UI expands, to display configurable fields
        into which the URLs allowed and disallowed can be entered.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Log Redaction Level
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Specify either <b>None</b> or <b>Partial Redaction</b>. 
        Specifying <b>Partial Redaction</b> means that when <i>explicit logging</i>
        is performed by the user, user data, such as key/value pairs and usernames,
        will be redacted from the log files, during collection.
        Metadata and system data will not be redacted. 
        Specifying <b>None</b> means that no redaction whatsoever occurs.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        The setting established
        here constitutes the future default: therefore when the <b>Collect Information</b> screen is accessed
        for the purpose of explicit logging,
        the screen's user interface, in its initial appearance, inherits this setting. 
        For more information on log redaction, 
        including the location of log files and the performance of explicit logging, see
        <xref href="../clustersetup/logging.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Logging</xref>.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Advanced Index Settings for Standard and Memory-Optimized Indexes</title><p>Define the Global Secondary Index type as Standard or Memory-Optimized option and then click
          <uicontrol>Show Advanced Index Settings</uicontrol> pull-down menu. </p>
      
      <table frame="all" id="table_advindex">
        
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Option</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Indexer Threads</entry>
              <entry>The number of dedicated threads used by the Index Service. The number can be
                increased on multi-core machines to increase the amount of CPU available to the
                Indexer. The default is set to 0. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Max Rollback Points</entry>
              <entry> The maximum number of the committed rollback points. The default is set to 5. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Indexer Log Level </entry>
              <entry>Adjust the logging level from least to most verbose, the options are:
                  <codeph>Silent</codeph>, <codeph>Fatal</codeph>, <codeph>Error</codeph>,
                  <codeph>Warn</codeph>, <codeph>Info</codeph>, <codeph>Verbose</codeph>,
                  <codeph>Timing</codeph>, <codeph>Debug</codeph>, and <codeph>Trace</codeph>. The
                default is set to <codeph>Info</codeph>. It is advised to leave this setting as the
                default unless Couchbase Support directs you to change it.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <p> </p>
  </body>
  <related-links>
    <link href="../security/concepts-rba.dita#concept_ntl_jph_hr"/>
  </related-links>
</topic>
