<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_bzd_zwr_w5">
  <title>cbq: The Command Line Shell for N1QL</title>
  <shortdesc><cmdname>cbq</cmdname> is a comprehensive new command line shell for N1QL. It is a powerful, developer friendly tool that enables you to query and update data from Couchbase Server.</shortdesc>
  <body><p>At a high level the <cmdname>cbq</cmdname> shell provides following capabilities: <ul>
        <li><xref href="#topic_bzd_zwr_w5/cbq-connection-mgmt" format="dita">Connection
            Management</xref> - provides commands to manage connections between the
          <cmdname>cbq</cmdname> shell and the cluster or query node directly.</li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_bzd_zwr_w5/cbq-session-mgmt" format="dita">Security</xref> - supports
          self-signed or CA based certificates for encrypting communication between clusters.</li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_bzd_zwr_w5/cbq-scripting-support" format="dita">Scripting
            Support</xref> - provides commands to interpret and run single or multiple commands on
          the shell. </li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_bzd_zwr_w5/cbq-query-mgmt" format="dita">Query Management</xref> -
          provides commands to monitor and profile queries. </li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_bzd_zwr_w5/cbq-session-mgmt" format="dita">Session Management</xref>
          - provides commands to set preferences and manage different shell sessions. The cbq shell
          provides the unique capability to store aliases for commands that are executed repeatedly
          or for complex queries. It also provides the ability to define positional parameters,
          which when used with the alias command is very useful and a powerful feature for
          developers.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <section id="cbq-connection-mgmt"><title>Connection Management</title>
      <p>These commands help manage the connection between the cbq shell and the query service or Couchbase cluster endpoint. </p><dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Managing Connections to the Cluster or Query Node</dt>
          <dd>You can connect the cbq shell to Couchbase Server either through the query service or
            through the cluster endpoint. There are two ways to establish a connection: <ul>
              <li>Using an option on startup:
                <codeblock>-e &lt;<varname>url to query engine or Couchbase cluster</varname>&gt;
--engine=&lt;<varname>url to query engine or Couchbase cluster</varname>&gt;</codeblock></li>
              <li>Using a shell command:
                <codeblock>cbq> \CONNECT <varname>url</varname>;</codeblock></li>
            </ul><p>The <varname>url</varname> is made up of two components: the URL and a port
              number. The URL can be any valid IP address or URL. The URL is optional and if it is
              not specified, the default URL <codeph>http://localhost:8091</codeph> is used. An
              error is thrown if the URL is invalid. </p><p>When connecting to the query service,
              use the query port 8093. When connecting to the cluster endpoint, use the admin port
              8091.</p><p>You can close the connection with an existing node or cluster without
              exiting the shell at any given time during the session using the
                <cmdname>\DISCONNECT;</cmdname> command. If the shell is not connected to any
              endpoint, an error with a message that the shell is not connected to any instance is
              thrown.
            </p><codeblock spectitle="Examples">./cbq -e=http://localhost:8091;
Connected to : http://localhost:8091/. Type Ctrl-D to exit.

cbq> \DISCONNECT;
Couchbase query shell not connected to any endpoint. Use \CONNECT command to connect.                   

cbq> \CONNECT http://127.0.0.1:8091;
Connected to : http://127.0.0.1:8091 . Type Ctrl-D / \exit / \quit to exit.

cbq> \EXIT;
Exiting the shell.

$./cbq -e=http://127.0.0.1:8091;
Connected to : http://127.0.0.1:8091/. Type Ctrl-D to exit.
cbq></codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry> 
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Bringing Up an Unconnected Instance</dt>
          <dd>You can bring up the shell without connecting to any query service or cluster endpoint
            by using the <option>-ne</option> or <option>--no-engine</option> option. After starting
            cbq without any service, you can connect to a specific endpoint using the
              <cmdname>CONNECT</cmdname> command.
            <codeblock spectitle="Example">$ ./cbq -ne
cbq> \CONNECT http://127.0.0.1:8091;
Connected to : http://127.0.0.1:8091 . Type Ctrl-D / \exit / \quit to exit.</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Exiting the cbq Shell</dt>
          <dd>You can exit the cbq shell using one of the following commands:
              <codeblock>\EXIT; | \QUIT; | Ctrl-D </codeblock><p>When you run the exit command, the
              cbq shell first saves the history, closes existing connections, saves the current
              session in a session file, resets all environment variables, and then closes the shell
              liner
            interface.</p><codeblock spectitle="Example">$ ./cbq
No Input Credentials. In order to connect to a server with authentication, please provide credentials.
Connected to : http://localhost:8091/. Type Ctrl-D to exit.

cbq> select name from `travel-sample` WHERE type="airline"  LIMIT 1;
{
    "requestID": "3a86dcf2-3bb4-445c-b419-a5eabd327a1d",
    "signature": {
        "name": "json"
    },
    "results": [
        {
            "name": "40-Mile Air"
        }
    ],
    "status": "success",
    "metrics": {
        "elapsedTime": "20.564ms",
        "executionTime": "20.539035ms",
        "resultCount": 1,
        "resultSize": 45
    }
}

cbq> \EXIT;
Exiting the shell.
$</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section id="cbq-security-mgmt"><title>Security Management</title>
      <p>The cbq shell supports self-signed or CA based certificates for encrypting communication
        between clusters. </p>
      <p> <b>Providing Multiple Credentials for Authorization</b></p>
      <p>Using the cbq shell, you can set the credentials for different users on startup or by using
        the SET shell commands to set the credentials query parameter. You can also use this to
        provide authentication credentials for multiple SASL buckets per session. Depending on the
        type of credential being set, there are multiple possible values for the credentials query
        parameter. </p>
      <p>To set the credentials for different users on startup, use one of the following options:
        <codeblock>-c=<varname>list-of-creds</varname>
--credentials=<varname>list-of-creds</varname></codeblock>
        The <varname>list-of-creds</varname> can take either one or multiple credentials. The
        credentials consist of an identity and a password separated by a colon ":". To specify
        multiple credentials, append all the user names and passwords to the same credentials array.
        For example: <codeblock>-c=beer-sample:pwd1,travel-sample:pwd2</codeblock></p>
      <p>You can pass a single user name credential to the cbq shell on startup:
        <codeblock>-u=<varname>username</varname>
--user=<varname>username</varname></codeblock>The
        shell then prompts you for a password. You can also provide a single password credential.
        Note that you can use this option only when the -u option is used.
        <codeblock>-p=<varname>password</varname>
--password=<varname>password</varname></codeblock><codeblock spectitle="Example">$ ./cbq -u=Administrator
Enter Password: 
Connected to : http://localhost:8091/. Type Ctrl-D to exit.</codeblock></p>
      <p>The query REST API defines two types of credentials: local per bucket and admin. You can
        provide the credential types using the SET command. </p>
      <note>The credentials are set for the shell session and not on a per query basis. You can use
        the SET, PUSH, POP and UNSET commands to reset the credentials during a session.</note>
      <p>To pass authentication credentials per query, set the query parameter to a new value using
        the SET shell command before executing the query.</p>
      <p>You can also switch between users and change credentials during a session. To do so, set
        the <parmname>-creds</parmname> query parameter for the session using the following command:
        <codeblock>\SET -creds beer-sample:b1, session:s1;</codeblock></p>
      
      <p><b>Passing Credentials Using Query REST API</b></p>
      <p>You can use query REST API to pass credentials from clients. </p>
      <p>For SASL buckets, you can pass the credentials
        as:<codeblock>[
  {
    "user":"beer-sample",     
    "pass”:"password"
  }  
]</codeblock></p>
      <p>If you are using the Administrator credentials: <codeblock>[
        {
        "user":"Administrator",     
        "pass”:"password"
        }  
        ]</codeblock></p>
      <p>For multiple SASL protected buckets, you can pass an array of authentication credentials: <codeblock>[
        {
        "user":"beer-sample",     
        "pass”:"password1"
        },
        {
        "user":"travel-sample",     
        "pass”:"password2"
        }
        ]</codeblock></p>
      <p><b>Displaying the Credentials</b></p>
      <p>You can display the credentials for the current session using the ECHO shell command. This
        command displays only the user names (and not the passwords).
        <codeblock>cbq> \ECHO -creds;
        
Administrator:*  </codeblock></p>
      <p>You can also display a full list of variables using the SET command specified without any
        arguments.
        <codeblock>cbq> \SET;
Query Parameters :: 
Parameter name : timeout Value  ["3ms" "4s"]

Named Parameters :: 
Parameter name : r Value  [9.5 9.5]

User Defined Session Parameters :: 

Predefined Session Parameters :: 
Parameter name : histfile Value  [".cbq_history"]</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section id="cbq-session-mgmt"><title>Session Management</title>
      <p>The session management commands enable you to set user preferences and manage different shell sessions.</p><dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Parameter Configuration</dt>
          <dd>When using parameters, you can set a stack of values for each parameter. You can
            either push a new value onto the stack using the PUSH command, or set the current value
            for a parameter using the SET command. The SET command always modifies the top of a
            variable's stack while the PUSH command adds to the stack. When you use PUSH with no
            arguments, it copies the top element of every parameter's (except the predefined
            parameters) stack and pushes that copy to the top of its respective stack. As a result,
            each stack grows by 1, but the values are preserved. You can then use the SET command to
            modify the top value. <p>To unset the values from a parameter's stack, you can use the
              UNSET command to remove all the values from the stack and delete the corresponding
              parameter stack. However, if you want to delete a single value from the settings, use
              the POP command. When you use the POP command with no arguments, it pops the one value
              from the top of each parameter's stack. </p><p><b>Setting Variable Values</b></p>Each
            variable has a separate stack associated with it and the <varname>prefix</varname>
            <varname>name</varname> argument helps distinguish between the stacks. <p>The SET
              command always modifies the top value of a variable. You can use the SET command to
              set different kinds of parameters: query parameter, predefined session variables,
              user-defined session variables and named parameters.
              <codeblock>\SET &lt;<varname>prefix</varname>>&lt;<varname>name</varname>> <varname>value</varname>;</codeblock></p><p>where
                <varname>name</varname> is the name of the parameter, <varname>value</varname> is
              the value to be set, and <varname>prefix</varname> is one of the following depending
              on the parameter type. </p><p>You can use the <cmdname>cbq</cmdname> shell to set all
              the REST API settings by specifying the settings as query parameters prefixed by '-'.
                <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_ltk_c5s_5v">
                <title>Prefixes for Parameters</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.5*"/>
                  <thead>
                    <row>
                      <entry>Prefix</entry>
                      <entry>Parameter Type</entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry>- </entry>
                      <entry>Query parameter</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>-$</entry>
                      <entry>Named parameters</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>No prefix</entry>
                      <entry>Predefined (built-in) session variable</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>$</entry>
                      <entry>User defined session variable</entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table></p><note>Positional parameters are set using the <parmname>-args</parmname>
              query parameter.</note><p>
              <codeblock>cbq> \ECHO -TIMEOUT;
100m 
cbq> \SET -TIMEOUT 3ms;
cbq> \ECHO -TIMEOUT;
3ms 
cbq> \PUSH;
cbq> \SET -TIMEOUT 4s;
cbq> \ECHO -TIMEOUT;
4s 
cbq> \POP -TIMEOUT;
cbq> \ECHO -TIMEOUT;
3ms </codeblock>
            </p><p>To display all the parameters defined in a session, use the SET command with no
              arguments.
              <codeblock>cbq> \SET;
Query Parameters :: 
Parameter name : timeout Value  ["100m"]

Named Parameters :: 
Parameter name : r Value  [9.5]

User Defined Session Parameters :: 

Predefined Session Parameters :: 
Parameter name : histfile Value  [".cbq_history"]</codeblock></p><p>The
              following table lists the available predefined session variables. <table frame="all"
                rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_p4d_pvs_5v">
                <title>Prefixes for Parameters</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                  <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.0*"/>
                  <thead>
                    <row>
                      <entry>Variable Name</entry>
                      <entry>Possible Values</entry>
                      <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <!--<row>
                      <entry>WORDWRAP</entry>
                      <entry>True or False</entry>
                      <entry>Specifies whether to use multiline mode or not. <p>Default:
                        true</p></entry>
                    </row>-->
                    <row>
                      <entry>HISTFILE</entry>
                      <entry>Valid file name</entry>
                      <entry>Specifies the file name to store the command history. By default the
                        file is saved in the user's home
                            directory.<p>Default:<filepath>.cbq_history</filepath></p></entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table></p><p><b>Resetting Variable Values</b></p><p>You can reset the value of a
              variable by either popping it or deleting it altogether. To pop the top of a
              parameter's stack use:
              <codeblock>cbq>\POP &lt;<varname>prefix</varname>>&lt;<varname>name</varname>>;</codeblock>
              To pop the top of every parameter's stack once, use the POP command without any
              arguments: <codeblock>cbq>\POP;</codeblock></p><p>To pop all the values of a
              parameter's stack and then delete the parameter, use:
              <codeblock>cbq> \UNSET &lt;<varname>prefix</varname>>&lt;<varname>name</varname>>;</codeblock></p></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>ECHO: Displaying Values of Parameters and More</dt>
          <dd>The ECHO command displays the current values of the parameters set for a session. You
            can use it to display any input string or command aliases that have been created using
            the ALIAS shell command. To display parameters, you must include their prefixes. If not,
            the shell considers the parameters as generic statements and displays the parameter as
            is. <codeblock>\ECHO <varname>input</varname> ... ;</codeblock>where
              <varname>input</varname> can be a parameter with prefix
              (<varname>&lt;prefix>&lt;parameter-name></varname>), an alias
              (\\<varname>command-alias</varname>), a N1QL statement, or a string.
            <codeblock spectitle="Examples">cbq> \ECHO hello;
hello 

cbq> \ECHO \\travel-alias1;
SELECT * from `travel-sample` LIMIT 1 
            
cbq> \ECHO -$r;
9.5 </codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Command Alias</dt>
          <dd>Using the ALIAS shell command, you can define and store aliases for commands. This is
            useful when you have lengthy queries that need to be executed often. Run the following
            command to define an alias:
            <codeblock>\ALIAS <varname>command-alias</varname> <varname>command</varname></codeblock><codeblock spectitle="Example">cbq> \ALIAS travel-alias1 SELECT * from `travel-sample` LIMIT 1;</codeblock>To
            run the command alias, use <codeph>\\<varname>command-alias</varname></codeph>.
            <codeblock spectitle="Example">cbq> \\travel-alias1;

{
    "requestID": "01f25f87-bd6c-4686-8852-ab81795290d1",
    "signature": {
        "*": "*"
    },
    "results": [
        {
            "travel-sample": {
                "callsign": "MILE-AIR",
                "country": "United States",
                "iata": "Q5",
                "icao": "MLA",
                "id": 10,
                "name": "40-Mile Air",
                "type": "airline"
            }
        }
    ],
    "status": "success",
    ...
}</codeblock>
            To list all the existing aliases, use:
              <codeblock>\ALIAS;</codeblock><codeblock spectitle="Example">cbq> \ALIAS;
serverversion  select version()
travel-alias1  SELECT * from `travel-sample` LIMIT 1</codeblock><p>You
              can delete a defined alias using the \UNLIAS
              command.<codeblock>\UNALIAS alias-name ... ;</codeblock><codeblock>cbq> \UNALIAS serverversion travel-alias1;

/* Check existing aliases */
cbq> \ALIAS;
 ERROR 141 : Alias does not exist :</codeblock>This
              command can take multiple arguments and deletes the defined alias for every input
              name.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>History</dt>
          <dd>The <cmdname>cbq</cmdname> shell stores the history for every session. All the
            commands executed in a session are stored in history. By default, history is stored in
              <filepath>~/.cbq_history</filepath>. You can change the name of the file using the SET
            command to set the predefined parameter <varname>HISTFILE</varname>.
            <codeblock>\SET HISTFILE <varname>filename</varname>;</codeblock> By default, all the
            commands are stored in the specified file. You can scroll through history and retrieve
            the commands from history using the scrolling arrow keys. Once the query is on the
            command prompt, you can edit it before executing the updated query. </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Exit Status</dt>
          <dd>The cbq shell returns the exit status 0 for successful exit with no errors and 1 if an
            error was encountered before exiting.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <!--<dlentry>
          <dt>Extending the cbq Shell Command Set</dt>
          <dd>The clean design of the cbq shell allows the command set to be extensible. The
            following is the interface design. All commands can implement these methods.
            <codeblock>/*
Interface to be implemented by shell commands.
*/
type ShellCommand interface {

  /* Name of the command */
  Name() string
            
  /* Return true if included in shell command completion */
  CommandCompletion() bool

  /* Returns the Minimum number of input arguments required by the function */
  MinArgs() int
            
  /* Returns the Maximum number of input arguments allowed by the function */
  MaxArgs() int
            
  /* Method that implements the functionality */
  ExecCommand(args []string) (int, string)

  /* Print Help information for command and its usage with an example */
  PrintHelp(desc bool) (int, string)
            
} </codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>-->
      </dl>
    </section>
    
    <section id="cbq-query-mgmt"><title>Query Management</title>
      <p>The cbq shell provides commands to interact with the query service. You can use these commands to execute prepared statements, handle named and positional parameters, cancel a query, and so on. </p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Executing Prepared Statements</dt>
          <dd>You can use the shell command to execute prepared statements. As a pre-requisite, you must first prepare a statement using the N1QL PREPARE statement. To execute prepared statements, follow these steps: <ol>
            <li>Set the named and positional parameters that are present in the prepared statement. </li>
            <li>Prepare using the N1QL PREPARE statement. This can be either prepared statement or a named prepared statement. If you do not specify a name for the prepared statement (<codeph>PREPARE <varname>query</varname>;</codeph>), a unique name is assigned. You can use this auto-assigned name when executing the prepared statement. If you specify a name (PREPARE <varname>name</varname> FROM <varname>query</varname>;), you can use this name to run the prepared statement. </li>
            <li>Execute the prepared statement using the shell command:
                <codeblock>EXECUTE <varname>name-of-prepared-stmt</varname>;</codeblock></li>
          </ol></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Handling Named Parameters</dt>
          <dd>Use the SET command to define named parameters. For each named parameter, prefix the
            variable name with '-$'. The following example creates named parameters 'r' and 'date'
            with values 9.5 and "1-1-2016"
            respectively.<codeblock>\SET -$r 9.5;
\SET -$date "1-1-2016";</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Handling Positional Parameters</dt>
          <dd>Use the SET shell command with the <parmname>-args</parmname> query parameter to
            define positional parameters:
            <codeblock>\SET -args <varname>value</varname>;</codeblock> The <varname>value</varname>
            contains the different values that correspond to positions within the query. For
            example, <codeblock>\SET -args [ 9.5, "1-1-2016"];</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Canceling a Query</dt>
          <dd>You can cancel a running query by using the Ctrl+C keys.<p><b>Connection Timeout
                Parameter</b></p><p>You can use the timeout parameter to limit the running time of a
              query. This parameter specifies the time to wait before returning an error when
              executing a query.
              <codeblock>--t=<varname>value</varname>
--timeout=<varname>value</varname></codeblock>Timeout
              can be specified in the following units: "ns" for nanoseconds, "μs" for microseconds,
              "ms" for milliseconds, "s" for seconds, "m" for minutes, and "h" for hours. Examples
              of valid values include "0.5s", "10ms", or "1m".</p><p>You can also the SET shell
              command to set this parameter. An error is thrown if the timeout is invalid.
              <codeblock>$ ./cbq --timeout="2s"

$ ./cbq -q
cbq> \SET -TIMEOUT 1ms</codeblock></p></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Handling Comments</dt>
          <dd>The shell considers anything preceded by a '#' or a '--' as a comment. While parsing
            the input, if it encounters a line that starts with '#' or '--', it logs the line into
            history and returns a new prompt. No other action is taken.
              <codeblock>cbq> select *
> #This is the first comment
> from `travel-sample`
> --This is the second comment
> LIMIT 1; </codeblock><p>However,
              if a comment exists within a statement, it is considered as part of the N1QL command.
              If the shell encounters block comments (enclosed within /* ... */) within a statement,
              it sends it to the query service.
              <codeblock>cbq> select * from `travel-sample` /* This statement includes a block comment */ LIMIT 1;</codeblock></p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section id="cbq-server-shell-info"><title>Server and Shell Information</title>
      <p>Cbq provides commands that convey information about the shell or cluster endpoints. </p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Version</dt>
          <dd>You can find the version of the client (shell) by using either the command line option
            to display the current version of the shell and exit, or as a shell command to print the
            version of the shell during the shell session.
              <codeblock spectitle="Example Using the Command-line Option">./cbq -v
SHELL VERSION : 1.0 
          
$ ./cbq --version
SHELL VERSION : 1.0</codeblock><codeblock spectitle="Example Using the Shell Command">cbq> \VERSION;
SHELL VERSION : 1.0 </codeblock><p>To
              display the version of the query service, use the N1QL commands <codeph>SELECT
                version();</codeph> and <codeph>SELECT min_version();</codeph>. </p></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Help</dt>
          <dd>Help displays the help information for the shell commands and for the general usage of
            cbq. Use the help option when bringing up the shell to display the information for all
            available options: <codeblock>$ ./cbq -h
$ ./cbq --help</codeblock> Use the HELP shell
            command during a session to display information for specific shell commands. If you
            specify one or more commands, the shell displays the usage information for the
            commands.<codeblock>cbq> \HELP <varname>command-name</varname>;</codeblock> If you do
            not specify a command, the cbq shell lists all the commands for which syntax help is
            available. <codeblock>cbq> \HELP;</codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Copyright</dt>
          <dd>You can view the copyright, attributions, and distribution terms of the command line
            query tool using the <codeph>\COPYRIGHT;</codeph> command.
            <codeblock>cbq> \COPYRIGHT;
Copyright (c) 2015 Couchbase, Inc. Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); 
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the 
License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND,
either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing permissions
cbq></codeblock></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <!--<dlentry>
          <dt>Shortcut Keys Used in the cbq Shell</dt>
          <dd>The following table lists the shortcut keys used in the cbq shell. <table frame="all"
              rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_qty_jhf_5v">
              <title>Shortcut Keys for cbq Shell</title>
              <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.97*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Keystroke</entry>
                    <entry>Action</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-A, Home</entry>
                    <entry>Move cursor to beginning of line</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-E, End  </entry>
                    <entry>Move cursor to end of line</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-B, Left</entry>
                    <entry> Move cursor one character left </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-F, Right </entry>
                    <entry>Move cursor one character right </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-Left </entry>
                    <entry>Move cursor to previous word </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-Right </entry>
                    <entry>Move cursor to next word </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-D, Del     </entry>
                    <entry>(if line is not empty) Delete character under cursor </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-D</entry>
                    <entry>(if line is empty) End of File - usually quits application </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-C</entry>
                    <entry>Reset input (create new empty prompt) </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-L</entry>
                    <entry>Clear screen (line is unmodified) </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-T</entry>
                    <entry>Transpose previous character with current character</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-H, BackSpace   </entry>
                    <entry>Delete character before cursor </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-W </entry>
                    <entry>Delete word leading up to cursor</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-K</entry>
                    <entry>Delete from cursor to end of line </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-U </entry>
                    <entry>Delete from start of line to cursor</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry> Ctrl-P, Up</entry>
                    <entry>Previous match from history</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-N, Down</entry>
                    <entry>Next match from history</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry> Ctrl-R     </entry>
                    <entry>Reverse Search history (Ctrl-S forward, Ctrl-G cancel)</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Ctrl-Y</entry>
                    <entry>Paste from Yank buffer (Alt-Y to paste next yank instead) </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Tab </entry>
                    <entry>Next completion </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Shift-Tab</entry>
                    <entry>(after Tab) Previous completion</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></dd>
        </dlentry>-->
      </dl>
      
    </section>
    <section id="cbq-scripting-support"><title>Support for Scripting</title>
      <p>The <cmdname>cbq</cmdname> shell can interpret and run single and multiple shell and N1QL
        commands. </p>
<dl>
  <!--<dlentry>
    <dt>Word wrap</dt>
    <dd>By default, the shell is set to multi-line mode. You can choose to disable it.
              <draft-comment author="amarantha">Using /SET multiline false?? </draft-comment></dd>
  </dlentry>-->
  <dlentry>
    <dt>Single Command Mode</dt>
    <dd>You can use the <parmname>--script</parmname> option to execute a single N1QL query and exit
            the shell:
            <codeblock>./cbq --script="select * from `travel-sample` LIMIT 1"</codeblock><codeblock spectitle="Results">Connected to : http://localhost:8091/. Type Ctrl-D to exit.
{
  ...
}</codeblock></dd>
  </dlentry>
  <dlentry>
    <dt>Multi-line Input</dt>
    <dd>You can enter N1QL statements and shell commands that spans multiple lines. The command
            prompt ">" indicates that the shell is in multi-line mode. End the command by specifying
            the ";" at the end.
            <codeblock>cbq> select *
> from `travel-sample`
> LIMIT 1;</codeblock></dd>  
  </dlentry>
  <dlentry>
    <dt>Run Commands by Redirection and Piping</dt>
    <dd>You can use redirection and piping to run commands on the cbq shell.
            <codeblock>$ echo "select * from \`beer-sample\` limit 10;" | ./cbq
 …
$ cat file.txt | ./cbq
 …
$ ./cbq &lt; file.txt
…</codeblock></dd>
  </dlentry>
  <dlentry>
    <dt>Exit on Error</dt>
    <dd>When you specify the argument <codeph>--exit-on-error</codeph>, the cbq shell checks the
            result returned after executing the query for any error and exits when the first error
            is encountered. </dd>
  </dlentry>
  <dlentry>
    <dt>File Based Operations</dt>
    <dd>Using the file based commands and options, the cbq shell can execute N1QL and shell commands
            contained in files. There are two ways to accomplish this: <ul>
              <li>Using an option on startup:
                  <codeblock>-f=<varname>input-file</varname>
--file=<varname>input-file</varname></codeblock><p>The
                  cbq shell executes the commands present in the input file, prints them to stdout
                  (or to a file if using redirects), and exits.</p></li>
              <li>Using a shell command:
                  <codeblock>\SOURCE <varname>input-file</varname>;</codeblock><p>Runs the commands
                  present in the input file and prints the result to stdout. </p></li>
            </ul><p>Consider the input file, <filepath>sample.txt</filepath>, containing the
              following commands:
              <codeblock>CREATE PRIMARY INDEX on `beer-sample` USING GSI;
SELECT * from `beer-sample` LIMIT 2;
SELECT abv from `beer-sample` LIMIT 3;
\HELP; </codeblock></p><p>To
              execute the commands contained in sample.txt using the -f option, run <codeph>$./cbq
                -f=sample.txt</codeph>
              <codeblock spectitle="Results">Connected to : http://localhost:8091/. Type Ctrl-D to exit.
CREATE PRIMARY INDEX on `beer-sample` USING GSI;
{ ...
  "results": [ ],
  ...
}
SELECT * from `beer-sample` LIMIT 2;
{ ...
  "results": [ ],
  ...
}
SELECT abv from `beer-sample` LIMIT 3;
{ ...
  "results": [ ],
  ...
}
\HELP;
Help Information for all Shell Commands
… 
$</codeblock></p><p>To
              execute the commands contained in <filepath>sample.txt</filepath> using the shell
              command, run <codeph>cbq> \SOURCE sample.txt;</codeph>
              <codeblock spectitle="Results">CREATE PRIMARY INDEX on `beer-sample` USING GSI;
{ ...
  "results": [ ],
 ...
}
SELECT * from `beer-sample` LIMIT 2;
{ ...
  "results": [ ],
  ...
}
SELECT abv from `beer-sample` LIMIT 3;
{ ...
  "results": [ ],
  ...
}
\HELP;
Help Information for all Shell Commands
… 
cbq> </codeblock></p><p><b>Redirecting
                Results to a File</b></p><p>You can redirect all the output for a session or part of
              a session to a specified file by using the following option:
              <codeblock>-o <varname>filename</varname>
--output=<varname>filename</varname></codeblock></p><p>To
              redirect a specific set of commands during a session, you must specify the commands
              between REDIRECT and REDIRECT OFF as shown:
              <codeblock>cbq> \REDIRECT filename;
command-1; command-2;, ..., command-n;
\REDIRECT OFF;</codeblock>
              All the commands specified after <codeph>\REDIRECT</codeph> and before
                <codeph>\REDIRECT OFF</codeph> are saved into the specified output file. If the file
              doesn't exist then it is created.
              <codeblock spectitle="Example">cbq> \REDIRECT temp_output.txt;
> CREATE PRIMARY INDEX on `beer-sample` USING GSI;
> SELECT * from `beer-sample` LIMIT 1;
> \HELP;
> \REDIRECT OFF;</codeblock></p>You
            can specify multiple <codeph>REDIRECT</codeph> commands. When you do so, the output file
            changes to the specified files and switches back to stdout only when you specify
              "<codeph>\REDIRECT OFF</codeph>;".</dd>
  </dlentry></dl></section>
  </body>
  
</topic>
