<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_wk1_5v3_t5">
  <title>Query Monitoring</title>
  <shortdesc>Couchbase Server 5.0 introduces new UI that allows you to monitor the current state of
    query service. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p dir="ltr">From the <uicontrol>Couchbase Web Console</uicontrol> >
        <uicontrol>Query</uicontrol> > <uicontrol>Query Monitor</uicontrol>, you can view the
      different types queries that are Active (currently running), Completed (recently run), and
      Prepared (aggregate statistics for prepared queries). </p>
    <p dir="ltr">You can also cancel the running queries. The information about these queries is
      automatically updated every 5 seconds. To freeze the display updates, click
        <uicontrol>pause</uicontrol> located above the query table, next to the table heading. When
      paused, a <uicontrol>resume</uicontrol> button becomes available to let you restart automatic
      updates. You can sort the column by clicking the column header.</p>
    <section id="active-queries">
      <title>Active Queries</title>
      <p>By default, the <uicontrol>Active Queries</uicontrol> page is displayed on the Query
        Monitoring screen. The currently running queries are displayed, showing the details such as
        the query syntax, the server IP address where the query is running, duration, request
        identification number, and the current state of the query. To cancel a long running query,
        click the <uicontrol>cancel</uicontrol> link located on the right side of the row. </p>
      <p>
        <image placement="break" href="images/query-monitor-active.png" width="720"
          id="image_oww_3mr_dz"/>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="complete-queries">
      <title>Completed Queries</title>
      <p>From the <uicontrol>Couchbase Web Console > Query > Query Monitor ></uicontrol> click the
          <uicontrol>Completed</uicontrol> button to view the table of completed queries whose
        runtime exceeded a system-specified threshold (default 1 second). Each row shows the query
        syntax, the server IP address where the query is running, duration, the result count, the
        current state of the query, and the timestamp when the query was run. </p>
      <p>
        <image placement="break" href="images/query-monitor-completed.png" width="720"
          id="image_cdd_lmr_dz"/>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="prepared-queries">
      <title>Prepared Queries</title>
      <p>From the <uicontrol>Couchbase Web Console > Query > Query Monitor ></uicontrol> click the
          <uicontrol>Prepared</uicontrol> button to view the prepared queries. This page displays
        the aggregate statistics for prepared queries showing details such as query syntax, average
        elapsed time, number of uses, and the server IP address. </p>
    </section>
    <p>
      <image placement="break" href="images/query-monitor-prepared.png" width="720"
        id="image_xqq_cys_gz"/>
    </p>
    <p>For more information about system keyspaces and API for monitoring the operation of
      individual queries and query service nodes, see <xref
        href="../monitoring/monitoring-n1ql-query.dita#topic_nvs_ghr_dz"/>.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
