<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_mbg_5lp_pp">
	<title>Elasticsearch plug-in 2.1</title>
	<shortdesc>The Couchbase Elasticsearch plug-in allows you to use Couchbase Server with
		Elasticsearch, an open source search engine. The plug-in enables you to provide rapid,
		full-text search results in your application. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
		<p>Your users can retrieve application documents from Couchbase Server based on text in your
			documents. For example, if your application is a product catalog, users can find items
			based on text descriptions of the products.</p>
		<p>The data model for Elasticsearch is compatible with the schema-free, document-oriented
			model used by Couchbase Server. Because search is often a CPU-intensive process, you can
			scale your Elasticsearch cluster separately from your Couchbase cluster to best meet the
			demands of your users. In doing so, search functions do not slow the performance of
			Couchbase Server reads or writes.</p>

		<section><title>How the plug-in works</title><p>The plug-in continuously streams data between
				Couchbase Server and Elasticsearch. Any document changes made in Couchbase Server
				are sent to Elasticsearch via the plug-in, which ensures your search index contains
				the most current items in your system. The plug-in enables the following:</p><ul>
				<li><b>Real-Time replication</b>. The plug-in continuously transfers data to the
					search cluster after Couchbase Server writes the data to disk. That helps keep
					your search index on Elasticsearch current with the information in Couchbase
					Server.</li>
				<li><b>Topology awareness</b>. Using the plug-in, the system can handle node
					failures within a Couchbase cluster or Elasticsearch cluster and adapt
					accordingly. Replication from a Couchbase cluster continues from functioning
					nodes and the items are sent to available servers in the Elasticsearch
					cluster.</li>
				<li><b>Recovery from network failure</b>. The plug-in is aware of what data has
					already been replicated from Couchbase and what data still needs to be
					replicated. If a network failure interrupts data transfer from a Couchbase
					cluster, after the network issue has been resolved, replication resumes for
					remaining data.</li>
			</ul><p>If you are already building applications with Couchbase Server, you are probably
				aware of using views to index and query data from the server. You use this
				functionality to find, retrieve, and sort data based on document metadata and
				specified document attributes. For example, if you have a database that contains
				information about beers, you could use views to retrieve all beer documents where
				the alcohol percentage is greater than 8%. Or you could use views to calculate the
				average alcohol percentage of all beers in an application. Providing full-text
				search for Couchbase documents with Elasticsearch complements this functionality by
				enabling you to provide text-based search results. The following figure shows the
				different elements in a system using Couchbase Server and Elasticsearch:</p>
			<image href="images/elastic_components.png" width="720"/>
			<p>Your website or web application interacts with Couchbase Server via a Couchbase SDK.
				SDKs are available for a variety of popular web programming languages. Each SDK
				provides APIs for establishing a connection with the server and for communicating
				reads, writes, and other functions with the server. The SDK also provides methods to
				index and query data from Couchbase Server by using views.</p><p>To provide
				full-text search with Couchbase Server you need to have a cluster of Elasticsearch
				engines, the Couchbase Elasticsearch plug-in, and a running Couchbase cluster. After
				an application writes or updates data in Couchbase Server, the server replicates a
				copy of that data to the Elasticsearch cluster for indexing. The Elasticsearch
				cluster performs indexing based on text content in your data. After the data is
				indexed, you can use an Elasticsearch client to send a search query to Elasticsearch
				via HTTP. Elasticsearch does not keep an entire copy of each item replicated from
				Couchbase cluster. After Elasticsearch indexes an item it keeps the ID for the item
				and other metadata, but discards the content to remain efficient. After your
				application queries Elasticsearch for an item via HTTP, it sends back document IDs
				that you can use to retrieve the entire document from Couchbase
			Server.</p></section>

		<section>
			<title>How querying works</title>
			<p>Using Couchbase Server with Elasticsearch, users can actually perform searches based on
				rich text content within a document, such as information in text descriptions. Imagine a
				user wants to find a beer that has a nice fruity flavor reminiscent of blueberries. Your
				application can take in a query string as a web form parameter and send the query to
				Elasticsearch as JSON containing the term blueberry. Your application sends a query via
				HTTP to Elasticsearch as follows:</p>
			<codeblock>GET http://127.0.0.1:9200/beer-sample/_search?q=blueberry
</codeblock>
			<p>Elasticsearch responds by sending the document ID for this beer document in a JSON
				array. The array will contain elements with document IDs for those documents which match
				the query parameter:</p>
			<codeblock>....
"hits" : [{
    ....
    "_source": {
        "meta" : {
            "id": "110ac410b16h"
            .....
        }
    }
}....
</codeblock>
			<p>For purposes of brevity we omit other details from the JSON response. The
					<codeph>id</codeph> field in the response is the ID you use to retrieve a document
				from Couchbase Server. With this ID, you can retrieve a document from Couchbase for the
				beer document that contains the term blueberry in the text description:</p>
			<codeblock>{
    "name" : "Wild Blueberry Lager",
    "abv" : 8,
    "brewery_id" : "110f01",
    "description" : "....blueberry aroma....",
    "style" : "Belgian Fruity Lambic"
    ....
}
</codeblock>
			<p>In addition to text search queries, you can also provide logic and regular expressions
				to describe search criterion.</p>
		</section>

	</conbody>
</concept>
