<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic1730">
	<title>Troubleshooting data transfer issues</title>
	<body>
		<p>Follow these steps to troubleshoot data transfer issues:</p>
		
			<ol><li>Check your Elasticsearch version.<p>The most common problem you can encounter with
					Couchbase-Elasticsearch integration is that data fails to transfer due to an
					incompatible Elasticsearch version. Elasticsearch evolves between versions and
					the Couchbase Elasticsearch plug-in is specifically designed and tested for one
					or more versions of Elasticsearch. If you use an earlier or later version, it
					will result in failure to transfer data. You can check which versions of
					Elasticsearch are compatible with your version the plug-in by consulting the
						<xref href="release-notes.dita#elastic-release-notes">release notes</xref>.
					If you have an incompatible version of the plug-in, you might see the following
					message:</p><codeblock>Attention - Failed to grab remote bucket info from any of known nodes</codeblock><p>If
					you check the Elasticsearch head console, a stack trace similar to the following
					displays:</p><codeblock>[2012-12-19 05:50:41,758][WARN ][org.eclipse.jetty.servlet.ServletHandler]
Error for /pools/default/buckets java.lang.NoSuchMethodError:
....</codeblock><p>If
					you get this error, make sure you are using the plug-in with the correct version
					of Elasticsearch.</p></li>
		
		
			<li>Check destination cluster references. <p>Another common error occurs when you create a
					cluster reference in Couchbase Web Console and then at a later time create and
					start the replication. After you create a reference to your Elasticsearch
					cluster, the IP address might change, especially if you are using Elasticsearch
					on a laptop. In this case you will get this error under XDCR | Ongoing
					Replications | Status:</p>
				<image href="images/elastic_xdcr_ref_fail.png" width="650px"/>
				<p>To resolve this error, check your remote Elasticsearch reference in XDCR and make
					sure the IP address is correct.</p></li></ol>

		
	</body>
</topic>
