<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">

<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic1500">
  <title>Cross Datacenter Replication (XDCR)</title><shortdesc>Cross Datacenter Replication (XDCR) 
    provides an easy way to replicate data from one cluster to another. </shortdesc>
  <body>
  <p>XDCR in Couchbase Server involves replicating active data to multiple, geographically diverse
      datacenters either for disaster recovery or to bring data closer to its users for faster data
      access.</p> <p>
      <image href="../images/cross-cluster.png" id="image_ocf_wbf_xq" width="600"
        placement="break" align="left"/>
    </p>
      
    <p>XDCR and intra-cluster replication can occur simultaneously. Intra-cluster replication is
        taking place within the clusters at both Datacenter 1 and Datacenter 2 while  XDCR is
        replicating documents across datacenters at the same time. Both datacenters are serving read
        and write requests from the application.</p>
    
    <section><title>Use cases for XDCR</title> XDCR is used mainly in these cases: for disaster
      recovery, to bring data closer to users and to replicate data for development and test needs. <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Disaster recovery</dt>
          <dd>Disaster can strike your datacenter at any time – often with little or no warning. The
            active-active cross datacenter replication in Couchbase Server ensures the availability
            of data 24/365 even if an entire datacenter goes down since applications can read and
            write to any geo-location.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl><dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Bringing data closer to users</dt>
          <dd>You can use XDCR to make your data available locally,  with low latency. </dd>
          <dd>Interactive web applications demand low latency response times to deliver an
            impressive application experience. Therefore, the best way to reduce latency is to bring
            relevant data closer to the user. For example, in online advertising, sub-millisecond
            latency is needed to make optimized decisions about real-time ad placements. <p>With
              XDCR, you can bring the post-processed user profile data closer to ensure low latency
              data access.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl><dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Data replication for development and test needs</dt>
          <dd>Developers and testers often need to simulate production-like environments for
            troubleshooting or to produce a more reliable test. By using XDCR, they can create test
            clusters that host subset of their production data so that they can test code changes
            without interrupting production processing or risking a data loss.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl></section> 
  </body>
</topic>
