<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic3554">
	<title>Managing Data Encryption</title><shortdesc>Secure XDCR enables you to encrypt traffic between two data centers using an SSL/TLS
		connection.</shortdesc>
	<body>
		<p>When you use Secure Cross Datacenter Replication (XDCR), all traffic in the source and
			destination data centers will be encrypted. This will cause a slight increase in the CPU
			load, since any encryption needs additional CPU cycles. </p>
		<note>With 4.0, Couchbase uses the TLS protocol by default for encrypted interactions. The server
			supports both TLS 1.0-1.2 for XDCR. Which version it uses depends on the source and
			target clusters.</note>
		<section><title>Enable XDCR data security</title><p>To enable XDCR data security using TLS and create replication:</p><ol>
				<li>On the destination cluster, navigate to Settings &gt; Cluster and copy the
					certificate. <ul>
						<li>(Optional) To regenerate the existing destination certificate, click
								<b>Regenerate</b> before copying.</li>
					</ul></li>
				<li>On the source cluster, select the XDCR tab.</li>
				<li>On the Remote Clusters panel, click <b>Create Cluster Reference</b> to verify or
					create the cluster reference.</li>
				<li>Select the <b>Enable Encryption</b> box and paste the certificate in the
					provided area and click <b>Save</b>.</li>
				<li>On the Ongoing Replications panel, click <b>Create Replication</b>, provide the
					cluster and bucket information, and click <b>Replicate</b>.</li>
			</ol></section>
		<section><title>Change XDCR data encryption</title><p>In some situations (such as updating TLS data security), the certificate is regenerated and the
				XDCR data encryption is updated. To change XDCR data encryption:</p><ol>
				<li>On the destination cluster, navigate to Settings &gt; Cluster.</li>
				<li>Click <b>Regenerate</b> and copy the certificate.</li>
				<li>On the source cluster, select the XDCR tab.</li>
				<li>On the <b>Remote Clusters</b> panel, for the destination cluster, click
						<b>Edit</b>.</li>
				<li>Paste the regenerated certificate in the provided area and click
					<b>Save</b>.</li>
			</ol><p>Anytime a destination cluster’s certificate is regenerated, the corresponding
				source cluster(s) must be updated with the regenerated certificate.</p><p>For
				example, if source clusters A, B, and C use XDCR data encryption to replicate to
				destination cluster D, each of the source clusters must be updated whenever the
				certificate on the destination cluster D is regenerated
				(changed).</p><p>Important</p><p>If a destination cluster's certificate is
				regenerated and the source cluster(s) are not updated with the new certificate,
				replication stops. </p></section>
		<section><title>Rotating Certificates</title><p>As a security best practice, periodically rotate the XDCR certificates and also make sure that
				you instantiate a new certificate on the remote cluster. The following is an example
				of an certificate and where the certificate is obtained on the cluster.</p>
			
			<fig><image href="../images/xdcr-remote-cert3.png" width="720">
				<alt>Remote certificate</alt>
			</image></fig>
		</section>
		
		<section><title>Create cluster reference</title>
			
			<p> To create a cluster reference: <ol>
					<li>Access the dialog at <menucascade>
							<uicontrol>XDCR</uicontrol>
							<uicontrol>Create Cluster Reference</uicontrol>
						</menucascade>. <p><image href="../images/create-cluster-reference.png"
								width="480"/></p></li>
					<li>Enter the following information: <dl>
							<dlentry>
								<dt>Cluster Name</dt>
								<dd>Name of the cluster you are adding.</dd>
							</dlentry>
						</dl><dl>
							<dlentry>
								<dt>IP/hostname</dt>
								<dd>The hostname or IP address of a node in the cluster you are
									adding.</dd>
							</dlentry>
						</dl><dl>
							<dlentry>
								<dt>Security</dt>
								<dd>Username and password or the login credentials for the remote
									cluster</dd>
							</dlentry>
						</dl><dl>
							<dlentry>
								<dt>Enable encryption</dt>
								<dd>If this option is selected, XDCR data encryption occurs using SSL/TLS. A window will
									open where you have to paste the SSL certificate that has been
									obtained from the remote cluster. This certificate is available
									on the remote cluster on the location <menucascade>
										<uicontrol>Settings</uicontrol>
										<uicontrol>Cluster</uicontrol>
									</menucascade>. <note type="attention"> Do not share the
										certificate with any unintended entities. </note><note
										type="attention"> Regenerate the certificate periodically
										based on your organizational requirements. </note></dd>
							</dlentry>
						</dl></li>
				</ol><note type="note">It is recommended to conduct traffic for XDCR using a Virtual
					Private Network (VPN).</note></p>
		</section>
		
		<section><title>XDCR data security error messages</title><p>When creating the cluster reference, if the certificates are not the same on the destination and
				source clusters, the following error message displays:</p><codeblock>Attention - Got certificate mismatch while trying to send https request to HOST:18091
</codeblock><p>If the certificates become mismatched (for example, if the certificate on the destination cluster
				is regenerated and the source cluster is not updated with the new certificate),
				vBucket replication stops and the following error message displays:</p><codeblock>Error replicating vbucket &lt;bucketNumber&gt;. Please see logs for details.
</codeblock></section>
	</body>
</topic>
