<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_zzc_hws_zs">
  <title>Recover Partitions from a Remote Cluster</title> <shortdesc>Data recovery from remote clusters requires XDCR and enough memory and disk
    space.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>If more nodes in a cluster catastrophically fail than the number of replicas, data partitions
      in that cluster will no longer be available. For example, if you have a four-node cluster with
      one replica and two nodes fail and are unrecoverable, some data shards will no longer be
      available. </p>
    <p>Data recovery from remote clusters requires an XDCR environment and adequate amount of memory and disk space to support the workload and recovered data.
    </p>
    <p>To recover the missing data partition in case of node failure and when vBuckets are unavailable, follow these steps.
    </p>
    <ol>
      <li>For each failed node, click on <menucascade>
          <uicontrol>Server Nodes</uicontrol>
          <uicontrol>Fail Over</uicontrol>
        </menucascade>. <p>You will see whether data is unavailable and which vBuckets are
          unavailable. If you do not have enough replicas for the number of the failed-over nodes,
          some vBuckets will no longer be available:</p><p><image
            href="picts/xdcr-recover-partition-1.png" id="image_rzb_vk5_zs" align="left" xtrc=""
            width="550"/></p></li>
      <li>Add new functioning nodes to replace the failed nodes.<p>Do not rebalance after you add
          new nodes to a cluster. Typically, you will rebalance after adding nodes to the cluster,
          but in this scenario the rebalance will destroy the information about the missing vBuckets
          and you cannot recover it.</p><p><image href="picts/xdcr-recover-partition-2.png"
            id="image_ngh_bl5_zs" align="left" width="550"/></p><p>In this example, two nodes failed
          in a three-node cluster and a new node at <codeph>10.3.3.61</codeph> was added. If you are
          certain that your cluster can easily handle the workload and recovered data, you may
          choose to skip this step.  </p></li>
      <li>Run <uicontrol>cbrecovery</uicontrol> to recover data from your backup cluster. In the
          <wintitle>Server Panel</wintitle>, the <uicontrol>Stop Recovery</uicontrol> button
        appears. <p><image href="picts/xdcr-recover-partition-3.png" id="image_jv4_hl5_zs"
            align="left" width="550"/>
        </p><p> After the recovery completes, this button disappears. </p></li>
      <li>Rebalance your cluster. <p>Once the recovery is completed, you can rebalance your cluster.
          Rebalancing will recreate replica vBuckets and redistribute them evenly across the
          cluster. </p><p><image href="picts/xdcr-recover-partition-4.png" id="image_wwv_nl5_zs"
            align="left" width="550"/></p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </body>
</topic>
