<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_zfs_h5q_pq">
  <title>XDCR Conflict Resolution</title>
  <body>
    <section><title>Understanding Conflict Resolution</title>
      <p>When the same dataset is being mutated on both ends of an XDCR replication (source and remote destination), then there is a high probability that conflicts could occur. XDCR automatically performs conflict resolution for different document versions on source and destination clusters. </p>
      <p>Couchbase Server 4.6 supports both strategies - revision ID based conflict resolution
        (default) and timestamp-based conflict resolution.</p>
      <p>By default, XDCR fetches metadata for every document which are over the Optimistic
        Replication Threshold (default 256 bytes) from destination cluster before it replicates the
        document. XDCR also fetches metadata on the source cluster and looks at the timestamp for a
        document. Depending on the conflict resolution method selected, it either compares source
        timestamps with destination timestamp, or the source revision ID with the destination
        revision ID, to pick the ‘winner’. If XDCR determines a document from a source cluster will
        win conflict resolution, it puts the document into the replication queue. If the document
        loses conflict resolution, XDCR will not put it into the replication queue. </p>
      <p>In case of documents with smaller size which are below Optimistic Replication Threshold
        (default 256 bytes), XDCR skips fetching metadata from destination cluster and instead
        optimistically replicates documents to destination cluster. </p>
      <p>Once the document reaches the destination, this cluster will request metadata once again to
        confirm the document on the destination has not changed since the initial check. If the
        document from the source cluster is still the ‘winner’ it will be persisted on to disk at
        the destination. The destination cluster will discard the document version which ‘loses’
        conflict resolution.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="revision-id-based-conflict-resololution"><title>Revision-based Conflict Resolution</title>
    <p>The algorithm is designed to consistently select the same document on either a source or
      destination cluster. For each stored document, XDCR perform checks of metadata to resolve
      conflicts. It checks the following:</p>
    <ul id="ul_v25_trv_py">
      <li>
        <p>Revision ID, a numerical sequence that is incremented on each mutation</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>CAS value</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Document flags</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Expiration (TTL) value</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>XDCR conflict resolution uses revision ID as the first field to resolve conflicts between two
      writes across clusters. Revision IDs are maintained per key and are incremented with every
      update to the key. Revision IDs keep track of number of mutations to a key, thus XDCR conflict
      resolution can be best characterized as "the most updates wins".</p>
    <p>In case of conflict resolution between an incoming mutation from another cluster and a local
      mutation in the current cluster, if the incoming mutation does not have a higher revision
      number than the local mutation, it will be discarded and will not be stored. In case of
      bidirectional replication, the mutation with the highest score takes precedence on both
      clusters.</p>
    <p>Conflict resolution is automatic and does not require any manual correction or selection of
      documents.</p>
    <p><b>How are Conflicts Resolved Using Revision ID Based Strategy</b></p>
    <p>For documents whose size exceeds the optimistic replication threshold setting, XDCR fetches
      metadata before it replicates the document to the destination cluster. XDCR fetches metadata
      on the source cluster and looks at the number of revisions for a document. It compares this
      number with the number of revisions on the destination cluster and the document with more
      revisions is considered the ‘winner.’</p>
    <p>If XDCR determines a document from a source cluster will win conflict resolution, it puts the
      document into the replication queue. If the document will lose conflict resolution because it
      has a lower number of mutations, XDCR will not put it into the replication queue. Once the
      replicated document reaches the destination, conflict resolution will be performed again by
      the remote cluster to ensure that the correct document 'wins'. This is to ensure that the
      correct version of the document 'wins' even if the document on the remote cluster has changed
      since the initial replication from the source cluster. If the document from the source cluster
      is still the ‘winner’ it will be persisted onto disk at the destination. The destination
      cluster will discard the document version with the lower number of mutations.</p>
    <p>The key point is that the number of document mutations is the main factor that determines
      whether XDCR keeps a document version or not. This means that the document that has the most
      recent mutation may not be necessarily the one that wins conflict resolution. If both
      documents have the same number of mutations, XDCR selects a winner based on other document
      metadata. Precisely determining which document is the most recently changed is often difficult
      in a distributed system. The revision id based conflict resolution algorithm Couchbase Server
      uses does ensure that each cluster can independently reach a consistent decision on which
      document wins.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="timestamp-based-conflict-resolution"><title>Timestamp-based Conflict Resolution</title>
      <p>In the new conflict resolution mode, the timestamp is used as the main criterion to order the mutations. Couchbase uses a hybrid timestamp (HT) to store the timestamp and as the way to keep consistent ordering. </p>
      <p>To use the timestamp-based conflict resolution you must enable the Timestamp Conflict
        Resolution setting on a per bucket basis. For more information, see Admin guide.</p>
      <p id="hybrid-timestamp"><b>Hybrid Timestamp</b></p>
      <p>The hybrid timestamp is a combination of the physical clock and a logical clock. </p>
      <p>The CAS of a document is now a hybrid logical clock timestamp stored as a 64-bit value,
        with the top 48 bits for the physical clock and the lower 16 bits for the logical portion.
        Each mutation has its own hybrid logical clock timestamp.</p>
      <p>Here are some important properties of hybrid timestamp: <ul id="ul_bjf_xtv_py">
          <li>Hybrid timestamp is monotonic. Its logical counter starts to increment when either the
            physical clock value is smaller or equal to the current maximum seen time, which ensures
            that it does not suffer from the potential leap-back of a physical clock. </li>
          <li>Hybrid timestamp captures happen-before relation just like the logical clock.</li>
          <li>Hybrid timestamp is close to physical time.</li>
        </ul></p>  
      <p id="time-synchronization"><b>Time Synchronization</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase Server requires an external entity to synchronize the clocks among the clusters
        such as NTP (Network Time Protocol) or other methods. </p>
      <p>Time synchronization is needed because: <ul id="ul_vsz_25v_py">
          <li>Hybrid timestamp can capture happen-before relation, and hence can always guarantee
            the correct ordering for updates with casual relationships.</li>
          <li>For concurrent or independent updates, the accuracy of picking the “last write” is
            affected by the time skew between the two clusters involved. In order to improve
            accuracy, the time skew between the two clusters needs to be kept in check through time
            synchronization mechanisms like NTP.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>It is important that you synchronize your clocks on each server node properly to use
        timestamp based conflict resolution effectively. Failing to do so can result in document
        mutations incorrectly winning conflicts and many related issues. <note type="important"
          >Timestamp based conflict resolution is not supported without synchronized
        clocks.</note></p>
      <p>For more information on using NTP to synchronize clocks, see <xref
          href="../install/synchronize-clocks-using-ntp.dita#topic_jbb_ccp_vx"/>.</p>
      <p><b>How are Conflicts Resolved Using Timestamp Based Strategy</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase performs conflict resolution on the destination cluster, and in the case of large
        documents [Optimistic Replication Threshold], it performs conflict resolution on the source
        cluster. It uses the same algorithm for both source side or destination side conflict
        resolution:
        <codeblock>if (incomingDocument.CAS > localDocument.CAS)
  incomingDocument succeeds
else if (incomingDocument.CAS == localDocument.CAS)
  // Check the RevSeqno
  if (incomingDocument.RevSeqno > localDocument.RevSeqno)
    incomingDocument succeeds
  else if (incomingDocument.RevSeqno == localDocument.RevSeqno)
    // Check the expiry time
    if (incomingDocument.Expiry > localDocument.Expiry)
      incomingDocument succeeds
    else if (incomingDocument.Expiry == localDocument.Expiry)
      // Finally check flags
      if (incomingDocument.Flags &lt; localDocument.Flags)
        incomingDocument succeeds
command fails</codeblock></p>
      <p>The key point is that the higher timestamp value is the main factor that determines whether
        XDCR keeps a document version or not. This means that the document that has the most recent
        mutation is the one that wins conflict resolution. If both documents have the same
        timestamp, XDCR selects a winner based on other document metadata such as revision ID,
        document flags and expiration (TTL) value. </p>
      <p>The following are the necessary and sufficient conditions to avoid data loss during cluster
        failover and failback: <ul id="ul_zzk_gvv_py">
          <li>m2 clock is faster than m1</li>
          <li>Let's say max time skew between 2 data centers is X. Then before failing the traffic
            to m2, wait for X. Simply put, if m2 clock is slower than m1 by X, then wait for X
            before failing over.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>Consider the following example:</p> <ol id="ol_tvm_qvv_py">
          <li>The data center A receives mutations (m1) from App1 and App2.</li>
          <li>Data center A has an outage before the latest mutations can be replicated to
            datacenter B.</li>
          <li>App1 and App2 then failover to data center 2 and the user sees that there is data loss
            since the latest mutations(m1) were not replicated.</li>
          <li>The user then submits another set of mutations(m2), which are available in data center
            B.</li>
          <li>Once the outage on data center A is fixed, the applications switch back to data center
            A. At this point, the user expects to see his latest mutations (m2) and not experience
            another data loss.</li>
        </ol>
      <p>The hybrid timestamp for a document is replicated across nodes within the same cluster (via
        DCP) and across clusters (via XDCR). Therefore causality relationship is maintained with
        replication. For example: <ol id="ol_zzc_bwv_py">
          <li>Mutation A1 is replicated to target B. Mutation A1's hybrid timestamp is now in target
            B.</li>
          <li>Now there is mutation A2. By comparing the hybrid timestamp of both A1 and A2, it can
            tell A1 "happens before" A2 -- since hybrid timestamp is monotonic.</li>
        </ol></p>
      <p>For concurrent mutations the order is determined by the physical time component (system
        clock, which should be synchronized via NTP or other method).</p>
      <p><b id="docs-internal-guid-04e0596d-a602-c5bd-01c5-6074f9d40e50">What Happens When Your
          Physical Clocks Are No Longer in Sync</b></p>
      <p>If your physical clocks are drifting ahead and the drift is larger than the threshold of 5
        seconds (5000 milliseconds), then an alert is raised on the destination cluster with the
        following message: “<systemoutput>[<varname>&lt;DATE></varname>] - Remote or replica
          mutation received for bucket "<varname>&lt;BUCKET></varname>" on node
            "<varname>&lt;IP></varname>" with timestamp more than 5000 milliseconds ahead of local
          clock. Please ensure that NTP is set up correctly on all nodes across the replication
          topology and clocks are synchronized.</systemoutput>” <image placement="break"
          href="picts/xdcr-timestamp-conflict-resolution-alert.png" width="450"
          id="image_adp_swv_py"/>If you see this alert, ensure that NTP is setup correctly on all
        nodes across the replication topology and that the clocks are synchronized.</p>
      <p>When the clocks are out of sync, you may also see the average drift mutation graph report
        an increased drift. </p>
      <p>You can change the default drift mutation threshold at run time by setting the following
        parameters to an integer value. These values can be adjusted per node using
          <cmdname>cbepctl</cmdname>. <ul id="ul_pf1_1xv_py">
          <li><parmname>hlc_drift_ahead_threshold_us</parmname>, specified in microseconds</li>
          <li><parmname>hlc_drift_behind_threshold_us</parmname>, specified in microseconds</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>The following example changes <codeph>bucket1</codeph>'s behind threshold to 6.5 seconds:
        <codeblock>$> cbeptcl host:port -b bucket1 set vbucket_param hlc_drift_behind_threshold_us 6500000</codeblock></p>
      <p>When a future CAS value is received and used to update the node’s HLC, it is an operation
        that cannot be undone. Thus a node with a very bad configuration may “poison” peers, and
        even if that bad node is fixed, the poisoning cannot be undone by normal traffic.</p>
      <p>You can undo this “poisoning” by waiting for time to pass or by changing the node’s real
        clock. Neither of these options would be desirable if the future clock was a very high
        value, for example "3017 10-Jan 14:14". </p>
      <p>In such cases, updating the <cmdname>epctl</cmdname> can undo the damage to some extent.
        <codeblock>cbepctl [localhost]:11210 -b [bucket_name] -p [bucket-password]
set_vbucket_param max_cas new_max_cas_value vbucket-id</codeblock></p>
      <p>For example to change the <codeph>max_cas</codeph> of vBucket 7 to “Wed, 05 Oct 2016
        13:00:00 GMT” the user must obtain the epoch as microseconds. Wed, 05 Oct 2016 13:00:00 GMT
        is 1475672493 seconds since epoch, or 1475672493000000 µs since epoch.
        <codeblock>cbepctl node1:11210 -b beer -p passw0rd
set_vbucket_param max_cas 1475672493000000 7</codeblock></p>
      
    </section>
    <p id="xdcr-conflict-resolution-use-cases"><b>XDCR Use Cases Supported by Timestamp-based Conflict Resolution</b></p>
    <p>XDCR is used by many customers as a high-availability solution. Failing over to a secondary
      cluster following cluster wide or partial failures is critical for customers requiring high
      availability on their database tier. Conflicts created during temporary failures will need to
      be reconciled when the failures are resolved.</p>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Unidirectional Replication Use Case - Disaster Recovery</dt>
        <dd>Disaster can strike anytime - often with very little or no warning. Using XDCR, data can
          be replicated to geo-located data centers, ensuring availability of data 24x365 even if an
          entire data center goes down. <image placement="break"
            href="picts/xdcr-unidirectional-usecase.png" width="570" id="image_ffw_jyv_py"/></dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Bidirectional Replication Use Case - Datacenter Locality</dt>
        <dd>Interactive web applications demand low latency response times to deliver a responsive
          application experience. The best way to reduce latency is to bring relevant data closer to
          the user. XDCR can be used to synchronize data between geo-located data centers. Consider
          the following scenario where the primary goal is to write to the data center located
          closer to the user. The two data centers are connected using private networks with low
          latencies and high bandwidth. <p>During normal operation, the application traffic would go
            to both data centers. However, the documents in use are exclusive to the user session
            interacting with the application. As a result, in the most common case, simultaneous
            updates to the same document in both clusters don't occur, hence conflicts are not
            generated. XDCR is primarily replicating data for possible recovery to the alternate
            data center. <image placement="break"
              href="picts/xdcr-timestamp-conflict-resolution-data-locality.png" width="570"
              id="image_aly_yyv_py"/></p></dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <p id="cross-cluster-failover-failback"><b>Cross-cluster Failover and Failback</b></p>
    <p><note type="important">This release supports the use of timestamp based conflict resolution
        for high availability across clusters only during failover and failback scenarios.</note>For
      both the use cases described above, using timestamp based conflict resolution ensures that
      conflicts are resolved by comparing timestamps of conflicting documents. This enables
      applications to continue showing the last change/version no matter when conflicts are resolved
      in the background. <image placement="break"
        href="picts/xdcr-timestamp-conflict-resolution-cluster-failover.png" width="570"
        id="image_s3r_gzv_py"/></p>
    <p>Consider the example in the diagram above: <ol id="ol_a25_3zv_py">
        <li>The data center A receives mutations (m1) from App1 and App2.</li>
        <li>Data center A has an outage before the latest mutations can be replicated to datacenter
          B.</li>
        <li>App1 and App2 then failover to data center 2 and the user sees that there is data loss
          since the latest mutations(m1) were not replicated.<note>For failover, it is recommended
            that a wait period is introduced before traffic is routed to the backup cluster. This is
            to ensure that residual mutations will lose in conflict resolution. The wait period
            should be longer than the replication latency and time skew.</note></li>
        <li>The user then submits another set of mutations (m2), which are available in data center
          B.</li>
        <li>Once the outage on data center A is fixed, before the applications switch back to data
          center A.<note>Applications should not write new mutations to data center A, until after
            mutations in data center B are replicated over to data center A. Also, it is recommended
            that the wait period should be longer than the replication latency and time
          skew.</note></li>
        <li>At this point, the user expects to see his latest mutations (m2) and not experience
          another data loss.</li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>Using timestamp based conflict resolution ensures that the user sees the last edits (m2) when
      the outage is fixed.</p>
    <p><b>Recommendations for Timestamp-based Conflict Resolution</b></p>
    <p>Note the following recommendations when using timestamp based conflict resolution: <ul
        id="ul_djt_vzv_py">
        <li>Clock synchronization<ul id="ul_wwy_11w_py">
            <li>Use NTP (or GPS or atomic clocks) to synchronize wall clock between all individual
              cluster nodes and clusters in the XDCR topology. If you are unable to synchronize all
              clocks across clusters, you must at least know the dispersion from the reference clock
              for each cluster so that you can add an appropriate delay to your application. See
                <xref href="#topic_zfs_h5q_pq/cross-cluster-failover-failback" format="dita"
                >cross-cluster failover and failback</xref> for details. </li>
            <li>Monitor time skew between clusters. By default, when a drift of 5seconds is
              detected, an alert is raised.</li>
          </ul></li>
        <li>In cross-cluster failover and failback use cases, use delay to synthesize ordering for
          consistency. That is, the failover timeout must be greater than the max of replication
          latency or the time skew between clusters.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p><b>Troubleshooting</b></p>
    <p>The following checks on your deployment will help ensure that your timestamp-based conflict
      resolution works as expected: <ul id="ul_mct_m1w_py">
        <li>Ensure your deployment is a supported use case for timestamp based conflict resolution.
          See <xref href="#topic_zfs_h5q_pq/xdcr-conflict-resolution-use-cases" format="dita">XDCR Supported Use Cases for Timestamp-based Conflict Resolution</xref> for details.</li>
        <li>Ensure that NTP is configured correctly on every node in both clusters and also before
          adding a node to the cluster. </li>
        <li>Ensure that NTP time  synchronization is working as expected. </li>
        <li>Ensure that NTP is still configured correctly if a node is removed and re-added to a
          cluster, or if a node is restarted. </li>
        <li>Ensure that there are no network issues between the NTP Server and NTP clients on
          Couchbase server nodes. </li>
        <li>Ensure that you monitor the time drift on the clusters using the stats. </li>
        <li>Ensure that an appropriate wait time (delay) is introduced in an application in case of
          cluster failover and failback. </li>
      </ul></p>
    
  </body>
  <related-links>
    
    <linklist>
      <desc>For information on how to set the conflict resolution type for a bucket, see</desc>
      <link href="../clustersetup/create-bucket.dita"></link>
    </linklist>
    <linklist>
      <desc>For information on monitoring various aspects of timestamp-based conflict resolution, see</desc>
    <link href="xdcr-monitor-timestamp-conflict-resolution.dita"></link>
    </linklist>
  </related-links>
</topic>

