<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_umk_vn5_zs">
  <title>Monitor the recovery process</title> <shortdesc>Use the Couchbase Web Console to monitor the recovery process.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>To monitor the progress of recovery:
    </p>
    <ol>
      <li>Click on the <uicontrol>Data Buckets</uicontrol> tab.</li>
      <li>Select the data bucket you are recovering from the <wintitle>Data Buckets</wintitle> drop-down list.</li>
      <li>Click on the <wintitle>Summary</wintitle> drop-down list to see more details about this
        data bucket. You will see an increased number of items during recovery: <p><image
            href="picts/xdcr-recovery-process-1.png" id="image_x1h_cq5_zs" align="left" width="450"
          /></p></li>
      <li>You can also see the number of active vBuckets increase as they are recovered until you
        reach 1024 vBuckets. <p>Click on the <wintitle>vBucket Resources</wintitle> drop-down:</p>
            <p><image href="picts/xdcr-recovery-process-2.png" id="image_hxy_hq5_zs" align="left"
            width="500"/></p><p>Since this tool runs from the command line, you can stop it at any
          time.</p></li>
      <li>The <wintitle>Stop Recovery</wintitle> button appears in the <wintitle>Servers</wintitle>
        panels. If you click this button, you will stop the recovery process between clusters. Once
        the recovery process completes, this button will no longer appear, and you will need to
        rebalance the cluster. You can also stop it in this panel: <p><image
            href="picts/xdcr-recovery-process-3.png" id="image_z2p_pq5_zs" align="left" width="600"
          /></p></li>
      <li>After the recovery completes, click on the Server Nodes tab and then on Rebalance to
        rebalance your cluster. When <codeph>cbrecovery</codeph> finishes, it will output a report
        in the console:
        <codeblock>  Recovery :                Total |    Per sec
        batch    :                 0000 |       14.5
        byte     :                 0000 |      156.0
        msg      :                 0000 |       15.6
        4 vbuckets recovered with elapsed time 10.90 seconds</codeblock>
      </li>
    
    </ol>
    <p>In this report:  <term>batch</term> is a group of internal operations performed by
      cbrecovery, <term>byte</term> indicates the total number of bytes recovered, and
        <term>msg</term> is the number of documents recovered. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
