<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_sp1_qws_zs">
  <title>XDCR Data Security</title> <shortdesc>The data replicated between clusters can be encrypted in both uni-directional and bi-directional replications. Only the Full Administrator can manage XDCR data security settings.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>When you use Secure Cross Datacenter Replication (XDCR), all traffic from the source and
      destination data centers will be encrypted. Encryption causes a slight increase in the CPU
      load since it requires additional CPU cycles.</p>
   
   <section><title>Enable XDCR Data Security</title> 
   
      <p>To enable XDCR data security using SSL and create replication:</p>
      
      <ol>
        <li>On the destination cluster, navigate to <menucascade>
            <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol>
            <uicontrol>Root Certificate</uicontrol>
          </menucascade> and copy the certificate. <p>(Optional) To regenerate the existing
            destination certificate, click Regenerate before copying.</p></li>
        <li>In the source cluster, select the <wintitle>XDCR</wintitle> tab.</li>
        <li>In the <wintitle>Remote Clusters</wintitle> panel, click <uicontrol>Create Cluster
            Reference</uicontrol> to verify or create the cluster reference.</li>
        <li>Select the <wintitle>Enable TLS Encryption</wintitle> box and paste the certificate in
          the provided area and click <uicontrol>Save</uicontrol>. <p><image
              href="../admin/picts/xdcr-createreference.png" id="image_wjp_hpk_3v"/></p></li>
        <li>In the <wintitle>Ongoing Replications</wintitle> panel, click <uicontrol>Create Replication</uicontrol>, provide the cluster and bucket information, and click <uicontrol>Replicate</uicontrol>.</li>
        
      </ol></section> 
    <section><title>Change XDCR Data Encryption</title>
      <p>In some situations, such as updating SSL data security, the SSL certificate is regenerated, and the XDCR data encryption is updated. Only the Full Administrator can regenerate the SSL certificate to update XDCR data
        encryption. </p>
      <p>To change XDCR data encryption:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>On the destination cluster, navigate to <menucascade>
          <uicontrol>Settings</uicontrol>
          <uicontrol>Cluster</uicontrol>
        </menucascade>.</li>
        <li>Click <uicontrol>Regenerate</uicontrol> and copy the certificate.</li>
        <li>On the source cluster, select the <wintitle>XDCR</wintitle> tab.</li>
        <li>In the <wintitle>Remote Clusters</wintitle> panel, for the destination cluster, click <uicontrol>Edit</uicontrol>.</li>
        <li> Paste the regenerated certificate in the provided area and click <uicontrol>Save</uicontrol>.
          Anytime you regenerate the destination cluster’s certificate, update the corresponding source cluster(s) 
          with that regenerated certificate.
          <p>For example, if source clusters A, B, and C use XDCR data encryption to replicate to destination cluster D, 
            update each of the source clusters whenever you regenerate the certificate on the destination cluster D.</p></li>
      </ol>
      
      <note type="important"> Replication will stop if you regenerate the destination cluster's 	
        certificate and don't update the source cluster(s) with the new 	certificate.</note>
    </section>
    <section><title>Use an SSL Certificate</title>
      <p>As a security best practice, 
        periodically rotate the XDCR certificates and also make sure that you instantiate a new certificate on the remote cluster.</p>
      <p> The following example is a self-signed SSL/TLS certificate obtained on the cluster. Click <menucascade>
        <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol>
        <uicontrol>Root Certificate</uicontrol>
      </menucascade> to reach the certificate.</p>
      <p><image href="picts/xdcr-ssl-cert.png" id="image_b14_2x5_zs" align="left" width="720"/></p>
      <p><b>XDCR Data Security Error Messages</b></p>
      <p>When creating the cluster reference, if the SSL certificates are not the same on the destination and source clusters, the following error message displays:
        
        <systemoutput>Attention - Got certificate mismatch while trying to send https request to HOST:18091</systemoutput></p>
      
      
      <p>The SSL certificates can become mismatched, such as when the certificate on the destination cluster is regenerated, 
        and the source cluster is not updated with the new certificate. 
        In this case, vBucket replication stops and the following error message displays:
        
        <systemoutput> Error replicating vbucket &lt;bucketNumber&gt;. Please see logs for details.</systemoutput></p>
    </section>
  </body>
  <related-links>
    <link href="../security/concepts-rba.dita#concept_ntl_jph_hr"/>
  </related-links>
</topic>
