<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="topic_9" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title id="title__Toc272567416">Correlated Subqueries</title>
  <shortdesc/>
  <conbody>
    <p>In the examples <xref href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q1">Q1</xref>, <xref
        href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q2">Q2</xref>, and <xref href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q3"
        >Q3</xref>, subqueries are independent of the parent queries. They do not depend on any of
      the variables and aliases defined in the outer query, nor the specific document being
      processed at the outer query. In such cases, the inner subquery has no correlation with its
      outer query so it is called as <i>non-correlated</i> subquery. When a subquery refers to
      variables, aliases, attributes, or keyspace in the outer statement, it is called as
        <i>correlated</i> subquery. These subqueries are special because their performance
      characteristics can be very different from non-correlated queries. Typically, correlated
      queries are expensive, and query engines take special care in planning and executing such
      queries efficiently.</p>
    <p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Performance</dt>
          <dd>For non-correlated queries, a subquery is evaluated once and resulting values are
            substituted in the parent query for all of the documents at the outer level queries.
            However, when a query includes a correlated subquery, the evaluation of the subquery
            depends on the outer query document being processed. The subquery refers to some values
            or attributes in the outer query. It is similar to having variables in the subquery
            whose exact values are provided by the outer query, which may change for each of the
            documents considered at outer levels. Therefore, the subquery is executed repeatedly
            once for each document that is selected in the outer query. <p>N1QL query engine
              optimizes the correlated subquery processing in multiple ways:<ul id="ul_nby_cjq_mz">
                <li dir="ltr">
                  <p dir="ltr">Subqueries are prepared only once, though they are executed multiple
                    times. This will avoid repetitive costs such as parsing &amp; planning of the
                    subquery.</p>
                </li>
                <li dir="ltr">When subquery is correlated through the FROM clause expression, fetch
                  of documents in the subquery is avoided. The query engine smartly reuses the
                  correlated document already fetched in the outer query.</li>
              </ul></p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <section><title>Correlation Types</title>In N1QL, a subquery is correlated with its parent
      queries which is very important. That dictates certain behaviors and limitations in writing
      nested subqueries, and impacts query performance.<p>
        <dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>Correlation by Source (or FROM clause-Expression)</dt>
            <dd>The data source for a query or subquery is specified by its FROM clause. When the
              FROM clause of a subquery refers to any variables (aliases, keyspace names, LET or
              LETTING variables, or document attributes) in the scope of parent queries, then the
              correlation is established using the source keyspace in the FROM expression. Such
              subquery is called <b>Source Correlated Subquery</b> and it offers the following
              benefits:</dd>
            <dd><b>Nested Paths in FROM clause</b></dd>
            <dd>Couchbase Server 5.0 introduced powerful subquery functionality where correlated
              nested paths can be used in a subquery FROM clause. This provides powerful language
              expressibility, simplicity, and flexibility to N1QL queries especially when dealing
              with nested array attributes. See <xref
                href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/nested-path-expr">Nested Paths in Subqueries</xref>
              for more details.</dd>
            <dd><b>Better Performance </b></dd>
            <dd>When correlation is established through the FROM clause in the subquery (with
              variables in scope), then the N1QL engine knows that the subquery is referring to the
              same document that is being processed in one of the outer queries. Therefore, the
              subquery avoids fetch of the documents used in the subquery. This significantly
              improves the performance of such subqueries, as shown in example <xref
                href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q6">Q6</xref> earlier whereas the example <xref
                href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q6A">Q6A</xref> cannot take advantage of this
              optimization.</dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl>
        <dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>Correlation by Reference (or non FROM clause-Expression)</dt>
            <dd>In this case the subqueries refer to <xref
                href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/section_onz_3tj_mz">variables in the scope</xref> of
              outer level queries, in clauses other than the FROM clause of the subquery. In such
              case, the FROM clause will have an independent keyspace identifier that does not
              reference any variables in the scope. This kind of subquery execution works like a
              JOIN query and requires the USE KEYS clause. For more information, see <xref
                href="#topic_9/use-keys" format="dita">USE KEYS in the subquery</xref> and <xref
                href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/from-clause"/> for more details.</dd>
            <dd>In the following example, in LET clause of parent query, with correlation introduced
              in the WHERE clause (<codeph>t2.iata = t1.airline</codeph>) and USE KEYS clauses of
              the subquery (referencing <codeph>t1</codeph> fields). This query finds the airline
              and route details of flights that have routes starting from SFO airport.</dd>
            <dd>
              <codeblock id="Q10">Example Q10:

SELECT airline_details, t1.destinationairport, t1.stops
FROM `travel-sample`  t1
LET airline_details = (SELECT t2.name, t2.callsign
                       FROM `travel-sample` t2
	              <b>USE KEYS t1.airlineid
</b>                      WHERE t2.type = "airline" 
                           AND t2.iata = t1.airline) 
WHERE t1.type = "route" AND t1.sourceairport = "SFO" 
      AND ARRAY_LENGTH(airline_details) > 0
LIMIT2;</codeblock>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl>
      </p></section>
    <section id="use-keys"><title>FROM clause and USE KEYS in Correlated Subqueries</title>In the
      example subquery <xref href="#topic_9/Q10" format="dita">Q10</xref>, the USE KEYS clause (in
        <b>bold</b>) is used to establish the correlation with the outer query documents. Otherwise,
      it is not possible to identify the documents in the subquery that are related to the specific
      document being considered by the outer query. <p dir="ltr">It is important to understand the
        reasoning to include the USE KEYS clause. That is not always mandatory. It entirely depends
        on how the FROM clause is formulated, which indicates the source of documents for the
        subquery and hence the correlation with the parent query.</p>When a keyspace name identifier
      is used in FROM-clause of a subquery, that refers to a collection of documents referenced by
      the keyspace identifier. However, when an alias of the keyspace is used in FROM-clause (or any
      other clauses of the query), that refers to an individual document of the keyspace being
      considered in the outer query.<p>
        <dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>FROM clause with Keyspace Identifier</dt>
            <dd>The USE KEYS clause is mandatory for the primary keyspace of the subquery when the
              FROM clause has keyspace identifier that is independent of any of the
              aliases/variables in scope. This is needed to establish correlation with the
              documents/keyspace used in the outer query. For example:<ul id="ul_oxc_jqx_mz">
                <li dir="ltr">
                  <p dir="ltr">The FROM clause of the subquery in <xref
                      href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q7">Q7</xref> is an independent keyspace
                    identifier <codeph>`travel-sample`</codeph> and hence the correlation with
                    parent query is established explicitly using the USE KEYS clause through the
                    referential attribute <codeph>t1.airlineid</codeph>.</p>
                </li>
              </ul><ul id="ul_pxc_jqx_mz">
                <li dir="ltr">
                  <p dir="ltr">Similarly, the subquery in <xref href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q6A"
                      >Q6A</xref> has an independent keyspace identifier
                      <codeph>`travel-sample`</codeph> in FROM clause, but the correlation is
                    self-referencing to the same document. Therefore, <codeph>USE KEYS
                      meta(t).id</codeph> is used.</p>
                </li>
              </ul>This is exactly same as the PrimaryKey-ForeignKey relationship required to <xref
                href="from.dita#concept_rnt_zfk_np/join-clause">join</xref> two documents that are
              referenced in the outer/inner queries. Note that, in <codeph>travel-sample</codeph>
              keyspace data model, the <codeph>route</codeph> documents refer the
                <codeph>airline</codeph> documents using the attribute <codeph>airlineid</codeph>.
              Refer to the <xref
                href="../../data-modeling/entity-relationship-doc-design.dita#concept_hgb_31r_dt"
                >concepts of data modeling</xref> for more details on reference based modeling.</dd>
            <dd>
              <p/>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>FROM clause with Expression</dt>
            <dd>The USE KEYS clause is not required in the subquery when the FROM clause in subquery
              has generic expression as data source, and not a keyspace name identifier. The FROM
              clause expression can be  an independent constant expression or subquery expression
              that does not refer to any variables in scope or a generic N1QL expression or subquery
              that refers to any variables in scope.<p dir="ltr">In the example <xref
                  href="subqueries.dita#topic_9/Q6">Q6</xref>, the FROM clause is an expression
                referring to the variable/alias <codeph>t</codeph> (in fact the nested path
                  <codeph>t.reviews</codeph>) that already establishes correlation and therefore the
                subquery does not need explicit USE KEYS clause.</p></dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl>
      </p></section>
    <section><title>Correlated Subquery versus JOINs</title><p>Correlated subqueries can be
        alternatively formulated using JOINs because conceptually a correlated query execution
        involves same steps as that of JOIN. For instance, evaluating nested subquery corresponding
        to each outer query document is equivalent to a nested-loop-join operation. This is one
        reason for the above mentioned mandatory requirement of USE KEYS clause for certain
        correlated queries using FROM clause.</p>In general, N1QL recommends usage of JOIN queries
      when possible, instead of semantically equivalent correlated subqueries. However, in some
      cases it may be easier or intuitive to formulate some queries using subqueries (instead of
      JOINs). In such case, it is recommended to understand the EXPLAIN query plans and performance
      of both queries.<p>
        <codeblock>Example Q7A: Earlier Q7 rewritten with JOIN

SELECT DISTINCT airline.name, airline.callsign, route.destinationairport, route.stops, route.airline
FROM `travel-sample` route 
      JOIN `travel-sample` airline 
      ON KEYS route.airlineid 
WHERE route.type = "route" 
      AND airline.type = "airline" 
      AND route.sourceairport = "SFO" 
LIMIT 2;
</codeblock>
      </p></section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
