<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_npk_mth_rq">
 <title>CREATE INDEX</title>
 
 <conbody>
 	<p>The CREATE INDEX statement allows you to create a secondary index. Secondary indexes contain a
			filtered or a full set of keys in a given bucket. Secondary indexes are optional but
			increase query efficiency on a bucket.</p>
 	<p>CREATE INDEX is by default a synchronous operation. CREATE INDEX statement blocks until the
			operation finishes. Index building starts by creating a task that is queued for index
			build. After this phase, if you lose connectivity, index build operation continues to
			happen in the background. You can also run index creation asynchronously using the
			"defer_build" clause. In the async mode, CREATE INDEX starts a task to create the primary
			index and returns as soon as the task is queued for execution. The full index creation
			operation happens in the background.</p>
		<p>Both GSI and View indexes provide a status field and mark index status pending. With GSI
			indexer, index status continues to report "pending". This status field and other index
			metadata can be queried using system:indexes.</p>
		<p/>
		<p><b>RBAC Privileges</b></p>
		<p>User executing the CREATE INDEX statement must have the <i>Query Manage Index</i> privilege
			granted on the keyspace/bucket. For more details about user roles, see <xref
				href="../../security/security-roles-used-in-access-control.dita#topic_auth_for_admins"
			/>.</p>
 	<note type="important">Indexes cannot be built concurrently on a given bucket unless the
				<codeph>defer_build</codeph> option of the CREATE INDEX statement is used in combination
			with BUILD INDEX statement. The following error is reported if a second index creation
			operation is kicked off before the completion of the ongoing index creation.
			<codeblock>"errors": [{"code": 12014, 
    "msg": "error: Build Already In Progress. Bucket BUCKET_NAME. Index INDEX_NAME. Index state: pending"}]</codeblock></note>
		<p>You can create multiple identical secondary indexes on a bucket for better index
			availability and place them on separate nodes using the "nodes" clause. </p>
		<p>
			<note type="note">Couchbase Server 4.5 release adds the capability to
				create global indexes on array elements and optimizes the execution of queries
				involving array elements. See <xref
					href="indexing-arrays.dita"/> for details.</note>
		</p>
 	<p><i>create-index:</i></p>
 	<codeblock>CREATE INDEX [index_name] ON named_keyspace_ref( expression [ , expression ] * )
    WHERE filter_expressions
    [ USING GSI | VIEW ]
    [ WITH { "nodes": [ "node_name" ], "defer_build":true|false } ];</codeblock>
 	<p><i>index_name:</i>
		</p>
		<p>A unique name that identifies the index. This parameter is required.</p>
		<p>Valid GSI index names can contain any of the following characters: A-Z a-z 0-9 # _, and
			must start with a letter, [A-Z a-z]. The minimum length of an index name is 1 character
			and there is no maximum length set for an index name. When querying, if the index name
			contains a '#' or '_' character, you must enclose the index name within backticks. </p>
 	
 	<p><i>named-keyspace-ref( expression [ ,expression ]* )</i></p>
 <codeblock>[ namespace-name :] keyspace-name </codeblock>
 	<p><i>keyspace-name:</i></p>
 	<p>An identifier that refers to the bucket name. Specifies the bucket as the source for which the
			index needs to be created. You can add an optional namespace name to the keyspace name in
			this way:</p>
 	<p><i>namespace-name : keyspace-name</i></p>
 	<p>For example, <codeph>main:customer</codeph> indicates the customer keyspace in the main
			namespace. If the namespace name is omitted, the default namespace in the current session
			is used.</p>
 	<p><i>Expression index-key</i></p>
		<p>Refers to an attribute name or a scalar function or an ARRAY expression on the attribute.
			This constitutes an index-key for the index. See <xref
				href="https://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/4.6/n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/indexing-arrays.html"
				format="html" scope="external">Array Indexing</xref> for more details about the
			array expressions.</p>
 	<p><i>USING GSI | VIEW</i></p>
 	<p>USING clause specifies the index type to use. Secondary indexes can be created using global
			secondary indexes (GSI) or views. If the USING clause is not specified, by default GSI
			is used as the indexer.</p>
 	<p><i>WITH options</i></p>
 	<p>With clause is used to specify additional options with the GSI type indexes.</p>
 	<p><i>"nodes":["node name"] </i></p>
 	<p>A single secondary index of type GSI can only be placed on a single node that runs the indexing
			service. The "nodes" option allows you to specify the node that the index is placed on.
			If nodes is not specified, one of the nodes running the index service is randomly picked
			for the index. <note type="important">The node name passed to the <codeph>nodes</codeph>
				parameter must include the cluster administration port (by default 8091). For
				example <codeph>WITH {"nodes": ["192.0.2.0:8091"]}</codeph> instead of <codeph>WITH
					{"nodes": ["192.0.2.0"]}</codeph>.</note></p> 	
 	
 	<p><i>"defer_build":true | false</i></p>
 	<p>With defer_build set to true, CREATE INDEX operation queues the task for building the index but
			immediately pauses the building of the index of type GSI. Index building require an
			expensive scan operation. Deferring building of the index with multiple indexes can
			optimize the expensive scan operation. Admins can defer building multiple indexes and,
			using BUILD INDEX statement, multiple indexes to be built efficiently with one efficient
			scan of bucket data.</p>
		<p>With defer_build set to false, CREATE INDEX operation queues the task for building the
			index and immediately kicks off the building of the index of type GSI. </p>
 	<note type="attention">We recommend that you do not create (or drop) secondary indexes when any node with a secondary index role is down as this may result in duplicate index names. </note> 	
 	<p><b>Using the <apiname>meta().id</apiname> function</b></p>
 	<p>You can use the <codeph>meta().id </codeph>function when creating an index. The
				<codeph>meta().id</codeph> function does not require a parameter; it implicitly uses
			the keyspace being indexed. </p>
 	<codeblock>CREATE INDEX id_ix on `beer-sample`(meta().id);</codeblock>
 	<p>The <codeph>meta().id </codeph>function in a query is given an expression; if it resolves to a
			keyspace alias, the requested field (id) is
			returned.<codeblock>SELECT b.name, meta(b).id 
FROM `beer-sample` b 
WHERE meta(b).id > "g" limit 1;</codeblock></p>
 	<p>The only supported <codeph>meta()</codeph> field in the  <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph>
			statement for Couchbase Server version 4.5 is <codeph>meta().id</codeph>.</p>
 	<p><b>Using indices for aggregates</b></p>
 	<p>If there is an index on the expression of an aggregate, that index may be used to satisfy the query. For example, given the index "<codeph>abv_idx</codeph>" created using the following statement: <codeblock>CREATE INDEX abv_idx ON `beer-sample`(abv);</codeblock></p>
 		<p>The query engine will use the index "<codeph>abv_idx</codeph>" for the following query: <codeblock>SELECT min(abv), max(abv) FROM `beer-sample`;</codeblock></p>
 	<section><title>Examples</title>
 		
 		<p>The following example creates a secondary index that contains beers with an
					<codeph>abv</codeph> value greater than 5 on the node
				<codeph>192.0.2.1</codeph>:</p>
 		<codeblock>CREATE INDEX over5 ON `beer-sample`(abv) WHERE abv > 5 USING GSI WITH {"nodes": ["192.0.2.1:8091"]};</codeblock>
 	<p>The following example creates a secondary index on the <codeph>beer-sample</codeph> bucket and
				then queries <codeph>system:indexes</codeph> for status of the index:</p>
 		
<codeblock>CREATE INDEX `beer-sample-type-index` ON `beer-sample`(type) USING GSI;
SELECT * FROM system:indexes WHERE name="beer-sample-type-index";</codeblock>
 	
<p>The following example creates the same secondary index by using the deferred build option and
				then queries <codeph>system:indexes</codeph> for status of the index:</p> 	<codeblock>CREATE INDEX `beer-sample-type-index` ON `beer-sample`(type) USING GSI
    WITH {"defer_build":true};
SELECT * FROM system:indexes WHERE name="beer-sample-type-index";</codeblock>
 	<p>Because the deferred build option was enabled, the output from the query on
					<codeph>system:indexes</codeph> shows <codeph>beer-sample-type-index</codeph> shows
				the index has not finished building (<codeph>"state": "pending"</codeph>). </p>
			<p>The following example uses the BUILD INDEX statement to kick off the deferred build on
				the <codeph>beer-sample-type-index</codeph> index and then queries <codeph>system:indexes</codeph> for status of the index:</p>
 <codeblock>BUILD INDEX ON `beer-sample`(`beer-sample-type-index`) USING GSI;
SELECT * FROM system:indexes WHERE name="beer-sample-type-index";</codeblock>
 		<p>This time the query on <codeph>system:indexes</codeph> shows that the index is built
					(<codeph>"state": "online"</codeph>).</p>
 	</section>
 <section id="idx-limitations"><title>Limitations</title>
	<ul>
	<li> The total size of the index keys cannot exceed 4K for a single document. Index key size is
					calculated using the total size of all the expressions being indexed in a single
					document. If an index keys size exceeds 4K, it will be skipped. The following
					error is logged to indicate that an item is skipped when building the index:
						"<systemoutput>Encoded secondary key is too long</systemoutput>" in the
						<filepath>indexer.log</filepath> file. The <filepath>indexer.log</filepath>
					file is included in cbcollect_info output. </li>
      </ul> 
 	</section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
