<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_hv4_sbr_w5">
  <title>Array Indexing</title>
  <body>
    <p>Couchbase 4.5 adds the capability to create global indexes on array elements and optimizes
      the execution of queries involving array elements. This is a huge leap from the previous
      versions where secondary indexes could only be created and subsequently queried on whole
      arrays. You can now create an index of array elements ranging from plain scalar values to
      complex arrays or JSON objects nested deeper in the array. </p>
    <section>
      <title>N1QL Syntax</title>
      <codeblock>CREATE INDEX [ <varname>index_name</varname> ] 
        ON <varname>named_keyspace_ref</varname> ( <varname>expression1</varname> || <varname>array_expression</varname>, <codeph>expression2</codeph>, … )
        [ WHERE <varname>filter_expressions</varname> ]
        [ USING GSI ]
        [ WITH { "nodes": [ "<varname>node_name</varname>" ], 
                "defer_build": true | false
              }
        ];</codeblock>
      <p>
        <dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>index_name</varname></dt>
            <dd>Specify a unique name to identify the index. </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>named_keyspace_ref</varname></dt>
            <dd>
              <codeblock><varname>named_keyspace_ref</varname> ::= [ <varname>namespace-name</varname> : ] <varname>keyspace-name</varname></codeblock>
              <p>Specify the name of the keyspace or bucket to create an index on</p>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>expression</varname></dt>
            <dd>Refers to the an attribute name or a function (or expression) that returns a single
              element.</dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>array_expression</varname></dt>
            <dd>
              <codeblock><varname>array_expression</varname> ::= <i>full_array_expr</i> | <i>simple_array_expr</i>
<i>full_array_expr</i> ::=
    (ALL | DISTINCT) ARRAY <varname>var_expr</varname>
        FOR <varname>var1</varname> ( IN | WITHIN ) <i>expr1</i>
           [ , <varname>var2</varname> ( IN | WITHIN ) <i>expr2</i> ]
           [ ( WHEN <varname>condition</varname> ) ] END
<i>simple_array_expr</i> ::=
    (ALL | DISTINCT)  (<i>var</i> | <i>expr</i>)</codeblock>
              <p>The <cmdname>ARRAY</cmdname> operator lets you map and filter the elements or
                attributes of a collection, object, or objects. It evaluates to an array of the
                operand expression that satisfies the WHEN clause, if specified. </p>
              <p><codeph><varname>var_expr</varname> ::= function(<i>var1</i>, <i>var2</i>,
                  ...)</codeph>
                <ul id="ul_ljt_vjj_rz">
                  <li>The expression is a function of the variables <i>var1</i>, <i>var2</i>, etc.
                    used in the FOR clause, and the expressions <i>expr1</i>, <i>expr2</i>, etc.
                    evaluate to an array of objects, elements of which are represented by the
                    variables <i>var1</i>, <i>var2</i>, etc. respectively.</li>
                  <li>The <i>var_expr</i> itself can be an <i>array_expr</i>, allowing nested array
                    expressions.  This enables creating array indexes on nested array fields.  See
                    example below.</li>
                </ul>evaluates to a function of
                  <varname>variable1</varname>/<varname>variable2</varname> etc, and
                  <varname>expression1/expression</varname> etc evaluate to an array of objects,
                each of which is represented by the variables. </p>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>simple_array_expr</varname></dt>
            <dd>When using <i>simple_array_expr</i>, only an array variable name <i>var</i> or an
              expression <i>expr</i> that can evaluate to an array can be specified.  In this case,
              all elements of the array are indexed. </dd>
            <dd>
              <note>Currently, array indexing is limited to using only one index key with
                  <i>array_expr</i>.  That is, to create an array index involving multiple array
                elements or multiple arrays:</note>
              <ul id="ul_myd_drj_rz">
                <li>The <i>var_expr</i> can be constructed as a compound object constituted with
                  different elements of the same array or multiiple arrays.</li>
                <li>Subsequent SELECT or DML must use similar compund objects in the WERE clause to
                  use the array index.  See examples below.</li>
              </ul>
              <note>Couchbase Server 4.6.2 release introduces the following enhacements to array
                indexing:</note>
              <ul id="ul_yzs_2rj_rz">
                <li>Allow arbitrary variable names in array index select.  That is, a SELECT query
                  that needs to use an array index can use different variable names in the query
                  from those used in the array index definition.</li>
                <li>Support <i>simple_array_expr</i> that provides simpler syntax for array indexing
                  when all array elements are indexed, without requiring to use the ARRAY operator
                  in the index definition.</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>USING GSI</dt>
            <dd>USING clause specifies the index type to use. </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>WITH options</dt>
            <dd>Use the WITH clause to specify additional options and is fully supported with nodes
              and <varname>defer_build</varname> expressions.</dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl>
      </p>
      <p>See the <xref
          href="http://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/4.1/n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/createindex.html"
          format="html" scope="external">CREATE INDEX</xref> statement for more details on the
        syntax. </p>
      <p id="query-predicate-format"><b>Format of Query Predicate in SELECT, UPDATE, or
        DELETE</b></p>
      <p>The query predicate, which must appear in the WHERE clause of a SELECT, UPDATE, or DELETE
        statement, must have the exact matching format as the variable in the array index key,
        including the name of the variable <varname>x</varname>. </p>
      <p>Consider the following expressions used in a CREATE INDEX statement:
        <codeblock>(a) DISTINCT ARRAY f(x) FOR x IN expr1 END;

(b) DISTINCT ARRAY f(x) FOR x WITHIN expr1 END;</codeblock></p>
      <p>And the expression used in the SELECT <varname>where-clause</varname>
        as:<codeblock>(c) ANY x IN expr2 SATISFIES g(x) END;

(d) ANY x WITHIN expr2 SATISFIES g(x) END</codeblock></p>
      <p>The following dependencies must be satisfied in Couchbase Server 4.5 for N1QL to consider
        the array index: <ul id="ul_k1w_4y2_cv">
          <li>The index keys used in CREATE INDEX must be used in the
              <varname>where-clause</varname>.</li>
          <li><varname>expr2</varname> in (c) and (d) must be equivalent to <varname>expr1</varname>
            in (a) and (b). This is a formal notion of equivalence. For example, if they are the
            same expressions, or equivalent arithmetic expressions such as (x+y) and (y+x).</li>
          <li>g(x) in (c) and (d) must be sargable for <codeph>f(x)</codeph> in (a) and (b). In
            other words, if there was a scalar index with key <codeph>f(x)</codeph>, that index
            would be applicable to the predicate <codeph>g(x)</codeph>. For example, the index key
              <varname>UPPER(x)</varname> is sargable for the predicate <codeph>UPPER(x) LIKE
              "John%"</codeph>.</li>
          <li>IN vs. WITHIN: Index key (a) can be used for query predicate (c). Index key (b) can be
            used for both query predicates (c) and (d).</li>
        </ul><note> Index key (b) is strictly more expensive than index key (a), for both index
          maintenance and query processing. Index key (b) and query predicate (d) are very powerful.
          They can efficiently index and query recursive trees of arbitrary depth.</note></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>N1QL Examples</title>
      <p>The following samples use the <codeph>travel-sample</codeph> bucket that is shipped with
        the product. </p>
      <p><b>Example 1: Indexing all DISTINCT elements in an array</b></p>
      <p>Create an index on all schedules:
        <codeblock>CREATE INDEX idx_sched 
        ON `travel-sample` ( DISTINCT ARRAY v.flight FOR v IN schedule END );</codeblock></p>
      <p>The following query finds the list of scheduled 'AA' flights:
        <codeblock>SELECT * FROM `travel-sample`
WHERE ANY v IN schedule SATISFIES v.flight LIKE 'AA%' END;</codeblock></p>
      <p><b>Example 2: Partial index (with WHERE clause) of individual attributes from selected
          elements (using WHEN clause) of an array</b></p>
      <p>Create an index on flight IDs scheduled in the first 4 days of the week:
        <codeblock>CREATE INDEX idx_flight_day 
ON `travel-sample` ( ALL ARRAY v.flight FOR v IN schedule WHEN v.day &lt; 4 END )
WHERE type = "route" ;</codeblock></p>
      <p><b>Example 3: Compound indexing with individual elements of an array and other
          attributes</b></p>
      <p>Create an index on scheduled flight IDs and number of stops:
        <codeblock>CREATE INDEX idx_flight_stops 
ON `travel-sample` ( stops, DISTINCT ARRAY v.flight FOR v IN schedule END )
WHERE type = "route" ;</codeblock></p>
      <p>The following query finds the list of scheduled 'AA' flights that have one or more stops:
        <codeblock>SELECT * FROM `travel-sample`
WHERE type = "route" AND ANY v IN schedule SATISFIES v.flight LIKE 'AA%' END AND stops >= 0;     </codeblock></p>
      <p><b>Example 4: Indexing the individual elements of nest arrays</b></p>
      <p>Use the DISTINCT ARRAY clause in a nested fashion to index specific attributes of a
        document when the array contains other arrays or documents that contain arrays. For example, <codeblock>cbq> UPDATE `travel-sample` 
SET schedule[0] = {"day" : 7, "special_flights" : 
                    [ {"flight" : "AI444", "utc" : "4:44:44"}, 
                      {"flight" : "AI333", "utc" : "3:33:33" } 
                    ] } 
WHERE type = "route" AND destinationairport = "CDG" AND sourceairport = "TLV";</codeblock>
        <codeblock>cbq> CREATE INDEX inested ON `travel-sample`
( DISTINCT ARRAY (DISTINCT ARRAY y FOR y IN x.special_flights END) FOR x IN schedule END) 
WHERE type = "route";</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section id="array-idx-limitations">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <p> Let's use the following sample document with Doc_Id "foo" to explain the limitations: <codeblock>"foo": {
          "a":1,
          "b":[1,2],
          "c":{"ca":[1,2,3], "cb":4},  
          "d":[{"da":5,"db":6},
          {"da":7,"db":8}],
          "e":[{"ea":9,"eb":[10,11,12]},
          {"ea":13,"eb":[14,NULL,16]}],
          "f":[[17,18],
          [19,20,21]]
          }   </codeblock><ul>
          <li>Covering indexes with indexed arrays do not cover queries where the array needs to be
            reconstructed in full form, with duplicates and position of each element placed
            correctly in the projection. <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1"
              id="table_crm_35r_w5">
              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="7.33*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Supported</entry>
                    <entry>Example</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <image href="../../introduction/images/yes.png" id="image_mq3_1wr_w5"
                        align="center" placement="break"/>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <codeblock>SELECT a 
         FROM default 
         WHERE ANY i IN b SATISFIES i &lt; 5 END;</codeblock>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <image href="../../introduction/images/yes.png" id="image_p2j_cwr_w5"
                        align="center" placement="break"/>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <codeblock>SELECT ARRAY_DISTINCT(b) 
        FROM default 
        WHERE a = 5;</codeblock>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <image href="../../introduction/images/no.png" id="image_phk_dwr_w5"
                        align="center" placement="break"/>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <codeblock>SELECT b,a 
       FROM default;</codeblock>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></li>
          <li>Indexed arrays do not maintain duplicate elements of an array or the position of the
            elements within an array in the GSI array index. This means that GSI array indexes do
            not cover expressions that reference the array attribute itself. For example, the
            following statements are not
            supported:<codeblock>SELECT b FROM default;
SELECT b[*] FROM default;
SELECT b[1] FROM default;</codeblock></li>
          <li>Array indexes only support ANY, ANY AND EVERY, ARRAY, DISTINCT, IN, WITHIN, and UNNEST
            operators. Other operators such as ALL and EVERY are not supported. <note>EVERY operator
              evaluates to true for arrays with zero elements, whereas ANY AND EVERY evaluates to
              true when the array has at least one matching element.</note></li>
          <li>The total size of the array index keys cannot exceed 10K for a single document. The
            array index key size is calculated using the total size of all array elements being
            indexed in a single document. If the total array index key size exceeds 10K in a single
            document, the items are skipped. The following error is logged to indicate that an item
            is skipped when building the index: "<systemoutput>Encoded array key is too
              long</systemoutput>" in the <filepath>indexer.log</filepath> file. The
              <filepath>indexer.log</filepath> file is included in cbcollect_info output. For
            example, the array key size for the following index is calculated by adding all the
            elements in this list : "{[1,1], [1,2]}". You can contact Couchbase Support for details
            on how to change the limit on array index key size.
            <codeblock>CREATE INDEX i1 on default(a,ARRAY x FOR x IN b END) USING GSI;</codeblock>
          </li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
    <section id="section_hgp_2tp_qz"><title>Array_expression</title><codeblock><i>array_expression</i> ::= full_array_expr | simple_array_expr
<i>full_array_expression</i> ::= 
(ALL | DISTINCT) ARRAY <i>var_expression</i> 
          FOR <i>variable1</i> ( IN | WITHIN ) <i>expression1</i>
          [ , <i>variable2</i> ( IN | WITHIN ) <i>expression2</i> ]
          [ ( WHEN <i>condition</i> ) ] END
<i>simple_array_expression</i> ::= 
(ALL | DISTINCT)  (<i>var</i> | <i>expr</i>) </codeblock><p>
        <dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>index_name</varname></dt>
            <dd>Specify a unique name to identify the index. </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>named_keyspace_ref</varname></dt>
            <dd>
              <codeblock><varname>named_keyspace_ref</varname> ::= [ <varname>namespace-name</varname> : ] <varname>keyspace-name</varname></codeblock>
              <p>Specify the name of the keyspace or bucket to create an index on</p>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>expression</varname></dt>
            <dd>Refers to the an attribute name or a function (or expression) that returns a single
              element.</dd>
          </dlentry>
          <dlentry>
            <dt><varname>simple_array_expression</varname></dt>
            <dd>
              <codeblock><varname>array_expression</varname> ::= 
[ ALL ] DISTINCT ARRAY <varname>var_expression</varname> FOR <varname>variable1</varname> ( IN | WITHIN ) [<b>TO_ARRAY</b>] <varname>expression1</varname>
                                      [ , <varname>variable2</varname> ( IN | WITHIN ) [<b>TO_ARRAY</b>] <varname>expression2</varname> ]
                                      [ ( WHEN <varname>condition</varname> ) ] END</codeblock>
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl>
      </p>The ARRAY operator lets you map and filter the elements or attributes of a collection,
      object, or objects. It evaluates to an array of the operand expression that satisfies the WHEN
      clause, if specified.<p dir="ltr"><i>var_expression</i> ::== function(var1, var2, …)</p><p
        dir="ltr">
        <ul id="ul_lgp_fsp_qz">
          <li>The expression is a function of the variables <i>var1</i>, <i>var2</i>, etc. used in
            the FOR clause, and the expressions <i>expr1</i>, <i>expr2</i>, etc. evaluate to an
            array of object, of which elements are represented by the variables <i>var1</i>,
              <i>var2</i>, etc.</li>
          <li>The <i>var_expression</i> itself can be an <i>array_expression</i>, allowing nested
            array expressions. This enables creating array indexes on nested array fields. See
            example below.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>When using <i>simple_array_expression</i>, just an array variable name <i>var</i>, or an
      expression <i>expr</i> that can evaluate to an array can be specified. In this case, all
      elements of the array are indexed.</section>
    <section id="section_igp_2tp_qz"><note> Currently, Array indexing I slimited to using only one
        index key with array_expression.  That is, to create an array index involving multiple array
        elements or multiple arrays:<ul id="ul_b3s_2tp_qz">
          <li>The var_expression can be constructed as a compound object constituted with different
            elements of the same array of multiple arrays.</li>
          <li>Subsequent SELECT or DML must use similar compound objects in the WHERE clause to use
            the array index.  See examples below.</li>
        </ul></note><note> The Couchbase Server 4.6.2 release introduces the following enhancements
        to array indexing:<ul id="ul_vzb_ftp_qz">
          <li>Allow arbitrary variable names in array index selection.  That is, a SELECT query that
            needs to use an array index can use different variable names in the query from those
            used in the array index definition.  In earlier releases, the variable names MUST
            exactly match.  See 4.5 documentation for more details.</li>
          <li>Support <codeph>simple_array_expression</codeph> that provides simpler syntax for
            array indexing when all array elements are indexed, without requiring to use the ARRAY
            operator in the index definition.</li>
        </ul></note><title>Array Examples</title>The following examples use the <xref
        href="https://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/4.6/sdk/sample-application.html"
        format="html" scope="external">travel-sample</xref> bucket that is shipped with the product.
          <p><b>Example 1:  Indexing all DISTINCT elements in an array</b></p><p>Create an index of
        all
        schedules:<codeblock>C1: CREATE INDEX idx_sched
    ON `travel-sample`(DISTINCT ARRAY v FOR v IN schedule END );</codeblock></p>The
      following query finds the list of schedule 'UA'
          flights:<codeblock>Q1: SELECT * FROM `travel-sample`
    WHERE ANY v IN schedule SATIFIES v.flight LIKE 'UA%' END;</codeblock><p><b>Example
          2:  Partial index (with WHERE clause) of individual attributes from selected elements
          (using WHEN clause) of an array</b></p><p>Create an index on flight IDs schedule in the
        first 4 days of the
        week:<codeblock>C2: CREATE INDEX idx_flight_day
    ON `travel-sample`(ALL ARRAY v.flight FOR v IN SCHEDULE WHEN v.day &lt; 4 END)
    WHERE type = "route";</codeblock></p><p>The
        following query finds the list of scheduled 'UA' flights on day
        1:<codeblock>Q2: SELECT * FROM `travel-sample`
    WHERE type = "route" AND
    ANY v IN schedule SATISFIES (v.flight LIKE 'UA%') AND (v.day=1) END;</codeblock></p><p>
        <note> The index C2 qualifies for the query Q2 because:<ul id="ul_sdz_wfp_qz">
            <li>Q2 predicate  type = "route" matches that of the partial index WHERE clause.</li>
            <li>The ANY operator uses the index key v.flight on which the index C2 is defined.</li>
            <li>The ANY-SATISFIES condition (v.day=1) in Q2 is sargable to that in the index
              definition WHEN clause (v.day&lt;4)</li>
          </ul></note>
      </p></section>
    <section id="section_ggq_qhp_qz"><b>Example 3:  Compound array index with individual elements of
        an array and other non-array fields</b></section>
    <section id="section_csb_22k_rz">Create an index on scheduled flight IDs and number of
      stops:<codeblock>C3: CREATE INDEX idx_stops_flight
    ON `travel-sample` (stops, DISTINCT ARRAY v.flight FOR v IN schedule END)
    WHERE type = "route";</codeblock>The
      following query find the list of scheduled UA flights that have one or more
        stops:<codeblock>Q3: SELECT * FROM `travel-sample`
    WHERE type = "route"
    AND stops >= 0
    AND ANY v IN schedule SATISFIES v.flight LIKE 'UA%' END;</codeblock><b>Example
        4:  Indexing the individual elements of nest arrays</b></section>
    <section id="section_hgq_qhp_qz">Use the DISTINCT ARRAY clause in a nested fashion to index
      specific attributes of a document when the array contains other arrays or documents that
      contain arrays.  For
      example,<codeblock>cbq> Update `travel-sample`
     SET schedule[0] = {"day": 7, "special_flights" :
         [ {"flight" : "AI444", "utc" : "4:44:44"},
           {"flight" : "AI333", "utc" : "3:33:33"}
         ] }
     WHERE type = "route" 
     AND destinationairport = "CDG"
     AND sourceairport = "TLV";</codeblock></section>
    <section id="section_g1q_mgk_rz">Create an index on scheduled flight IDs and number of
      stops:<codeblock>C4: CREATE INDEX idx_nested ON `travel-sample`
    (DISTINCT ARRAY 
        <b>(DISTINCT ARRAY y.flight
        FOR y IN x-special_flights END)</b>
    FOR x IN schedule END)
    WHERE type = "route" ;</codeblock></section>
    <p>
      <note>In this case, the inner ARRAY construct (in <b>bold</b>) is used as the <i>var_expr</i>
        for the outer ARRAY construct.</note>
    </p>
    <section id="section_xk2_1jk_rz">The following query Q4 uses nested ANY operator to use the
      index:<codeblock>Q4: SELECT count(*) FROM `travel-sample`
    WHERE type = "route"
    AND ANY x IN schedule SATISFIES
        (ANY y IN x.special_flights SATISFIES y.flight IS NOT NULL END)
    END;</codeblock></section>
    <section id="section_pqv_z3k_rz">The following query Q5 uses UNNEST operator to use the
      index:<codeblock>Q5: SELECT count(*) FROM `travel-sample`
    UNNEST schedule AS x
    UNNEST x.special_flights AS y
    WHERE type = "route"
    AND y.flight IS NOT NULL;</codeblock></section>
  </body>
  <related-links><link href="http://blog.couchbase.com/2016/may/1.making-most-of-your-arrays..-with-covering-array-indexes-and-more" format="html" scope="external"> <linktext>Blog: Covering Array Indexes </linktext></link></related-links>
</topic>
