<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_atw_ymv_xq">
 <title>Index service operations</title>
 <shortdesc>Index service operations refers to the internal operations for managing primary key and
  secondary indexes in the Index service.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  
  <p>The index service has the following major components:</p>
  
  
  <dl>
   <dlentry>
    
    <dt>Projector</dt>
    <dd>The projector is responsible for mapping mutations to a set of secondary key versions. The
     projector can reside within the master key-value (KV) node in which the mutation is generated
     or it can reside in separate node. The projector receives mutations from ep-engine through UPR
     protocol and sends the evaluated results to the router. </dd>
   </dlentry>
   
   <dlentry><dt>Router</dt> 
    <dd>The router is responsible for sending the key version to the index nodes. It relies on the
     index distribution/partitioning topology to determine the indexer which should receive the key
     version. The router resides in the same node as the projector. </dd></dlentry>
   
   <dlentry><dt>Index manager</dt>
    <dd>The index manager is responsible for receiving requests for indexing operations (creation,
     deletion, maintenance, scan/lookup). The index manager is located in the index node, which can
     be different from the KV node. The index manager runs in one indexer node as the index
     coordinator master and in a few other configurable nodes as the index coordinator replica. In
     rest of the nodes, it runs in dormant mode.</dd></dlentry>
   
   <dlentry><dt>Indexer (local indexer)</dt>
    <dd>The indexer processes the key versions received from router and provides persistence support
     for the index. Indexer also provides the interface for query client to run index scans and to
     gather data for queries. The indexer resides in index node.</dd></dlentry>
   
   <dlentry><dt>Query catalog</dt>
    <dd>The query catalog component provides catalog implementation for the Query service. This
     component allows the Query servuce to perform Index DDL (Create, Drop) and Index Scan/Stats
     operations. The query catalog resides in the same node as the Query service.</dd></dlentry>
  </dl>
  
  
  
  <p>The following diagram shows the index architectural flow:</p>
  
  <fig><image width="720" href="../images/index-2nd-arch.png"></image></fig>
  
  
  
  
 </conbody>
</concept>
