<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="concept_y1w_3hb_ys">
 <title>View Indexes for N1QL</title>
 <shortdesc>Just like GSIs, Views for N1QL supports a variety of OLTP like use-cases including basic, ad-hoc, and short-running reporting queries that require filtering and aggregations.</shortdesc>
 <conbody>
  <p>Views are deployed into the data service as a local index within the Couchbase Server cluster, aligned with data service distribution. Views provide the following advantages: <ul>
   <li>Auto Partitioning of Indexes: Views come with auto partitioning and smart placement within the data service. </li>
   <li>Built-in replicas and HA for Indexing: Views come with built in replicas for high availability within the data service including rack/zone awareness support and rebalance support.</li>
   <li>Simple Scaling Model: Views are automatically placed and scaled with the data service.</li></ul></p>
  <section><title>Creating Views for N1QL</title>
   <p>You can define a primary or secondary index using Views for N1QL using the CREATE INDEX statement. For more information on the syntax and examples, see <xref
    href="../n1ql/n1ql-language-reference/createindex.dita"/> statement.</p>
  </section>
  <section><title>Placement of Views</title>
   <p>Data nodes hash partition data so that data is uniformly distributed across the cluster. View indexes are co-located with the data and each view index contains only a subset of the data that is available on the node.</p>
  </section>
  <section><title>Views Performance</title>
   <p>Views require a scatter gather due to its architecture. View is a local index that is placed
    aligned with data distribution in the data service. <fig id="fig_bqj_1bb_vv">
     <title>Monitor Resource Usage for Index Nodes</title>
     <image placement="break" href="images/query-exe-with-views.png" width="370"
      id="image_cqj_1bb_vv"/></fig></p>
  </section>
  <section><title>Query and View Consistency</title>
   <p>In Couchbase Server, mutations to data in the data service is done with full consistency. (All mutations to a given key is done using the same vBucket on a node and is immediately available to anyone reading the latest value for the given key). However views are maintained in an eventually consistent manner. This is true for all indexers (GSI, View and Spatial). At query time, you can specify a query consistency flag for each N1QL query request, similar to the view API. The query consistency flag can be one of the following: <ul>
    <li><parmname>Stale-ok</parmname>: This scan_consistency flag executes the query immediately without requiring any consistency for the query. If the view maintenance is running behind, query may return out-of-date results. </li>
    <li><parmname>Stale-false</parmname>: This scan_consistency flag executes the query but require the indexes to be updated to the logical timestamp of the query request. For example, application issuing the query may have done its last update 10 msec ago. Application issuing the query with stale-false scan consistency flag, takes the logical timestamp of query request. This behavior achieves consistency, at least or later than the moment of the request timestamp. If the view maintenance is running behind the request timestamp, query waits for the view to catch up to the request timestamp.</li> </ul>For N1QL, the default consistency setting is not_bounded.</p>
  </section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
