<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">

<concept id="concept_kx3_kkf_xp">
	<title>Security in Couchbase </title>
	<shortdesc>Security is very important for big data applications, which process a large amount of
		unstructured data coming in big volumes and at high speed. </shortdesc>
	<conbody>
	
		<p>Couchbase Server provides security features that allow the administrators to implement various
			security controls to ensure secure deployment. </p>
		<p>Secure deployment in Couchbase consists of security controls to access the entire stack, from
			physical protection of the network infrastructure to Couchbase Server and the deployed
			applications</p>
	
		<p><image href="../images/BP-02.png" width="240"/></p>
		<p>Infrastructure protection covers the network itself, storage devices, servers, virtual
			machines, and the operating systems installed on these machines. Database and
			application protection covers Couchbase Server itself and different applications used
			with it. </p> 
		<section><title>Where is security enforced</title> Maintain and update security in the following
			areas: <ul>
				<li>Outside network, where web browsers and mobile applications are located.</li>
				<li>Perimeter network between the internal and external firewall, which typically
					consists of web servers and load balancing machines. This network provides
					physical separation between backend and external interfaces, such as the web and
					mobile applications.</li>
				<li>Internal network within the internal firewall, where Couchbase Server is
					typically deployed. </li>
			</ul>
			<p><image href="../images/BP_security1.png" width="620"/></p>
			<p>Requests from the external network come through an external firewall and are directed
				to the load balancing unit, where security administrators can introduce packet
				filtering and blocking of malicious IP addresses. After that, the requests proceed
				to a web server. </p><p>On the second firewall level, between the perimeter and
				internal network, the IT or database administrators can allow only Couchbase ingress
				and egress ports to be accessible through the internal firewall.</p><p>While the
				external firewall allows only certain ports to be open, the internal firewall allows
				only certain Couchbase ports to be open. </p></section> 
	</conbody>
</concept>
