<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_qbs_wpm_lq">
  <title>Encryption on the Wire</title>
  <shortdesc>Couchbase encrypts the data moving between client and server, between servers within a
    cluster, and between data centers. </shortdesc>
<body>
  
    <note type="note">Starting with version 4.0, Couchbase Server uses the TLS protocol by default for encrypted interactions. 
      The server supports both TLS 1.0-1.2 for XDCR. Which version it uses depends on the source and target clusters.</note>
    <p>Data moving between client and server needs to be protected from any attackers eavesdropping
        on the connection. Couchbase Server enables encrypted data access using SSL/TLS for
        client-server communications.</p>
    
  <section id="admin-access"><title>Secure Administrative Access</title>
   <p>The Full Administrators can configure encrypted administrative access using SSL/TLS to
      enable HTTPS access for the Couchbase Web Console and the REST API.</p>
   
      
      
      
      <p>Couchbase Server client libraries support client-side encryption using the SSL/TLS protocol
        by encrypting data in-flight between the client and the server. This encryption establishes a
        secure channel between the remote machine and the server.</p>
      
      
      
      <p>By default, Couchbase Server generates a self-signed certificate for the initial node, which
        is propagated throughout the server nodes in the cluster. You can switch over from a
        self-signed to an X.509 certificate before you deploy your application into production. </p>
      <p>To set up certification, see <xref
          href="security-x509certsintro.dita#topic_cfk_mhn_xv/configuring-x.509"/>.</p>
      
    <sectiondiv><b>Connecting to the Couchbase Web Console </b><p>While an administrative console is
          typically protected via an HTTPS connection, the new administrative access on port
            <codeph>18091</codeph> allows connection to the Couchbase Web Console over SSL/TLS,
          which is enabled by default.  </p><p>To talk over SSL/TLS to the Couchbase Web Console,
          connect to the following URL with your web browser:
            <userinput>https://couchbase_server:18091</userinput></p></sectiondiv>

     <sectiondiv><b>Verifying the cluster's certificate </b><p>To verify which certificate your
          cluster is currently using:  </p><ol>
          <li>Select <menucascade>
              <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol>
              <uicontrol>Root Certificate</uicontrol>
            </menucascade>. <note type="note">Only the Full Administrator role can see the Root
              Certificate tab in the Couchbase Web Console UI.</note><p><image
                href="pict/self-signed-cert.png" id="image_tps_ftv_4v" align="left" width="720"
              /></p>
          </li>
          <li>The <wintitle>Root Certificate</wintitle> link shows that a self-signed certificate
            has been deployed across the cluster. This certificate can be regenerated or replaced
            using <xref href="../rest-api/rest-encryption.dita#topic_i45_xf2_gw"/> or <xref
              href="../cli/cbcli/ssl-manage.dita#cbcli-xdcr-ssl">CLI </xref> commands for managing
            certificates.</li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv> 
      
     <sectiondiv><b>Viewing the SSL Certificate Used in the Web Browser</b>
        <ol>
          <li>Connect to Couchbase Server through an encrypted port to communicate on a secure
            channel (<codeph>18091</codeph> for REST HTTP or <codeph>18092</codeph> for CAPI HTTP). </li>
          <li>Log in with the Full Administrator's name and password. </li>
          <li>Once you are logged in, the URL shows a secure connection.  </li>
        </ol><p>The following section shows an example URL of a secure connection using the Safari
          web browser.</p></sectiondiv>
    
      
     <sectiondiv><b>Disabling the Couchbase Web Console on Port 8091 </b><p>If you would like to
          force Administrators to log in to the UI over an encrypted channel, you can disable the UI
          over the 8091 HTTP port, so that administrators can only access the administrative web
          console over port 18091.  </p><note type="remember">This setting does not disable port
          8091 completely since port 8091 is an important Couchbase port that also handles REST
          requests in addition to the administrative web console. </note><p>To disable the Couchbase
          Web Console over port 8091:
          <codeblock>curl -X POST -u Administrator:password http://127.0.0.1:8091/diag/eval \
            -d 'ns_config:set(disable_ui_over_http, true)’</codeblock>
        </p><p>To re-enable the Couchbase Web Console over port 8091:
          <codeblock>curl -X POST -u Administrator:password http://127.0.0.1:8091/diag/eval \
            -d 'ns_config:set(disable_ui_over_http, false)’</codeblock></p>
      </sectiondiv> 
      </section>
  
 

  <section id="data-access"><title>Secure Data Access</title>
<p>Couchbase Server client libraries support client-side encryption using the Secure
  Sockets Layer (SSL) and Transport Layer Security (TLS).</p>
  
  
 
    <note>Couchbase Server and SDKs support TLS v1.0 - 1.2 by default. Which version you use depends
      on the client and server version. Older versions might still use SSL, and should be
      upgraded to newer version of the SDK.</note>
    <p>Starting with Couchbase Server version 4.1.1, you can set the minimum version of TLS 1.2 or
      higher using the following command:
      <codeblock>curl -X POST -u Administrator:password http://127.0.0.1:8091/diag/eval -d "ns_config:set(ssl_minimum_protocol, 'tlsv1.2’)”</codeblock></p>
    <p>The TLS 1.2 setup command can be executed per cluster. The command has to be invoked using full
      administrator privileges.</p>
    <note type="note">For changes to be affective on port 18092, cluster restart is needed. 
      For changes to be affective just on port 18091, no cluster restart is needed.
    </note>
    <p>Encryption for data access is performed through client-server communication and view
      access.</p>
    
    
  <sectiondiv><b>SSL/TLS Based Client-server Communication </b><p>Couchbase Server client libraries
          support client-side encryption using the SSL/TLS protocol by encrypting data in-flight
          between the client and the server. For Couchbase clients released after version 2.0,
          Couchbase Server provides secure client-server communication that does not require
          configuration. </p><p>When a TLS connection is established, a handshaking, known as the
            <term>TLS Handshake Protocol</term>, occurs. Within this handshake, a client hello
            (<codeph>ClientHello</codeph>) and a server hello (<codeph>ServerHello</codeph>) message
          are passed (RFC 5246). First, the client sends a cipher suite list, a list of the cipher
          suites that it supports, in order of preference. Then the server replies with the cipher
          suite that it has selected from the client cipher suite list. Check whether your clients
          support TLS. </p><p>The key-exchange algorithms like RSA and Elliptic Curve Cryptography
          (ECC) govern the way the server and client will determine which symmetric keys to use
          during a TLS session. The TLS protocol supports both RSA and ECC, however for Couchbase
          Server, it supports <i>only</i> RSA keys.</p><p>To enable SSL/TLS on the client side, you
          need to get a certificate from Couchbase Server and then follow the steps appropriate to
          the client you are using. </p><p>You can obtain a self-signed, server -generated
          certificate using the Couchbase Web Console. Navigate to <menucascade>
            <uicontrol>Settings</uicontrol>
            <uicontrol>Certificate</uicontrol>
            <uicontrol>Show certificate</uicontrol>
          </menucascade> and copy the certificate. </p><note type="note">If the self-signed
          certificate obtained via the Couchbase Web Console is regenerated, you must obtain a new
          one.</note></sectiondiv>
    
 <sectiondiv><b>SSL/TLS Support by Clients </b><p>The following clients support SSL/TLS: Java, .NET,
          Node.js, PHP, C, and Go.</p><note type="note">Use the Couchbase network port
            <codeph>11207</codeph> for data communication between the client and the data nodes
          using SSL/TLS. </note></sectiondiv>
  
<sectiondiv>SSL/TLS Based View Access
      
      <p>A new port <codeph>18092</codeph> is established for view access:
        <codeph>https://couchbase_server:18092</codeph>
      </p></sectiondiv>
    
    
<sectiondiv><b>Supported Ciphers</b>
        <p>Couchbase Server uses the ciphers that are accepted by default by OpenSSL.The default is
          to have high-security ciphers built in with openSSL. For example, on the MAC OS these are: <ul>
            <li>AES256-SHA...YES</li>
            <li>AES128-SHA...YES</li>
            <li>DES-CBC3-SHA...YES </li>
          </ul></p><p>You can override this selection by setting the environment variable before
          starting Couchbase as follows: </p><p><codeph>COUCHBASE_SSL_CIPHER_LIST</codeph>=
            &lt;<varname>list of ciphers to accept</varname>&gt; </p><p>Set the variable to
            <codeph>COUCHBASE_SSL_CIPHER_LIST= MEDIUM, HIGH</codeph> to include only medium- and
          high-security ciphers for your installation.</p> For example, on the MAC OS these are: <ul>
          <li>SEED-SHA...YES</li>
          <li>AES256-SHA...YES</li>
          <li>AES128-SHA...YES</li>
          <li>DES-CBC3-SHA...YES</li>
          <li>RC4-SHA...YES</li>
          <li>RC4-MD5...YES</li>
          <li>RC4-MD5...YES </li>
        </ul></sectiondiv>
 
  </section>
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <section><title>Data Moving Between Servers within a Cluster</title>
    <p>Your data has to be available all the time (24x7x365), and your applications must be able to
        access that data even if any of the servers in the cluster dies. To ensure high
        availability, Couchbase Server replicates data within the cluster and across data
        centers.</p>
      <p>If you encrypt all your sensitive data in the documents, the replica copies will be
        transmitted as is (encrypted) and stored. For added security, it is a good security practice
        to use IPSec on the network that connects the Couchbase server nodes. </p>
    <p>IPSec has two modes: tunnel mode and transport mode. 
      We recommend using IPSec with the transport mode, as it is easier to setup than the tunnel mode 
      and does not require creating tunnels between all pairs of Couchbase nodes. </p><p>To learn more about setting up transport mode IPSec for Couchbase, see the blog <xref
          href="http://blog.couchbase.com/2016/june/configuration-ipsec-for-a-couchbase-cluster"
          format="html" scope="external">"Configuring IPsec for a Couchbase Cluster"</xref>.
      </p></section>
  <section><title>Data Moving Between Data Centers</title>
    <p>To protect sensitive data transmitted among data centers in different geo-locations, you can
        use TLS to encrypt your XDCR connection. When you enable TLS in XDCR, Couchbase Server uses
        TLS certificates, and all traffic between source and destination datacenters will be
        encrypted. The encryption causes a slight increase in the CPU load.</p>
    <p>It is a good security practice to rotate the XDCR
        certificates periodically, as per your organization's security policy.</p>
    </section>
</body>
</topic>
