<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_cfk_mhn_xv">
  <title>X.509 Certificates for TLS</title> <shortdesc>Couchbase Server uses X.509 certificates to encrypt client-server communications and
    XDCR (Cross Data Center Replication).</shortdesc>
  <body>
  
      <p>Couchbase Server 4.5 Enterprise Edition supports X.509 certificates for Transport Layer
        Security (TLS).</p>
      <p>With X.509 certificates, Couchbase Server can strongly encrypt client-server communications
        and <xref href="http://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/4.1/xdcr/xdcr-intro.html"
          format="html" scope="external">XDCR</xref> (Cross Data Center Replication).</p>

    <p><note type="note">Full administrators in Couchbase can manage certificates using the Couchbase CLI
        tools (as described in <xref href="../cli/cbcli/ssl-manage.dita#cbcli-xdcr-ssl"/>) or REST
<<<<<<< HEAD
        API.</note></p>

=======
        API (as described in <xref href="../rest-api/rest-encryption.dita#topic_i45_xf2_gw"
        />.</note></p>
>>>>>>> 56615ef... xref checked for CB 4.5
      <p><image href="pict/ca_sys_diagram.png" id="image_gnp_5mk_y5" width="570"/></p>
      <p>With CA-based certificates, you also achieve their simplified management and rotation
      without client downtime. Full administrators in Couchbase can manage certificates using the
      Couchbase CLI tools (as described in <xref href="../cli/cbcli/ssl-manage.dita#cbcli-xdcr-ssl"
      />) or REST API (as described in .</p>
      <note type="note">Your prior knowledge of TLS/SSL, PKI certificates including X.509
        certificates, and Certificate Authorities (CAs) is assumed for this overview. </note>
      
      <p><b>When to use X.509 Certificates</b></p>
      <p>An X.509 certificate does more than just
        distribute the public key: it is signed by a trusted (internal or third-party) CA and
        verifies the identity of the server so that clients know their information is not being sent
        to a rogue
        server.</p>
      <p>Some common scenarios which may require use of X.509 certificates are:</p>
      <ul id="ul_j3z_b1k_1v">
        <li>In production where clients have to go through the internet.</li>
        <li>When transferring sensitive data on the wire between application and Couchbase Server,
          or between data centers (XDCR).</li>
        <li>When mandated by regulatory compliance regulations.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>CA Hierarchies Supported by Couchbase</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase customers can tie Couchbase Server with their CA hierarchies. The CA at the top
        of a hierarchy is called the root authority, or root CA. There are two types of CA
        hierarchies supported by Couchbase: single- or n-tier. </p>
      
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Single-Tier Hierarchy</dt>
          <dd>In its simplest form, the single-tier hierarchy starts with a root CA. <p><image
            href="pict/ca_single_tier.png" id="image_my1_wmk_y5" align="left"/></p><p>For
              example, as shown in the figure above, the root CA is also the issuing CA. All
              certificates immediately below the root certificate inherit its trustworthiness and
              can be used to secure systems. </p><p>Although this is the simplest form of CA
                hierarchy, most enterprises use an N-tier CA hierarchy as described next.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>N-Tier Hierarchy</dt>
          <dd>Typically, in many production deployments, a hierarchy will have multiple
            CAs.<p><image href="pict/ca_n_tier.png" id="image_t1g_ymk_y5" align="left" width="570"/>
            </p></dd>
          <dd>In a multi-tier hierarchy, the root CA issues certificates to the intermediate CAs, which
            in turn generate intermediate certificates used to sign the client
            certificates such as a cluster certificate:<ul>
              <li>Trusted root CA > Intermediate CA > Cluster certificate</li>
              <li>Trusted root CA > Intermediate CA 1 > Intermediate CA 2.... >
                Intermediate CA N > Cluster certificate </li>
            </ul><p>When you need to regenerate the intermediate certificate, ensure
              that the chain can be verified up to the root CA. </p><p>If all
                intermediate certificates are not installed on your server, some clients
                might think you are on an insecure connection. This results in
                'untrusted' warnings like the following:</p><p><image
                  href="pict/back-to-safety.png" id="image_ofr_hg1_z5" align="left"
                  width="450"/>
                </p><p>To avoid such warnings, a server should always send a complete trust
                  chain. The trust chain contains your certificate concatenated with all
                  intermediate certificates.</p>
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      
  </body>
</topic>
