<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="rbac_upgrade">
 
 <title>
  Upgrading to RBAC
 </title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  Couchbase provides an upgrade path, whereby users can seamlessly transition their
  activities from Couchbase Server 4.6 and earlier (which are all pre-RBAC releases) to
  5.0 and post-5.0 (which are RBAC-enabled releases). 
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Migration to 5.0 and post-5.0
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Releases of Couchbase Server prior to 5.0 did not feature the Role-Based
    Access Control that is now provided. 5.0/post-5.0 administrators and developers must therefore
    become familiar with the new model, and modify procedures as appropriate.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    However, to ensure the continued running of legacy applications, Couchbase Server
    provides an automated migration of existing buckets to the new RBAC model, as part of the upgrade procedure. 
    The following sections explain this migration.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Legacy Bucket-Definitions
   </title>
   
   <p>
    In releases of Couchbase Server prior to 5.0, buckets could either be established on
    the <i>standard port</i> (11211), which was SASL-enabled, and required that the bucket be
    password-protected; or on an administrator-dedicated port, in which case the bucket
    was accessible by means of the ASCII protocol, and was not password-protected. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Each of these types of bucket-definition is considered below, in relation to how the 
    corresponding buckets are accessed
    following upgrade to Couchbase Server 5.0 and beyond.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Legacy Buckets on the Standard Port
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Legacy buckets that were defined on the SASL-enabled standard port were protected by a
    <i>bucket-password</i>. These bucket-passwords are no longer supported, in Couchbase 
    Server 5.0 and beyond. Instead,
    buckets, as other resources, must be accessed through RBAC.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    During the upgrade process, Couchbase performs forward-migration on legacy, password-protected buckets;
    so that following upgrade, the buckets can be accessed through RBAC, without immediate changes to
    authentication-procedures required. This forward-migration has the following characteristics:
   </p>
   
   <ul>
    <li>
     Any existing bucket that is resident on the standard port is <i>stripped of
      its legacy bucket-password</i>.
     <p>
      <!-- Vertical Space -->
     </p>
     
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
     After all cluster-nodes have successfully
     been upgraded, 
     for each bucket that has been stripped of its bucket-password,
     a new <i>user</i> is created; whose username is
     identical to the name of the bucket. This user appears along with all others, in the <b>Security</b> screen
     of the Couchbase Web Console. 
     <p>
      <!-- Vertical Space -->
     </p>
     
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
     Each new user that has been defined to correspond to a legacy bucket that featured a bucket-password is 
     assigned a user-password: this user-password is
     identical to the stripped, bucket-password of the legacy bucket; and will be referenced in association with
     the new user, in the <b>Security</b> screen
     of the Couchbase Web Console.
     
     <p>
      Each new user that has been defined to correspond to a legacy bucket that featured no bucket-password is
      <i>not</i> assigned a user-password.
     </p>
     <p>
      <!-- Vertical Space -->
     </p>
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
     Each new user that has been defined in this way &#8212; either with or without a password &#8212; is assigned 
     the <b>Application Access</b> role, by default. This
     role (which in RBAC-enabled versions of Couchbase Server prior to 5.5 was referred to as <b>Full Bucket Access</b>)
     allows the new user the same bucket-access privileges (including read-write on bucket-data) as were previously
     possible by means of the bucket-password; and is visible in association with the user in the <b>Security</b> screen
     of the Couchbase Web Console.
     <p>
      <!-- Vertical Space -->
     </p>
     
    </li>
    
    <li>
     Applications that continue to attempt bucket-access by specifying the legacy bucket-name and (where appropriate) 
     bucket-password <i>do not fail</i>;
     since the bucket-name is interpreted as a username, and the bucket-password as a corresponding user-password; and
     the bucket access-privilege thereby attained is identical to that attained under previous releases of Couchbase Server.
     <p>
      <!-- Vertical Space -->
     </p>
     
    </li>
    
   </ul>
  </section>
  
 </body>
 
</topic>
