<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_s4n_42h_vx">
  <title>Pluggable Authentication Modules</title>
  <shortdesc>Pluggable Authentication Modules (PAM) is an authentication framework used by Linux and
    other operating systems. It enables you to integrate multiple low-level authentication schemes
    into a high-level application programming interface (API). Starting from version 4.6, the
    Enterprise Edition of Couchbase Server supports administrator authentication using
    PAM.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Using PAM, administrators can set up the following features: <ul>
        <li><b>External authentication</b>: PAM support enables Linux administrator accounts defined
            in<codeph>/etc/shadow</codeph> to be used in Couchbase Server.</li>
        <li><b>Password policy management</b>: PAM enables you to easily control password expiration
          rules, and synchronize administrator passwords on all servers through Linux password
          management.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <note type="important">Although PAM provides several authentication modules, Couchbase Server
      PAM authentication supports only the Linux password module. PAM authentication in Couchbase
      Server is an enterprise only feature, and is only available on Linux platforms.</note>
    
    <section><title>Getting Started with PAM Authentication</title>
      <p><b>Prerequisites</b></p>
      <p>Ensure that the following prerequisites are available in your environment before using PAM in Couchbase: 
        <ul>
          <li><xref href="http://www.couchbase.com/nosql-databases/downloads" format="html"
              scope="external">Couchbase Server version 4.6</xref> (or above) running on Linux
            environment.</li>
          <li>saslauthd library 2.1.x or higher.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p><b>Linux Password Authentication Using PAM</b></p>
      <p>The following walks through a sample authentication scenario which uses PAM only to check
        Linux user login names and passwords. Every administrator permitted to connect to Couchbase
        Server should have a Linux user account that is mapped to an administrator role in
        Couchbase. You’ll need root access to perform the following tasks.</p>
      <p><ol>
        <li>Install the <codeph>saslauthd</codeph> library for your Linux distribution, if it is not
            already installed.
                <p><b>Centos/RHEL</b></p><codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ yum install cyrus-sasl</codeblock><p><b>Ubuntu/Debian</b></p><codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ apt-get install sasl2-bin</codeblock></li>
          <li>Ensure that the <codeph>couchbase</codeph> user is in the <codeph>sasl</codeph> group
            to allow access to <codeph>saslauthd</codeph>.<p>
              <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ usermod -aG sasl couchbase</codeblock>
            </p></li>
        <li>In the <codeph>saslauthd</codeph> config file, verify that <codeph>saslauthd</codeph> is
            set up to use PAM.<p><b>
              Centos/RHEL</b></p><codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ grep "MECH" /etc/sysconfig/saslauthd
MECH=pam</codeblock>If the above command does not return that <codeph>MECH</codeph> is set to
              <codeph>pam</codeph> then adjust the parameter in the config file
          accordingly.<p><b>Ubuntu/Debian</b><codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ grep 'MECHANISMS' /etc/default/saslauthd
MECHANISMS="pam"</codeblock></p><p>If
              the above command does not return that <codeph>MECHANISMS</codeph> is set to
                <codeph>"pam"</codeph> then adjust the parameter in the config file
            accordingly.</p></li>
        <li>Set up PAM to authenticate the Couchbase service by creating a file named
              <filepath>/etc/pam.d/couchbase</filepath>. Because Linux users are supported, copy
              <filepath>/etc/pam.d/passwd</filepath> to <filepath>/etc/pam.d/couchbase</filepath>.
          <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ cp /etc/pam.d/passwd /etc/pam.d/couchbase</codeblock></li>
        <li>Test that Linux authentication permits you to log in. For example, use user name:
              <userinput>don</userinput> and password: <userinput>secretpa$$</userinput>. You can
            execute this step with any other Linux credentials as well. <p>To create a Linux user
              and set password, you can use the following
              commands:<codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ useradd don
$ passwd don</codeblock></p></li>
        <li>Map the Linux login name (user name) to one or many Couchbase Server administrator
            roles. <image placement="break" href="pict/security-pam-auth-linux.png" width="570"
              id="image_nbk_ykh_vx"/></li>
        <li>Re-start the SASL service for PAM authentication to take effect.
          <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ service saslauthd restart</codeblock></li>
        <li>Restart the Couchbase service for external authentication through PAM to take effect.
          <codeblock outputclass="language-bash">$ service couchbase-server restart</codeblock></li>
        <li>Try connecting using the Linux user credentials created earlier,
              <userinput>don/secretpa$$</userinput>. <p>Couchbase Server should permit the
              connection, and once authenticated, the privileges of that user in Couchbase should be
              as per the role mapping. </p></li>
      </ol>
        Congratulations! You've successfully logged in as a Linux user, using the privileges granted through the administrator role membership.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
