<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_auth_for_admins">
 
 <title>
  Creating and Managing Users with the UI
 </title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  Using the Couchbase Web Console, you can assign roles to users interactively.
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
  
  <section>
   <title>
    Authorization for Full Administrators
   </title>
   
   <p>
    The administrator who initially performs installation and configuration of Couchbase
    Server &#8212; the <i>Full Administrator</i> &#8212; is granted read-write access 
    to the entire system. The user ID of this
    administrator can be either locally defined, or remotely; for example, by means of LDAP.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Once basic system-configuration has been completed, the Full Administrator
    is free to add additional administrators to the system, and assign them roles; thereby specifing their 
    access-privileges.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Adding Users
   </title>
   
   <p>
    As Full Administrator, to add <i>users</i> (each of which might be either an <i>administrator</i> or
    an <i>application</i>) to Couchbase Server,
    use the Couchbase Web Console.
    Access the <uicontrol>Dashboard</uicontrol>, and left-click on the <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> tab, on the
    vertical navigation-bar, at the left. This brings up the <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> view, as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/securityView.png" id="security_view" align="left" width="820"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> view allows users to be defined, and roles to be allocated to them. It also
    allows management of the <uicontrol>Root</uicontrol> and <uicontrol>Client</uicontrol> certificates; of 
    <uicontrol>Audit</uicontrol>-processing; of <uicontrol>Log Redaction</uicontrol>; and of <uicontrol>Session</uicontrol>
    timeouts.
    To add a user, left-click on the <uicontrol>Add User</uicontrol> control, at the upper right. The <uicontrol>Add New
    User</uicontrol> dialog now appears:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/manageUserNew.png" id="manage_user_new" align="left" width="380"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The <uicontrol>Authentication Domain</uicontrol> panel features two checkboxes: one specifying 
    <uicontrol>Couchbase</uicontrol>, the other <uicontrol>External</uicontrol>. By default,
    <uicontrol>Couchbase</uicontrol> is checked: this means that the user will be defined locally, and that
    a user-password must therefore be created, using the <uicontrol>Password</uicontrol> fields displayed on
    the dialog. To define a user externally (for example, by accessing an LDAP server over the network), 
    check the <uicontrol>External</uicontrol> checkbox. If you
    do so, no password need be specified, since one is assumed to have been defined elsewhere; and the
    <uicontrol>Password</uicontrol> fields therefore disappear from the dialog. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Define a Couchbase user, by adding appropriate entries into the <uicontrol>Username</uicontrol> 
    and <uicontrol>Password</uicontrol> fields. The
    <uicontrol>Full Name</uicontrol> field may be left blank.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    For more information on defining users locally and externally, see
    <xref href="./security-authentication.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Authentication</xref>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
   
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Adding Roles
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Roles can be specified by checking checkboxes in the
    <uicontrol>Roles</uicontrol> panel:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/addNewUserDialogRolesPanel.png" id="add_new_user_dialog_roles_panel" align="left" width="280"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Roles are arranged in groups. The
    first group, which appears at the top of the panel, is for <b>Administration &amp; Global Roles</b>: this 
    roles are either administrative, or involve access to cluster-wide features. Subsequent
    groups appear below the first: each consists of roles that are applied <i>per bucket</i>.
    By default, a single subsequent group is displayed, <b>All Buckets (*)</b>. Each individual bucket 
    on the cluster will be represented below <b>All Buckets (*)</b>, with its
    own hierarchy of roles. This allows each individual user to be assigned roles either that apply to all
    buckets defined on the cluster, or to individual buckets.
    Left-click on the corresponding right-pointing arrowhead to display a group's contents, scrolling down
    if necessary:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/allBucketsCheckboxes.png" id="all_buckets_checkboxes" align="left" width="280"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    To display roles at lower levels of the <b>All Buckets (*)</b> hierarchy, left-click on the right-pointing
    arrowheads.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    
   </p>
   
   <p>
    To assign roles to the user, simply check the appropriate checkboxes. Then, left-click on the <b>Add User</b>
    button, at the lower right.
   </p>

   <p>
    Note that some roles are considered to be <i>subsets</i> of others. In such cases, manually checking one checkbox
    may trigger the automated checking of others &#8212; indicating that the corresponding roles are also
    assigned to the user.
    To demonstrate this, left-click on the <uicontrol>Full Admin</uicontrol> checkbox, near the top. The <uicontrol>Roles</uicontrol>
    panel now appears as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/rolesPanelAdminChecked.png" id="roles_panel_admin_checked" align="left" width="280"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    As illustrated, selecting the <uicontrol>Full Admin</uicontrol> role causes all other roles
    also to become selected: this is because <uicontrol>Full Admin</uicontrol> stands at the top of the
    hierarchy, and is a superset of all other roles. 
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Saving and Making Changes
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Whenever you have finished allocating roles to a particular user, left-click on <uicontrol>Add User</uicontrol>. 
    The dialog disappears, and the <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> view
    now displays, on the row of the corresponding <uicontrol>username</uicontrol>, the roles you have allocated. For example, if you
    have allocated <uicontrol>Data Reader</uicontrol> and <uicontrol>Data Writer</uicontrol> on
    <uicontrol>travel-sample</uicontrol>, the view is as
    follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/securityViewWithNewUser.png" id="security_view_with_new_user" align="left" width="720"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Note that by left-clicking within the row, you display options for editing:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/securityViewWithEditOptions.png" id="security_view_with_edit_options" align="left" width="720"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    By left-clicking on <uicontrol>Delete</uicontrol>, you delete the user. By left-clicking on <uicontrol>Edit</uicontrol>,
    you bring up the <uicontrol>Edit testUser </uicontrol> dialog, with the options to redefine username, full name,
    and roles (the content of this dialog is very similar to that of the <uicontrol>Add New User</uicontrol> dialog, examined
    in detail above). The <uicontrol>Reset Password</uicontrol> button only appears when the selected user is <i>locally</i>
    defined. Left-clicking on the button brings up a dialog that allows redefinition of
    the user's password:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/resetPassword.png" id="reset_password" align="left" width="260"/> 
   </p>

   
   <p>
    For a complete account of the roles you can allocate and their significance, see 
    <xref href="./security-roles.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Roles</xref>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Role-Based Console Appearance
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Role-assignment determines which features of Couchbase Web Console are available to the administrator. Non-available
    features are not displayed:
    therefore, the console's appearance changes, based on which roles have been assigned to the current 
    user.
   </p>
   

  </section>
  
 </body>
 
</topic>
