<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="security-admin-access">
  <title>Secure Administrative Access</title>
  <shortdesc>Configure encrypted administrative access using SSL/TLS to
    enable HTTPS access for the Couchbase Web Console and the REST API.</shortdesc>
  <conbody>
    
    
    
    <p>Couchbase Server client libraries support client-side encryption using the SSL/TLS protocol
      by encrypting data in-flight between the client and the server. This encryption establishes a
      secure channel between the remote machine and the server.</p>
    
    
    
    <p>By default, Couchbase Server generates a self-signed certificate for the initial node, which
      is propagated throughout the server nodes in the cluster.</p> 
      
    
    <section> <title>Connecting to the Couchbase Web Console</title>
      <p>While an administrative console is typically protected via an HTTPS connection, the new
        administrative access on port <codeph>18091</codeph> allows connection to the Couchbase Web
        Console over SSL/TLS, which is enabled by default. </p>
      <p>To talk over SSL/TLS to the Couchbase Web Console, connect to the following URL with your
        web browser: <userinput>https://couchbase_server:18091</userinput></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Verifying the cluster's certificate</title>
      <p>To verify which certificate your cluster is currently using: </p>
      <ol>
        <li>Select <menucascade>
            <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol>
            <uicontrol>Root Certificate</uicontrol>
          </menucascade>. <p><image href="pict/self-signed-cert.png"
              id="image_tps_ftv_4v" align="left" width="720"/></p>
        </li>
        <li>The <wintitle>Root Certificate</wintitle> link shows that a self-signed certificate has
          been deployed across the cluster. This certificate can be regenerated or replaced using
            <xref href="../rest-api/rest-x509.dita#reference_ytt_hdx_hv">REST</xref> or <xref
            href="../cli/cbcli/ssl-manage.dita#cbcli-xdcr-ssl">CLI </xref> commands for managing
          certificates.</li>
      </ol>
    </section> 
    
    <section><title>Viewing the SSL Certificate Used in the Web Browser</title>    
      <ol>
        <li>Connect to Couchbase Server through an encrypted port to communicate on a secure channel
            (<codeph>18091</codeph> for REST HTTP or <codeph>18092</codeph> for  CAPI HTTP). </li>
        <li>Log in with the Full Administrator's name and password. </li>
          <li>Once you are logged in, the URL shows a secure
          connection. 
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>The following section shows an example URL of a secure connection using the Safari web browser.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Disabling the Couchbase Web Console on Port 8091</title>
      <p>If you would like to force Administrators to log in to the UI over an encrypted channel, 
        you can disable the UI over the 8091 HTTP port, 
        so that administrators can only access the administrative web console over port 18091. </p> 
      <note type="remember">This setting does not disable port 8091 completely since port 8091 is an 
        important Couchbase port that also handles REST requests in addition to the administrative web console.</note> 
      <p>To disable the Couchbase Web Console over port 8091:
        <codeblock>curl -X POST -u Administrator:password http://127.0.0.1:8091/diag/eval \
-d 'ns_config:set(disable_ui_over_http, true)’</codeblock></p>  
      <p>To re-enable the Couchbase Web Console over port 8091:
        <codeblock>curl -X POST -u Administrator:password http://127.0.0.1:8091/diag/eval \
-d 'ns_config:set(disable_ui_over_http, false)’</codeblock></p>    
    </section>
    
    
   
</conbody>
</concept>
