<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_cfk_mhn_xv">
  <title>X.509 for TLS</title> <shortdesc>Couchbase Server uses X.509 certificates to encrypt client-server communications and
    XDCR (Cross Data Center Replication).</shortdesc>
  <body>
  
      <p>Couchbase Server 4.5 Enterprise Edition supports X.509 certificates for Transport Layer
        Security (TLS).</p>
      <p>With X.509 certificates, Couchbase Server can strongly encrypt client-server communications
        and <xref href="http://developer.couchbase.com/documentation/server/4.1/xdcr/xdcr-intro.html"
          format="html" scope="external">XDCR</xref> (Cross Data Center Replication).</p>

    <p><note type="note">Full administrators in Couchbase can manage certificates using the Couchbase CLI
        tools (as described in <xref href="../cli/cbcli/ssl-manage.dita#cbcli-xdcr-ssl"/>) or REST
        API (as described in <xref href="../rest-api/rest-security.dita#reference_ytt_hdx_hv"
        />).</note></p>




      <p><image href="pict/ca_sys_diagram.png" id="image_gnp_5mk_y5" width="570"/></p>
      <p>With CA-based certificates, you also achieve their simplified management and rotation
      without client downtime. </p>




      <note type="note">Your prior knowledge of TLS/SSL, PKI certificates including X.509
        certificates, and Certificate Authorities (CAs) is assumed for this overview. </note>
      
      <p><b>When to use X.509 Certificates</b></p>
      <p>An X.509 certificate does more than just
        distribute the public key: it is signed by a trusted (internal or third-party) CA and
        verifies the identity of the server so that clients know their information is not being sent
        to a rogue
        server.</p>
      <p>Some common scenarios which may require use of X.509 certificates are:</p>
      <ul id="ul_j3z_b1k_1v">
        <li>In production where clients have to go through the internet.</li>
        <li>When transferring sensitive data on the wire between application and Couchbase Server,
          or between data centers (XDCR).</li>
        <li>When mandated by regulatory compliance regulations.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>CA Hierarchies Supported by Couchbase</b></p>
      <p>Couchbase customers can tie Couchbase Server with their CA hierarchies. The CA at the top
        of a hierarchy is called the root authority, or root CA. There are two types of CA
        hierarchies supported by Couchbase: single- or n-tier. </p>
      
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Single-Tier Hierarchy</dt>
          <dd>In its simplest form, the single-tier hierarchy starts with a root CA. <p><image
            href="pict/ca_single_tier.png" id="image_my1_wmk_y5" align="left"/></p><p>For
              example, as shown in the figure above, the root CA is also the issuing CA. All
              certificates immediately below the root certificate inherit its trustworthiness and
              can be used to secure systems. </p><p>Although this is the simplest form of CA
                hierarchy, most enterprises use an N-tier CA hierarchy as described next.</p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>N-Tier Hierarchy</dt>
          <dd>Typically, in many production deployments, a hierarchy will have multiple
            CAs.<p><image href="pict/ca_n_tier.png" id="image_t1g_ymk_y5" align="left" width="570"/>
            </p></dd>
          <dd>In a multi-tier hierarchy, the root CA issues certificates to the intermediate CAs, which
            in turn generate intermediate certificates used to sign the client
            certificates such as a cluster certificate:<ul>
              <li>Trusted root CA > Intermediate CA > Cluster certificate</li>
              <li>Trusted root CA > Intermediate CA 1 > Intermediate CA 2.... >
                Intermediate CA N > Cluster certificate </li>
            </ul><p>When you need to regenerate the intermediate certificate, ensure
              that the chain can be verified up to the root CA. </p><p>If all
                intermediate certificates are not installed on your server, some clients
                might think you are on an insecure connection. This results in
                'untrusted' warnings like the following:</p><p><image
                  href="pict/back-to-safety.png" id="image_ofr_hg1_z5" align="left"
                  width="450"/>
                </p><p>To avoid such warnings, a server should always send a complete trust
                  chain. The trust chain contains your certificate concatenated with all
                  intermediate certificates.</p>
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    
   <section id="configuring-x.509">
  <title>Configuring X.509</title> 
  
    <p>This section explains how to configure X.509 certificates for TLS in Couchbase Server.</p>
    <note type="note">Choosing a root CA, the CA hierarchy, and obtaining a certificate from that CA
      chain to set up a Couchbase cluster are not within the scope of this document.</note>
   
   <sectiondiv id="x509-bestpractices">
     <p><b>X.509 Certificate Requirements and Best Practices</b></p>
      <p>Here are the basic requirements for using your X.509 certificates in Couchbase: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>The certificate must be in available in the <codeph>.pem</codeph> format.</li>
        <li>The certificate must be an RSA key certificate.</li>
        <li>The current system time must fall between the times set in the certificate's properties
            <codeph>valid from</codeph> and <codeph>valid to</codeph>. </li>
        <li>Common name: This can be a certificate with a <codeph>nodename</codeph> (preferable), IP
          address, URI (<codeph>www.example.com</codeph>), or URI with a subject alternative name
          (SAN) certificate (<codeph>example.com</codeph> and <codeph>example.net</codeph>).</li>
        <li>The node certificate must be designated for server authentication set in the optional
          field of the certificate's property <codeph>enhanced key usage</codeph> as <codeph>Server
            Authentication</codeph>. </li></ul>
      
      <p>Here are a few best practices around X.509 certificates in Couchbase that you should
        consider using:</p>
          
          <ul>
            <li>To avoid man-in-the-middle attacks do not use wildcards with IP addresses in the
          certificate common name.</li>
            <li>We recommended at least RSA key-length of 2048 bits or higher. As computing
          capabilities increase, longer RSA keys provide increased security.</li>
          </ul>

      <p>The certificate chain must be valid from the node certificate up to the root certificate,
        which can be verified using the <xref
          href="https://www.openssl.org/docs/manmaster/man1/verify.html" format="html"
          scope="external">OpenSSL validate certificate test</xref>. </p></sectiondiv>
   <sectiondiv id="validate-server-identity">
    <p><b>Validating Server Identity</b></p> 
      <p>The HTTPS specification mandates that HTTPS clients must be capable of verifying the
        identity of the server. This requirement can potentially affect how you generate your X.509
        certificates. The HTTPS specification defines a generic mechanism for verifying the server
        identity, known as the HTTPS URL integrity check, which is the standard mechanism used by
        Web browsers. </p>
      <sectiondiv><b>HTTPS URL integrity check</b>
        <p>The basic idea of the URL integrity check is that the server certificate's identity must
          match the server hostname. This integrity check has an important impact on how you
          generate X.509 certificates for HTTPS: the certificate identity (usually the certificate
          subject DN’s common name) must match the name of the host on which Couchbase Server is
          deployed. </p><p>The URL integrity check is designed to prevent man-in-the-middle attacks.
          </p><p>Specify the certificate identity for the URL integrity check in one of the
          following ways: </p><dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>Using the <codeph>commonName</codeph></dt>
            <dd>The usual way to specify the certificate identity (for the purpose of the URL
              integrity check) is through the Common Name (CN) in the subject DN of the certificate.
            </dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl><dl>
          <dlentry>
            <dt>Using the <codeph>subjectAltName</codeph></dt>
            <dd>If you deploy a certificate on a multi-homed host, however, you might find it is
              practical to allow the certificate to be used with any of the multi-homed host names.
              In this case, it is necessary to define a certificate with multiple, alternative
              identities, and this is only possible using the <codeph>subjectAltName</codeph>
              certificate extension. </dd>
          </dlentry>
        </dl><p>The HTTPS protocol also supports in host names the wildcard character *. For
          example, you can define the <codeph>subjectAltName</codeph> as follows:
          <codeblock>subjectAltName=DNS:*.couchbase.com </codeblock></p><p>This certificate identity
          matches any three-component host name in the domain <codeph>couchbase.com</codeph>.
          </p><note type="note">As a best practice, try to avoid using the wildcard character in the
          domain name. Be sure never to do this accidentally by forgetting to type the dot (.)
          delimiter in front of the domain name.  For example, if you specified *couchbase.com, your
          certificate could be used in any domain that ends with the string
            <codeph>couchbase</codeph>. </note></sectiondiv></sectiondiv>
    <sectiondiv id="cluster-certificate">
    <p><b>Couchbase Cluster Certificate</b></p>
      <p>The Couchbase cluster certificate is the root CA's public key <codeph>ca.pem</codeph>. In
        the configuration steps shown in the following sections, <codeph>ca.pem</codeph> is the CA
        public key that should be configured in Couchbase as the cluster certificate.</p>
      <p>When you load the cluster certificate into Couchbase, it is first checked to make sure it
        is a valid X.509 certificate. Next, if the per-node certificates are not signed by the
        cluster certificate, a warning is shown for each node during configuration. As the per-node
        certificates are updated, such that they are signed by the cluster certificate, the warning
        for each node goes away.</p></sectiondiv>
    <sectiondiv id="pernode-certificate">
     <p><b>Per Node Certificate</b></p>
      <p>The Couchbase cluster certificate is used to sign per-node Couchbase certificates, each
        containing the following:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The node private key, which is named <codeph>pkey.key</codeph> as shown in the
          configuration steps below.</li>
        <li>The node public key certificate file, which is named <codeph>pkey.pem</codeph> as shown
          in the configuration steps below.</li>
        <li>The certificate chain file based on the supported CA hierarchy, This file is named
            <codeph>chain.pem</codeph> as shown in the configuration steps below.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_r1q_1zz_pv">
          <title>Private and public keys you need to have</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.43*"/>
            <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="3.34*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry/>
                <entry>Key name</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry morerows="4">Server-side files</entry>
                <entry><codeph>ca.pem</codeph></entry>
                <entry>Root CA public key or the cluster certificate.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><codeph>int.pem</codeph></entry>
                <entry>Intermediate public key. There can be one or more intermediate public keys in
                  the hierarchy.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><codeph>pkey.key</codeph></entry>
                <entry>Node private key per node (private key of the node). Each node in the cluster
                  must have its private key.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><codeph>pkey.pem</codeph></entry>
                <entry>Node public key (public key of the node). Each node in the cluster must have
                  its public key.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><codeph>chain.pem</codeph></entry>
                <entry>Concatenated chain file (chain file). This file contains the node public key
                  and the intermediate public keys that signed first the node key (pkey.pem) and
                  then each other. <p>This file does not contain the CA public key. </p></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry morerows="1">Client-side files</entry>
                <entry><codeph>ca.pem </codeph></entry>
                <entry>CA public key, which should be configured on the client</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><codeph>chain.pem</codeph></entry>
                <entry>Concatenated chain file (chain file)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </p>
    </sectiondiv>
     <sectiondiv id="prepare-configuration">
   <p><b>Prepare for Configuration</b></p>
      <note type="note">If your CA authority supports automatic generation of certificates, you can
        skip the X.509 configuration steps.</note>
      <p>Before you start configuring X.509 certificates for your nodes, assess your needs. </p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Where will you put the configured CA, intermediate, and node keys?</dt>
          <dd>All the keys and certificates are generated in a directory named SSLCA, which can be
            located anywhere on your machine. </dd>
          <dd>The generated private node key (<codeph>pkey.key</codeph>) and chain certificate
              (<codeph>chain.pem</codeph>) must be posted in a specific place that is in the
            certificate trust path (such as <filepath>/Users/&lt;username&gt;/Library/Application\
              Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/inbox/</filepath> on MacOSX). </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Do you have one or more nodes in the cluster?</dt>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>With one node, you will generate one node directory inside the directory SSLCA
                that will contain the private node key (<codeph>pkey.key</codeph>) and the
                certificate chain file (<codeph>chain.pem</codeph>). The node public key
                  (<codeph>pkey.pem</codeph>) is included in the chain file.</li>
              <li>With multiple nodes, you need to add an appropriate number of node directories
                with distinctive names, such as <codeph>node-sales</codeph>,
                  <codeph>node-hr,</codeph> or whatever your situation requires.</li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Do you have one or more intermediate CAs in your trust path?</dt>
          <dd>With only one CA, create one directory named <codeph>int</codeph>. If you have
            multiple intermediate CAs, be sure to name them in a way that will allow you to stack
            them properly in the chain file, such as <codeph>int1</codeph>, <codeph>int2</codeph>,
            and so on. </dd>
          <dd>This order will show that the intermediate CA closest to the node (which signed the
            node certificate) has the higher number, or in the sample below
              <codeph>int2</codeph>.<p>For example: </p><p><image href="pict/chain-pem.png"
                id="image_e5g_bcn_sv" align="left" width="500"/>
            </p></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
     </sectiondiv></section>
     
    <section id="sslconfig">
      <title>Configure X.509 Certificates using openSSL</title>
      <p>Here are the steps to help you generate X.509 certificates:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Create a top-level directory called SSLCA in your user folder and three types of
          sub-directories: <ul>
            <li>One subdirectory called <codeph>root</codeph></li>
            <li>One or more <codeph>int</codeph> subdirectories</li>
            <li>One or more <codeph>node</codeph> subdirectories</li>
          </ul></li>
        <li>Generate the root private key file (<codeph>ca.key</codeph>), and CA public key file
            (<codeph>ca.pem</codeph>).<p>Enter the following command inside the
              <codeph>root</codeph>
          subdirectory:</p><codeblock>openssl genrsa -out <b>ca.key</b> 2048</codeblock><codeblock>Generating RSA private key, 2048 bit long modulus
............................................................................................+++
....+++ 
e is 65537 (0x10001)</codeblock><codeblock>openssl req -new -x509  -days 3650 -sha256 -key <b>ca.key</b> -out <b>ca.pem</b> \
-subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=My Company Root CA' </codeblock></li>
        <li>Generate the intermediate private key file (<codeph>int.key)</codeph> and the
          intermediate certificate signing request (<codeph>int.csr</codeph>) to generate the
          intermediate public key file (<codeph>int.pem</codeph>). <p>Enter the following command
            inside the <codeph>int</codeph> subdirectory:
            <codeblock>openssl genrsa -out <b>int.key</b> 2048</codeblock><codeblock>Generating RSA private key, 2048 bit long modulus
..........................................+++ 
.....+++ 
e is 65537 (0x10001 </codeblock><codeblock>openssl req -new -key <b>int.key</b> -out <b>int.csr</b> -subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=My Company Intermediate CA' </codeblock></p></li>
        <li>Create the extension file (<codeph>v3_ca.ext)</codeph> to add extensions to the
          certificate and to generate the certificate signing request.<p>In the <codeph>int</codeph>
            subdirectory enter:</p><codeblock>cat &lt;&lt;EOF &gt;&gt; v3_ca.ext </codeblock><p>Then
            add the following:
            <codeblock>subjectKeyIdentifier = hash
authorityKeyIdentifier = keyid:always,issuer:always
basicConstraints = CA:true
EOF</codeblock></p><p>Your
              <codeph>int</codeph> directory now contains three files: <codeph>int.csr</codeph>,  <codeph>int.key</codeph>, and 
              <codeph>v3_ca.ext</codeph>.
          </p></li>
        <li>Generate the intermediate public key file (<codeph>int.pem)</codeph> based on the
          intermediate certificate signing request (<codeph>int.csr</codeph>), and signed by the
          root public key (<codeph>ca.pem</codeph>):<p>
            <ol>
              <li>In the <codeph>int</codeph> subdirectory
                  enter:<codeblock>openssl x509 -req -in <b>int.csr</b> -CA ../root/<b>ca.pem</b> -CAkey ../root/<b>ca.key</b> -CAcreateserial \
-CAserial rootCA.srl -extfile v3_ca.ext -out <b>int.pem</b> -days 365</codeblock><p>The
                  response will be similar to the
                following:</p><codeblock>Signature ok        
subject=/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=My Company Intermediate CA       
Getting CA Private Key</codeblock></li>
              <li>Verify that <codeph>openssl</codeph> has correctly signed the intermediate
                certificate with the root certificate:<p>
                  <codeblock>openssl verify -CAfile ../root/<b>ca.pem</b> <b>int.pem</b> </codeblock>
                </p><p>The response will
                  be:<codeblock>int.pem: OK
openssl x509 -in int.pem -text</codeblock></p></li>
            </ol>
          </p></li>
        <li>Generate the node private key file (<codeph>pkey.key</codeph>) and the node certificate
          signing request (<codeph>pkey.csr</codeph>) to generate the node public key file
            (<codeph>pkey.pem</codeph>). <p>Be sure to enter another node and use the appropriate
            node name instead of the variable <b>&lt;node-name&gt;</b>, such as "sales" or "HR’.
            Each time you use another name, another set of files will be generated.</p><ol>
            <li>Inside the node subdirectory (repeated for each node in the cluster):
                <codeblock>openssl genrsa -out <b>pkey.key</b> 2048
openssl req -new -key <b>pkey.key</b> -out <b>pkey.csr</b> -subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=<b>&lt;node-name></b>'
openssl x509 -req -in <b>pkey.csr</b> -CA ../int/<b>int.pem</b> -CAkey ../int/<b>int.key</b> -CAcreateserial \
-CAserial intermediateCA.srl -out <b>pkey.pem</b> -days 365  </codeblock><p>For
                example, for the <codeph>node-sales</codeph>
                directory:<codeblock>openssl genrsa -out <b>pkey.key</b> 2048
openssl req -new -key <b>pkey.key</b> -out <b>pkey.csr</b> -subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=<b>sales</b>'
openssl x509 -req -in <b>pkey.csr</b> -CA ../int/<b>int.pem</b> -CAkey ../int/<b>int.key</b> -CAcreateserial \
-CAserial intermediateCA.srl -out <b>pkey.pem</b> -days 365 </codeblock></p><p>The
                response for the <codeph>node-sales</codeph> directory should be as follows:
                <codeblock>johns-MacBook-Pro-4:node-sales john$ openssl genrsa -out pkey.key 2048
Generating RSA private key, 2048 bit long modulus
....................................................................+++
.............+++
e is 65537 (0x10001)
johns-MacBook-Pro-4:<b>node-sales</b> john$ openssl req -new -key pkey.key -out pkey.csr -subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=<b>sales</b>'
johns-MacBook-Pro-4:<b>node-sales</b> john$ openssl x509 -req -in pkey.csr -CA ../int/int.pem -CAkey ../int/int.key -CAcreateserial \
> -CAserial intermediateCA.srl -out pkey.pem -days 365
Signature ok
subject=/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=<b>sales</b>
Getting CA Private Key   </codeblock></p></li>
            <li>Repeat the same step in each node directory you have. Each time another set of node
              keys will be generated.
              <codeblock>johns-MacBook-Pro-4:node-hr john$ ls
intermediateCA.srl	pkey.csr		pkey.key		pkey.pem                 </codeblock></li>
          </ol></li>
        <li>Verify the node-intermediate-root chain. <ol>
            <li>Try to specify the node certificate <codeph>pkey.pem</codeph>:
                <codeblock>openssl verify -verbose <b>pkey.pem</b>  </codeblock><p>The response
                should be similar to the
                following:<codeblock>johns-MacBook-Pro-4:node-sales john$ openssl verify -verbose pkey.pem
pkey.pem: /C=UA/O=My Company/CN=sales
error 20 at 0 depth lookup:unable to get local issuer certificate </codeblock></p><p>This
                means that the certificate at <codeph>depth=0</codeph> (intermediate certificate)
                cannot be looked up. </p></li>
            <li>Next, let’s try to specify an intermediate certificate:
                <codeblock>openssl verify -untrusted ../int/<b>int.pem</b> <b>pkey.pem</b>  </codeblock><p>The
                response should be similar to the following:
                <codeblock>pkey.pem: /C=UA/O=My Company/CN=My Company Intermediate CA                   
error 20 at 1 depth lookup:unable to get local issuer certificate</codeblock></p><p>This
                means that the certificate at <codeph>depth=1</codeph> (root certificate) cannot be
                looked up. </p></li>
            <li>Next, let’s try to specify the root certificate:
                <codeblock>openssl verify -untrusted ../int/<b>int.pem</b> -CAfile ../root/<b>ca.pem</b> <b>pkey.pem</b></codeblock><p>The
                response will be: <codeblock>pkey.pem: OK  </codeblock></p><p>This means that
                certificate validation has passed.</p></li>
          </ol></li>
        <li>Generate a certificate chain file.<p>When a client application tries to verify a
            certificate signed by the intermediate CA, it must also verify the intermediate
            certificate against the root certificate. To complete the chain of trust, create a
            certificate chain to present it to the application.</p>In a chain file, the lowest
          certificate goes first, then the intermediate certificates in proper order.<note
            type="important">Do not include in your chain file the root CA’s public key certificate
            and intermediate certificates that are not in the trust path.</note><note type="note"
            >The root certificate is not included in this chain. </note><p>To create the certificate
            chain file, concatenate the intermediate and root certificates together, beginning with
            the lowest one in the chain.<ul>
              <li>If you have only one intermediate CA in your trust path, use this command:
                <codeblock>cat <b>pkey.pem</b> ../int/int.pem > <b>chain.pem</b></codeblock></li>
              <li>If you have more intermediate CAs in your trust path, keep in mind that the order
                of certificates in an SSL Certificate Chain file is important: <ul>
                  <li><codeph>pkey.pem</codeph> certificate is signed by intermediate
                      (<codeph>int3.pem</codeph>) certificate</li>
                  <li><codeph>int3.pem </codeph>is signed by intermediate
                    (<codeph>int2.pem</codeph>) </li>
                  <li><codeph>int2.pem </codeph>is signed by intermediate
                    (<codeph>int1.pem</codeph>) </li>
                </ul><p>For multiple intermediate CAs, use this command:
                </p><codeblock>cat <b>pkey.pem</b> ../int3/int.pem ../int2/int.pem ../int1/int.pem  > <b>chain.pem</b></codeblock></li>
            </ul></p></li>
        <li>Copy the node private key (<codeph>pkey.key)</codeph> and the chain file
            (<codeph>chain.pem</codeph>) manually to the <codeph>inbox</codeph> folder on each node. <p>
            <ol>
              <li>Create an <codeph>inbox</codeph> folder in the Couchbase server path:
                  <codeblock>mkdir /Users/&lt;username&gt;/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/<b>inbox</b>  </codeblock><p>For
                  example:
                  <codeblock>mkdir /Users/john/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/<b>inbox</b> </codeblock></p></li>
              <li>Now go to the directory <filepath>SSLCA/node</filepath> and copy the files
                  <codeph>chain.pem</codeph> and <codeph>pkey.key</codeph> into the created
                  <codeph>inbox</codeph> folder:
                  <codeblock>cp chain.pem /Users/<b>&lt;username&gt;</b>/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/inbox/chain.pem
cp pkey.key /Users/<b>&lt;username&gt;</b>/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/inbox/pkey.pem </codeblock><p>For
                  example:
                  <codeblock>cp <b>chain.pem</b> /Users/<b>john</b>/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/inbox/<b>chain.pem</b>
cp <b>pkey.key</b> /Users/<b>john</b>/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/inbox/<b>pkey.key</b></codeblock></p><p>Check
                  if the the files <codeph>chain.pem</codeph> and <codeph>pkey.key</codeph> have
                  been posted to the inbox:</p><p>
                  <codeblock>johns-MacBook-Pro-4:inbox john$ ls
chain.pem	pkey.key </codeblock>
                </p></li>
            </ol>
          </p></li>
        <li>Change permissions so that Couchbase can read <codeph>pkey.key</codeph> and
            <codeph>chain.pem:</codeph>
          <p>
            <codeblock>cd /Users/<b>&lt;username&gt;</b>/Library/Application\ Support/Couchbase/var/lib/couchbase/inbox/
chmod 777 chain.pem
chmod 777 pkey.pem </codeblock>
          </p></li>
        <li>Set up the cluster certificate and then a node certificate on each of the nodes.</li></ol></section>
    <section><title>Setting up a Cluster CA Certificate</title>
          
          <dl>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>Using CLI</dt>
              <dd>
                <codeblock>couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c <b>&lt;node-name></b>:8091 -u<b>[admin]</b> -p<b>[password]</b> \
    --upload-cluster-ca=<b>&lt;path to pem-encoded root certificate></b></codeblock>
                <p>For example:
                  <codeblock>couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c <b>MyNode</b>:8091 -u <b>Administrator</b> -p <b>password</b> \
    --upload-cluster-ca=<b>./root/ca.pem </b> </codeblock></p>
              </dd>
            </dlentry>
          </dl>
          <dl>
            <dlentry>
              <dt>Using REST API</dt>
              <dd>
                <codeblock>cd ../root
    curl -X POST --data-binary "@./ca.pem" \
    http://<b>Administrator</b>:<b>password</b>@127.0.0.1:8091/controller/uploadClusterCA</codeblock>
              </dd>
            </dlentry>
          </dl>
       
  
    <sectiondiv>
     <p><b>Setting up a Per Node CA Certificate</b></p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Using CLI</dt>
          <dd>
            <codeblock>couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c <b>&lt;node-name></b>:8091 -u[admin] -p[password] --set-node-certificate</codeblock>
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl> <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Using REST API</dt>
          <dd>
            <codeblock>curl -X POST http://Administrator:password@<b>&lt;node-name></b>:8091/node/controller/reloadCertificate</codeblock>
          </dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
     
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>See also:</dt>
          <dd>CLI: <xref href="../cli/cbcli/ssl-manage.dita#cbcli-xdcr-ssl"/></dd>
          <dd>REST API: <xref href="../rest-api/rest-uploads-ca.dita#reference_jm5_j2x_hv"/></dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl></sectiondiv>
    </section>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    <section id="rotate-x509">
      <title>Rotating X.509</title>
      
       
          <p>Certificate rotation is needed when a certificate expires, if you are considering moving from an old CA authority to a new CA authority, 
            there is a change in the policy of the certificates issued by the CA, 
            or in the case of a widespread breach of security occurs in the system.</p>
          <p>You need to have a plan in place to renew the CA well before it expires. 
            X.509 certificate rotation in Couchbase is an online operation and does not require a node or cluster restart. 
            You can be reassured that the application will have continued access to Couchbase without getting hit 
            with a downtime during the rotation operation.</p>
          
          
       
      <sectiondiv><p><b>How to Rotate an X.509 Certificate in Couchbase</b></p>
          
          
          <ol>
            <li><b>Generate a new certificate.</b>
              <p>Before you rotate a certificate, you need to generate a new certificate.
              </p><p>Typically, your Certificate Authority (CA) will give you a self-service option to
                re-issue certificates. If this is not the case, you can manually regenerate your new
                X509 certificate.</p><ol>
                  <li>Renew the root CA certificate<p>The root certificate authority (CA) is the topmost
                    CA in a CA hierarchy. Its validity period is typically longer, between 10 and 20
                    years. </p><note type="note">When you renew the root CA, you have the option of
                      reusing its existing private key. If you keep the same private key on your root CA,
                      all certificates can continue to validate successfully against the new root; all
                      that's required of you is to trust the new root. </note></li>
                  <li>Generate the root CA for the first time
                    <codeblock>openssl genrsa -out <b>ca.key</b> 2048
                      openssl req -new -x509  -days 3650 -sha256 -key <b>ca.key</b> -out <b>ca.pem</b> \
                      -subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=My Company Root CA'</codeblock></li>
                  <li>After ten years, the renewal time for the root CA comes up! <ul>
                    <li>Renew the root CA using the existing <codeph>ca.key</codeph>:
                      <codeblock>openssl req -new -key <b>ca.key</b> -out <b>newcsr.csr</b> 
                        openssl x509 -req -days 3650 -sha256 -in <b>newcsr.csr</b> -signkey <b>newca.key</b> -out <b>newca.pem</b></codeblock></li>
                    <li>Generate a completely new root CA similar to what you did the first time:
                      <codeblock>openssl genrsa -out <b>newca.key</b> 2048
                        openssl req -new -x509  -days 3650 -sha256 -key <b>newca.key</b> -out <b>newca.pem</b> \
                        -subj '/C=UA/O=My Company/CN=My Company Root CA' </codeblock></li>
                  </ul></li>
                  <li>Renew the intermediate certificates.<p>For the intermediate CAs, a possible strategy
                    might be to renew them for a year to six months before they expire and reuse the
                    existing key. </p><p>By replacing the old chain file with the new chain file (that
                      contains the updated intermediate certificate), rotation of the intermediate
                      certificate can be performed:
                      <codeblock>> cat <b>pkey.pem</b> ../int/<b>newint.pem</b> &lt;possibly other intermediate CAs&gt; > <b>chain.pem</b> </codeblock></p></li>
                </ol></li>
            <li><b>Deploy the CA public key and intermediate certificates</b>
              <p>Before modifying anything on the server-side, deploy the CA public key and intermediate
                certificates in the certificate stores used by your client browser and the SDK
                language.</p><p>For example, here are steps to do that for <xref
                  href="http://www.cyberciti.biz/faq/firefox-adding-trusted-ca/" format="html"
                  scope="external">Firefox</xref> and <xref
                    href="http://blogmines.com/blog/how-to-import-a-certificate-in-google-chrome/"
                    format="html" scope="external">Chrome</xref>.</p></li>
            <li><b>Rotate certificates on the server</b>
              
              
              <ol>
                <li>Configure the new root CA certificate (<codeph>newca.pem</codeph> is the new root CA certificate). 
                  <ul>
                    <li>Using CLI:
                      <codeblock>couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c &lt;node-name>:8091 -u Administrator -p password \
                        --upload-cluster-ca=<b>newca.pem</b>  </codeblock></li>
                    <li>Using REST:
                      <codeblock>curl -X POST --data-binary "@newca.pem" \
                        http://Administrator:password@127.0.0.1:8091/controller/uploadClusterCA</codeblock></li>
                  </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Configure the new intermediate and node certificate. <p>For each node, copy over new
                  <codeph>chain.pem</codeph> file, and per node private key (new
                  <codeph>pkey.pem</codeph> file, if the node certificate is rotated) to the
                  <codeph>inbox</codeph> folder.</p><ul>
                    <li>Using CLI:
                      <codeblock>couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c &lt;node-name>:8091 -u Administrator -p password \
                        --set-node-certificate     </codeblock></li>
                    <li>Using REST:
                      <codeblock>curl -X POST http://Administrator:password@[node-name]:8091/node/controller/reloadCertificate </codeblock></li>
                  </ul></li>
                
              </ol>
            </li>  
            <li><b>Test the server CA certificate</b>
              <p>You can also use OpenSSL's <codeph>s_client</codeph> by trying to connect to a server
                that you know is using a certificate signed by the CA that you just installed:
                <codeblock>> openssl s_client -connect https://&lt;hostname&gt;:8091 -CApath &lt;root ca public key&gt; </codeblock></p></li>
            <li><b>Troubleshoot X.509 certificates</b>
              <p>During the development process these external tools might come in handy for verifying
                and debugging SSL traffic: <ul>
                  <li><cmdname>openssl</cmdname>: OpenSSL command line tool</li>
                  <li>wireshark: Network traffic analyzer</li>
                  <li>nmap: Sophisticated security scanner </li>
                </ul></p></li>
            <li><b>Revert from the X.509 to the self-signed certificate</b>
              <p>If you configured Couchbase to use X.509 certificates, and you want to go back to the
                self-signed certificates, you can do this by regenerating the self-signed cluster
                certificate using CLI or REST.  </p><note type="warning">Moving from CA certificates to
                  self-signed certificates will cause application downtime because you need to reconfigure
                  the self-signed cluster certificate on the client machines after self-signed certificate
                  regeneration.</note><ul>
                    <li>Using CLI:
                      <codeblock>couchbase-cli ssl-manage -c &lt;hostname&gt;:8091 -u Administrator -p password \
                        --regenerate-cert=/tmp/test.pem            </codeblock></li>
                    <li>Using REST:
                      <codeblock>curl -X POST  http://Administrator:password@remoteHost:8091/controller/regenerateCertificate</codeblock></li>
                  </ul>
            </li>
            
          </ol></sectiondiv>
        </section>
      
      
 
    <section id="trbl-x509">
      <title>Troubleshooting X.509</title>
      
   <p>This section lists the error messages connected to the configuration of cluster and node
        certificates in Couchbase.</p>
  <sectiondiv>
    <p><b>Cluster CA Certificates</b></p>
          
          
          <p>Here are some error messages you might encounter when configuring the cluster CA
          certificate and the suggested corrective actions:</p>
          <p>
            <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_fsj_r3d_5v">
              <title>Error messages when configuring cluster CA certificates</title>
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Couchbase Error Message</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                    <entry>Suggested User Action</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Certificate should not be empty</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>This error message can occur if the request body of the certificate is
                      empty.</entry>
                    <entry>Open the certificate file, and verify whether it is empty or not. The
                      certificate file should be readable using openssl or via online SSL tools such as
                      <xref href="https://www.sslchecker.com/certdecoder" format="html"
                        scope="external">sslcheker </xref>. </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Certificate is not valid at this time</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>This error message can occur if the certificate has expired, or is not yet
                      valid.</entry>
                    <entry>Verify whether the certificate validity dates (begins on, and expires on) are
                      currently valid corresponding to the server clock time.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Malformed certificate</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>This error message can occur due to many reasons - an extra space in the
                      certificate digest body, incorrect certificate format, and so on. </entry>
                    <entry>Use a properly configured certificate, and make sure it’s readable using
                      <codeph>openssl</codeph>. It should look as follows: Certificate begins with
                      <p><codeph>-----BEGIN CERTIFICATE-----</codeph></p><p>and ends with</p><p><codeph>
                        -----END CERTIFICATE-----</codeph></p><p>on a new line with no spaces before or after.</p></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Only one certificate per request is allowed</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>Appears when the file contains more than one key or certificate.</entry>
                    <entry>Open the <codeph>.pem</codeph> file, and make sure that it has only a single
                      certificate digest (such as single <codeph>BEGIN CERTIFICATE,</codeph>
                      <codeph>END CERTIFICATE</codeph> pragmas).</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Encrypted certificates are not supported </codeph></entry>
                    <entry>This error message can occur if you are trying to load a certificate that is
                      encrypted. Verify by opening the certificate file. If you see something like shown
                      below, you will know your certificate is encrypted.: <p><codeph>-----BEGIN RSA
                        PRIVATE KEY-----</codeph></p></entry>
                    <entry>Couchbase does not support encrypted certificates. Decrypt the certificate
                      with <codeph>openssl</codeph> before loading the certificate in Couchbase.
                      <codeblock>openssl rsa -in privateKey.pem -out newPrivateKey.pem </codeblock></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Invalid certificate type: ~s </codeph></entry>
                    <entry>Appears when a header other than <codeph>BEGIN CERTIFICATE</codeph> has been
                      found.</entry>
                    <entry>Open the certificate file, and verify whether it is a valid certificate. The
                      certificate file should be readable using <codeph>openssl</codeph> or via online
                      SSL tools such as <xref href="https://www.sslchecker.com/certdecoder"
                        format="html" scope="external">sslchecker</xref>.</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </p>
  </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
<p><b>Node Certificates</b></p>
          
          <p>Here are some error messages you might encounter when configuring the node certificate
          and the suggested corrective actions:</p>
          <p>
            <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_u3d_bkd_5v">
              <title>Error messages when configuring node certificates</title>
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Couchbase Error Message</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                    <entry>Suggested User Action</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Cluster CA needs to be set before setting node
                      certificate</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>This error can occur when your cluster is still using the self-generated
                      certificate, and you are attempting to configure a node certificate.</entry>
                    <entry>Set up the cluster CA certificate before configuring the per node
                      certificate.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Incorrectly configured certificate chain. &lt;Error></codeph></entry>
                    <entry>Denotes an invalid certificate in the chain file when configuring Couchbase. </entry>
                    <entry>Chain file should contain a sequence of PEM (base64) encoded X.509
                      certificates ordered from leaf to and including the intermediate certificate
                      authorities.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Unable to read private key file &lt;Path>. &lt;Error></codeph>
                    </entry>
                    <entry><codeph>&lt;Error></codeph> is one of the file read errors. </entry>
                    <entry>Make sure that you have copied an unencrypted version of the private key
                      file to the inbox folder on the Couchbase node.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Unable to read certificate chain file &lt;Path>. &lt;Error>
                    </codeph></entry>
                    <entry><codeph>&lt;Error></codeph> is one of the file read errors.</entry>
                    <entry>Make sure that you have copied an unencrypted version of the chain file to
                      the inbox folder on the Couchbase node.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Invalid private key type: &lt;Type></codeph></entry>
                    <entry>The private key has an unsupported header.</entry>
                    <entry>Make sure that you use a valid private key file.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Provided certificate doesn't match provided private
                      key</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>The certificate doesn't recognize the message signed with a private
                      key.</entry>
                    <entry>Be sure that you use a complete key pair</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Encrypted keys are not supported</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>The private key is encrypted.</entry>
                    <entry>Couchbase does not support encrypted keys. You should decrypt the private key
                      with OpenSSL before loading the certificate in Couchbase. </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Provided private key contains incorrect number of
                      entries</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>The private key is a chain of entries.</entry>
                    <entry>The private key file should contain a single key digest.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Malformed or unsupported private key format</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>The private key cannot be used.</entry>
                    <entry>Open the key file, and verify whether it is a valid private key. The
                      certificate file should be readable using <codeph>openssl</codeph>.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>File does not exist</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>The file is missing, does not exist.</entry>
                    <entry>Add the missing file.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>Missing permission for reading the file, or for searching one of the
                      parent directories</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>You don't have the proper permissions to read the file or to search its
                      parent directories.</entry>
                    <entry>Change the permissions to allow you to read the file.</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </p>
          
      </sectiondiv>     
      
      
    </section>
  
      
  </body>
</topic>
