<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_auth_for_admins">
 
 <title>
  RBAC for Administrators and Applications
 </title>
 
 <shortdesc>
  The Couchbase <i>Role-Based Access Control</i> (RBAC) system allows a <i>full</i> administrator to specify, 
  with fine granularity, the access-rights of other administrators, and of applications; so restricting
  their activities to appropriately assigned areas. This section provides an introduction both to Couchbase
  RBAC and to the user-interface whereby users and roles are defined.
 </shortdesc>
 
 <body>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Authorization for Full Administrators
   </title>
   
   <p>
    The administrator who initially performs installation and configuration of Couchbase
    Server is granted full read-write access to the entire system, by default. The user ID of this
    administrator can be either locally specified, or <i>remotely</i>, by means of LDAP.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Once basic system-configuration has been completed, the initial, <i>full</i> administrator
    is free to add additional administrators to the system, and control their 
    system-access by means of Couchbase-defined <i>roles</i>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Adding Users
   </title>
   
   <p>
    As full administrator, to add <i>users</i> (each of which might be either an <i>administrator</i> or
    an <i>application</i>, or both) to Couchbase Server,
    use the Couchbase Web Console.
    Access the <uicontrol>Dashboard</uicontrol>, and left-click on the <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> tab, on the
    vertical navigation-bar, at the left. This brings up the <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> view, as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/securityView.png" id="security_view" align="left" width="820"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> view, appearing by default with the <uicontrol>Users</uicontrol> tab
    selected, on the upper horizontal control-bar, allows users to be defined, and roles to be allocated to them. 
    (With other tabs selected, it also
    allows management of the <uicontrol>Root Certificate</uicontrol>, and of <uicontrol>Audit</uicontrol>-processing.)
    Towards the upper-left, the statement <uicontrol>authentication Not enabled</uicontrol> appears. This refers
    to the possibility of performing <xref href="./security-ldap-new.dita" scope="local" format="dita">LDAP-Based
    Authentication</xref>. If some users are to be authenticated by means of a network-available server, accessed
    by means of LDAP, left-click on the interactive <uicontrol>enable</uicontrol> tab. The display now appears as
    follows.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/authenticationEnabled.png" id="authentication_enabled" align="left" width="220"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    To add a user, left-click on the <uicontrol>+ Add User</uicontrol> control, at the upper right. The <uicontrol>+ Add
    User</uicontrol> dialog now appears:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/newManageUserInitialWithLDAP.png" id="manage_user_new" align="left" width="300"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    The <uicontrol>Authentication Source</uicontrol> panel features two checkboxes: one specifying 
    <uicontrol>LDAP</uicontrol>, the other <uicontrol>Couchbase</uicontrol>. By default,
    <uicontrol>LDAP</uicontrol> is checked: this means that no user-password need be specified on
    the current dialog. To define a user locally, check the <uicontrol>Couchbase</uicontrol> checkbox. The dialog
    now appears as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/newManageUserInitialWithCouchbase.png" id="manage_user_new_with_pwd_field" align="left" width="300"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    A password-field has been added, allowing definition of a local user. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Add appropriate entries into the <uicontrol>Username</uicontrol> 
    and <uicontrol>Password</uicontrol> fields. The
    <uicontrol>Full Name</uicontrol> field may be left blank. 
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Adding Roles
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Next, examine the
    <uicontrol>Role(s)</uicontrol> panel. This displays a list of roles, selectable by means of
    checkboxes. Note that checkboxes are arranged in a hierarchy. Some of those initially visible
    allow assignment of roles with extensive privileges (for example, <uicontrol>Admin</uicontrol>, 
    which provides read-write access
    on all Couchbase Server administrative features). Other checkboxes exist at lower levels, and are
    accessed by left-clicking on arrowheads: when you click, the adjacent header expands into a vertical
    list that contains additional checkboxes and, in some cases, arrowheads with lower-level headers. You
    can work downwards through the hierarchy, repeatedly left-clicking on arrowheads, to expand all available
    lists; and thereby inspect all the available roles.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Some roles are considered to be <i>subsets</i> of others. In such cases, manually checking one checkbox
    may cause the automated checking of others &#8212; indicating that the corresponding roles are also
    assigned to the user.
    To demonstrate this, left-click on the <uicontrol>Admin</uicontrol> checkbox. The <uicontrol>Roles</uicontrol>
    panel now appears as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/rolesPanelAdminChecked.png" id="roles_panel_admin_checked" align="left" width="320"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Selecting the <uicontrol>Admin</uicontrol> role caused other roles
    also to become checked: <uicontrol>Read Only Admin</uicontrol>, <uicontrol>Cluster Admin</uicontrol>, and
   <uicontrol>Replication Admin</uicontrol>. This is because <uicontrol>Admin</uicontrol> stands at the top of the
    hierarchy, and is a superset of all other roles. 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    To demonstrate this further, left-click on the arrowhead adjacent to <uicontrol>bucket Roles</uicontrol>, and then,
    when they become visible, on <uicontrol>Bucket Admin</uicontrol> and <uicontrol>Bucket Full Access</uicontrol>. 
    The <uicontrol>Role(s)</uicontrol> pane now appears
    as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/rolesWithFullAdminAndBucketsOpen.png" id="roles_with_full_admin_and_buckets_open" align="left" width="320"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    All roles contained under <uicontrol>Bucket Admin</uicontrol> and <uicontrol>Bucket Full Access</uicontrol>, permitting
    read-write access to administrative and production bucket-data respectively, are checked; since they fall, hierarchically,
    under <uicontrol>Admin</uicontrol>.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Now, uncheck <uicontrol>Admin</uicontrol>, and check <uicontrol>Read Only Admin</uicontrol>. The <uicontrol>Role(s)</uicontrol>
    pane now appears as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/rolesWithReadOnlyAdminAndBucketsOpen.png" id="roles_with_read_only_admin_and_buckets_open" align="left" width="320"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    This demonstrates that the <uicontrol>Bucket Admin</uicontrol> and <uicontrol>Bucket Full Access</uicontrol> roles do not fall under
    <uicontrol>Read Only Admin</uicontrol>; and so do not become available when <uicontrol>Read Only Admin</uicontrol> is checked. This is
    because both <uicontrol>Bucket Admin</uicontrol> and <uicontrol>Bucket Full Access</uicontrol> require <i>write</i> as well as <i>read</i>
    permission.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    You can, however, give read-write permission selectively to a user who more generally is restricted to read-only access, or
    who otherwise has no access whatsoever. For example, you might give read-write permission on a single bucket.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/travelSampleReaderWriterRole.png" id="travel_sample_reader_writer_role" align="left" width="260"/> 
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Saving and Making Changes
   </title>
   
   <p>
    Whenever you have finished allocating roles for a particular user, left-click on <uicontrol>Save</uicontrol>. 
    The <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> view
    now displays the roles you have allocated on the row of the corresponding <uicontrol>Username</uicontrol>. For example, if you
    have allocated <codeph>Read Only Admin</codeph> and <codeph>Data Reader Writer [travel-sample]</codeph>, the view is as
    follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/securityViewWithNewUser.png" id="security_view_with_new_user" align="left" width="820"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Note that by left-clicking within the row, you display options for editing:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/securityViewWithEditOptions.png" id="security_view_with_edit_options" align="left" width="820"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    By left-clicking on <uicontrol>Delete</uicontrol>, you delete the user. By left-clicking on <uicontrol>Edit</uicontrol>,
    you return to the <uicontrol>Manage User > testUser </uicontrol> dialog, with the options to redefine username, full name,
    and roles. The <uicontrol>Reset Password</uicontrol> button only appears when the selected user is <i>locally</i>
    defined, rather than through LDAP. Left-clicking on the button brings up a dialog that allows redefinition of
    the user's password:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/resetPassword.png" id="reset_password" align="left" width="300"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Note also that by left-clicking on a role, displayed in the <uicontrol>Role</uicontrol> column, you display
    a tool-tip, which provides information on the role's significance:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/roleToolTip.png" id="role_tool_tip" align="left" width="740"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    For a complete account of the roles you can allocate and their significance, see 
    <xref href="./security-roles-used-in-access-control.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Roles Used in Access Control</xref>.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   
   <title>
    Role-Based Console Appearance
   </title>
   
   <p>
    An administrator's roles determine which administrative features are available to them. Non-available
    features are not displayed by Couchbase Web Console; 
    therefore, the console's appearance changes, based on which roles have been assigned to the current 
    administrator.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    This can be demonstrated with reference to the role
    <i>Cluster Admin</i>, which is assigned as follows by means of the <uicontrol>Manage User</uicontrol>
    dialog. Note that when the <codeph>Cluster Admin</codeph> checkbox is manually checked, the checkboxes
    for all other roles that are each considered a subset of <i>Cluster Admin</i> are themselves automatically
    checked.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/clusterAdminRoleSelection.png" id="cluster_admin_role_selection" align="left" width="220"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    When a user defined in this way logs into the Couchbase Web Console, the console's appearance 
    is as follows:
   </p>
   
   <p>
    <image href="./pict/dashboardInitialForClusterAdmin.png" id="dashboard_initial_for_cluster_admin" align="left" width="820"/> 
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Note that the <uicontrol>Security</uicontrol> option has been removed from the vertical navigation-bar, at the left; since
    the <i>Cluster Admin</i> role does not feature the privilege of reading or writing security-related data.
   </p>
   
   <p>
    Other roles and role-combinations restrict feature-access in similar ways, and in consequence, produce different 
    console-appearances
    for differently defined users.
   </p>
   
  </section>
  
 </body>
 
</topic>
