<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_jzr_ct2_gv">
  
  <title>
    Password-Based Authentication
  </title>
  
  <shortdesc>
    To access Couchbase Server, administrators <i>must</i> authenticate. Applications
    <i>may</i> be required to authenticate, when accessing particular buckets.
    Authentication is password-based, for both administrators
    and applications. For additional security, applications can be designed to use 
    passwords in hash-based challenge-response routines.
  </shortdesc>
  
  <body>
    
    <section>
      
      <title>
        Authentication for Administrators 
      </title>
     
      <p> 
        Administrator usernames and passwords, both required for authentication, are initially established during installation of
        Couchbase Server: see 
        <xref href="../install/init-setup.dita#topic12527/setpass">Configure Server</xref> 
        for details. Subsequently, passwords can be changed by means of the
        password-reset tool,
        <xref href="../cli/cbreset_password-tool.dita#cbreset_password_tool"/>
      </p>
        
      <p>
        Best practices for password-definition are 
        listed in the section 
        <xref href="security-passwords.dita#topic_iyx_5ps_lq">Couchbase passwords</xref>. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        When the Couchbase Web Console is running on the default port, <codeph>http://localhost:8091</codeph>,
        the administrator's username and password are passed in the clear, from the administrator's browser
        to the console. Optionally, Couchbase Web Console can be configured for <i>secure access</i>, at
        <codeph>https://localhost:18091</codeph>; so that the username and password are passed in
        encrypted form. For information, see
        <xref href="./security-comm-encryption.dita" scope="local" format="dita">Encryption On the Wire</xref>.
      </p>
        
    </section> 
    
    <section id="standardport">
      <title>
        Authentication for Applications
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Buckets can be password-protected. To
        access password-protected buckets, applications must authenticate, using one of three
        mechanisms provided  by the <i>Simple Authentication 
        and Security Layer</i> (SASL) framework: PLAIN, CRAM-MD5, and SCRAM-MD5. The CRAM-MD5 and
        SCRAM-MD5 mechanisms allow
        applications to authenticate securely, by transmitting the password only in <i>protected form</i>.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Note that <i>default buckets</i>, provided with Couchbase Server for demonstration
        and test purposes, are not password-protected. 
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Configuring Access-Control
      </title>
      
      <p>
        Access-control is configured on a bucket by means of the Couchbase Web Console, using the
        <uicontrol>Create New Data Bucket</uicontrol> option. Access-control
        can be set for either of two ports:
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <image href="../images/admin-access-control.png" align="left" width="600"/>
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>
          <i>Standard port</i>: Port <codeph>11211</codeph>, which requires SASL
          authentication. This requires establishment of a password, which should comply
          with best-practice rules.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <i>Dedicated port</i>: The port-number is administrator-defined. ASCII protocol is supported,
          and authentication is not required. 
          
          <p>
            Note that server-side <i>moxi</i> proxy is deprecated in Couchbase
            Server version 4.5 and above.  For application-design, either use the Couchbase SDK or client-side moxi. 
          </p>
          
          <p>
            
            <!-- Vertical space -->
            
          </p>
          
        </li>
      </ul>
      
    </section>  
    
    <section>
      <title>
        Password Authentication-Mechanisms
      </title>
      
      <p>
        In ascending order of strength, the password authentication-mechanisms are as follows:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        
        <li>
          <i>PLAIN</i>: The client sends the password in unencrypted form. All
          clients support this authentication-method. It is insecure, providing no defence against
          passwords being stolen in tranmission.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <i>CRAM-MD5</i>: The <i>Challenge Response Authentication Mechanism</i>,
          which uses an MD5 cryptographic hash-algorithm to protect the password during authentication-exchange.
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <i>SCRAM-SHA</i>: The <i>Salted Challenge Response Authentication Mechanism</i>,
          which both protects the password during authentication-exchange, and also verifies the
          server's identity to the application.
          
          <p>
            Couchbase supports the SHA-1 hash function for SCRAM, in compliance with the SCRAM RFC. 
            As a security best practice, use SCRAM with TLS; to improve authentication-security further.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            Note that drivers may need to be upgraded to versions that support SCRAM-SHA.
            The minimum-required driver-versions are: 
          </p>
          
          <p>
            <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_bd2_w5f_qv">
              <title>Driver requirements for SCRAM-SHA authentication </title>
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.04*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="3.54*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Couchbase Client</entry>
                    <entry>Version</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Java</entry>
                    <entry>2.2.5 and higher</entry>
                    <entry>Supports SCRAM without any code changes.</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
            
          </p>
          
          <p>
            <!-- Vertical space -->
          </p>
          
        </li>
        
      </ul>
      
      <p>
        During initial
        client-server negotiation, the strongest protocol supported by both Couchbase Server and the
        application's client OS is selected for use. 
        For example, if the client supports only the PLAIN protocol, the PLAIN protocol is used; but
        if the client also supports the CRAM-MD5 protocol, then CRAM-MD5 is used.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        A challenge-response method can be transmitted through both encrypted and unencrypted channels. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Note that the challenge-response protocols CRAM-MD5 and SCRAM-MD5 only 
        authenticate the process of password-validation. To secure the subsequent session, TLS should be used.
      </p>
    
    </section>
      
  </body>
</topic>
